The Preface of the Author to His Son, Faustinus
and Unto the Readers of This Book

That I to thee some joyous jests
may show in gentle glose,
And frankly feed thy bended ears
with passing pleasant prose:
So that thou deign in seemly sort
this wanton book to view,
That is set out and garnished fine,
with written phrases new.
I will declare how one by hap
his human figure lost,
And how in brutish formed shape
his loathed life he tossed.
And how he was in course of time
from such a state unfold,
Who eftsoons turn’d to pristine shape,
his lot unlucky told.

What and who he was attend a while, and you shall understand that it was even I, the writer of mine own Metamorphosie and strange alteration of figure. Hymettus, Athens, Isthmia, Ephire, Tenaros, and Sparta, being fat and fertile soils (as I pray you give credit to the books of more everlasting fame) be places where mine ancient progeny and lineage did sometime flourish: there I say, in Athens, when I was young, I went first to school. Soon after (as a stranger) I arrived at Rome, whereas by great industry, and without instruction of any schoolmaster, I attained to the full perfection of the Latin tongue. Behold, I first crave and beg your pardon, lest I should happen to displease or offend any of you by the rude and rustic utterance of this strange and foreign language. And verily this new alteration of speech doth correspond to the enterprised matter whereof I purpose to entreat, I will set forth unto you a pleasant Grecian feast. Whereunto gentle reader if thou wilt give attendant ear, it will minister unto thee such delectable matter as thou shalt be contented withal.

The Second Chapter

How Apuleius told to the strangers, what he saw a juggler do in Athens.

The other night being at supper with a sort of hungry fellowes, while I did greedily put a great morsel of meat in my mouth, that was fried with the flower of cheese and barley, it cleaved so fast in the passage of my throat and stopped my wind in such sort that I was well-nigh choked. And yet at Athens before the porch there called Peale, I saw with these eyes a juggler that swallowed up a two hand sword, with a very keen edge, and by and by for a little money that we who looked on gave him, he devoured a chasing spear with the point downward. And after that he had conveyed the whole spear within the closure of his body, and brought it out again behind, there appeared on the top thereof (which caused us all to marvel) a fair boy pleasant and nimble, winding and turning himself in such sort, that you would suppose he had neither bone nor gristle, and verily think that he were the natural Serpent, creeping and sliding on the knotted staff, which the god of Medicine is feigned to bear. But turning me to him that began his tale, I pray you (quoth I) follow your purpose, and I alone will give credit unto you, and for your pains will pay your charges at the next Inne we come unto. To whom he answered Certes sir I thank you for your gentle offer, and at your request I will proceed in my tale, but first I will swear unto you by the light of this Sun that shineth here, that those things shall be true, least when you come to the next city called Thessaly, you should doubt anything of that which is rife in the mouthes of every person, and done before the face of all men. And that I may first make relation to you, what and who I am, and whither I go, and for what purpose, know you that I am of Egin, travelling these countries about from Thessaly to Etolia, and from Etolia to Boetia, to provide for honey, cheese, and other victuals to sell again: and understanding that at Hippata (which is the principal city of all Thessaly), is accustomed to be sold new cheeses of exceeding good taste and relish, I fortuned on a day to go thither, to make my market there: but as it often happeneth, I came in an evil hour; for one Lupus a purveyor had bought and engrossed up all the day before, and so I was deceived.

Wherefore towards night being very weary, I went to the Baines to refresh myself, and behold, I fortuned to espy my companion Socrates sitting upon the ground, covered with a torn and course mantle; who was so meagre and of so sallow and miserable a countenance, that I scantly knew him: for fortune had brought him into such estate and calamity, that he verily seemed as a common begger that standeth in the streets to crave the benevolence of the passersby. Towards whom (howbeit he was my singular friend and familiar acquaintance, yet half in despair) I drew nigh and said, Alas my Socrates, what meaneth this? how fareth it with thee? What crime hast thou committed? verily there is great lamentation and weeping for thee at home: Thy children are in ward by decree of the Provincial Judge: Thy wife (having ended her mourning time in lamentable wise, with face and visage blubbered with tears, in such sort that she hath well-nigh wept out both her eyes) is constrained by her parents to put out of remembrance the unfortunate lose and lacke of thee at home, and against her will to take a new husband. And dost thou live here as a ghost or hogge, to our great shame and ignominy?

Then he answered he to me and said, Oh my friend Aristomenus, now perceive I well that you are ignorant of the whirling changes, the unstable forces, and slippery inconstancy of Fortune: and therewithal he covered his face (even then blushing for very shame) with his rugged mantle insomuch that from his navel downwards he appeared all naked.

But I not willing to see him any longer in such great miserie and calamity, took him by the hand and lifted him up from the ground: who having his face covered in such sort, Let Fortune (quoth he) triumph yet more, let her have her sway, and finish that which she hath begun. And therewithal I put off one of my garments and covered him, and immediately I brought him to the Baine, and caused him to be anointed, wiped, and the filthy scurf of his body to be rubbed away; which done, though I were very weary myself, yet I led the poor miser to my Inne, where he reposed his body upon a bed, and then I brought him meat and drinke, and so we talked together: for there we might be merry and laugh at our pleasure, and so we were, until such time as he (fetching a pitiful sigh from the bottom of his heart, and beating his face in miserable sort), began to say.

The Third Chapter

How Socrates in his returne from Macedony to Larissa was spoyled and robbed, and how he fell acquainted with one Meroe a Witch.

Alas poore miser that I am, that for the onely desire to see a game of triall of weapons, am fallen into these miseries and wretched snares of misfortune. For in my returne from Macedonie, wheras I sould all my wares, and played the Merchant by the space of ten months, a little before that I came to Larissa, I turned out of the way, to view the scituation of the countrey there, and behold in the bottom of a deep valley I was suddenly environed with a company of theeves, who robbed and spoiled me of such things as I had, and yet would hardly suffer me to escape. But I beeing in such extremity, in the end was happily delivered from their hands, and so I fortuned to come to the house of an old woman that sold wine, called Meroe, who had her tongue sufficiently instructed to flattery: unto whom I opened the causes of my long peregrination and careful travell, and of myne unlucky adventure: and after that I had declared to her such things as then presently came to my remembrance, she gently entertained me and made me good cheere; and by and by being pricked with carnall desire, she brought me to her own bed chamber; whereas I poore miser the very first night of our lying together did purchase to myself this miserable face, and for her lodging I gave to her such apparel as the theeves left to cover me withall.

Then I understanding the cause of his miserable estate, sayd unto him, In faith thou art worthy to sustaine the most extreame misery and calamity, which hast defiled and maculated thyne owne body, forsaken thy wife traitorously, and dishonoured thy children, parents, and friends, for the love of a vile harlot and old strumpet. When Socrates heard me raile against Meroe in such sort, he held up his finger to me, and as halfe abashed sayd, Peace peace I pray you, and looking about lest anybody should heare, I pray you (quoth he) I pray you take heed what you say against so venerable a woman as she is, lest by your intemperate tongue you catch some harm. Then with resemblance of admiration, What (quoth I) is she so excellent a person as you name her to be? I pray you tell me. Then answered he, Verily she is a Magitian, which hath power to rule the heavens, to bringe down the sky, to beare up the earth, to turne the waters into hills and the hills into running waters, to lift up the terrestrial spirits into the aire, and to pull the gods out of the heavens, to extinguish the planets, and to lighten the deepe darknesse of hell. Then sayd I unto Socrates, Leave off this high and mysticall kinde of talke, and tell the matter in a more plaine and simple fashion. Then answered he, Will you hear one or two, or more of her facts which she hath done, for whereas she enforceth not onely the inhabitants of the countrey here, but also the Indians and the Ethiopians the one and the other, and also the Antictons, to love her in most raging sort, such as are but trifles and chips of her occupation, but I pray you give eare, and I will declare of more greater matters, which she hath done openly and before the face of all men.

The Fifth Chapter

How Socrates and Aristomenus slept together in one Chamber, and how they were handled by Witches.

In speaking these words, and devising with myself of our departing the next morrow, lest Meroe the witch should play by us as she had done by diverse other persons, it fortuned that Socrates did fall asleepe, and slept very soundly, by reason of his travel and plenty of meat and wine wherewithall he had filled himself. Wherefore I closed and barred fast the doors of the chamber, and put my bed behinde the door, and so layed me down to rest. But I could in no wise sleepe, for the great feare which was in my heart, untill it was about midnight, and then I began to slumber. But alas, behold suddenly the chamber doors brake open, and locks, bolts, and posts fell down, that you would verily have thought that some Theeves had been presently come to have spoiled and robbed us. And my bed whereon I lay being a truckle bed, fashioned in form of a Cradle, and one of the feet broken and rotten, by violence was turned upside down, and I likewise was overwhelmed and covered lying in the same. Then perceived I in myself, that certain affects of the mind by nature doth chance contrary. For as tears oftentimes trickle down the cheekes of him that seeth or heareth some joyfull newes, so I being in this fearfull perplexity, could not forbear laughing, to see how of Aristomenus I was made like unto a snail [in] his shell. And while I lay on the ground covered in this sort, I peeped under the bed to see what would happen. And behold there entred in two old women, the one bearing a burning torch, and the other a sponge and a naked sword; and so in this habit they stood about Socrates being fast asleep. Then she which bare the sword said unto the other, Behold sister Panthia, this is my deare and sweet heart, which both day and night hath abused my wanton youthfulness. This is he, who little regarding my love, doth not only defame me with reproachfull words, but also intendeth to run away. And I shall be forsaken by like craft as Ulysses did use, and shall continually bewaile my solitariness as Calipso. Which said, she pointed towards me that lay under the bed, and showed me to Panthia. This is he, quoth she, which is his Counsellor, and persuadeth him to forsake me, and now being at the point of death he lieth prostrate on the ground covered with his bed, and hath seene all our doings, and hopeth to escape scot-free from my hands, but I will cause that he will repente himself too late, nay rather forthwith, of his former intemperate language, and his present curiosity. Which words when I heard I fell into a cold sweat, and my heart trembled with feare, insomuch that the bed over me did likewise rattle and shake. Then spake Panthia unto Meroe and said, Sister let us by and by tear him in pieces or tye him by the members, and so cut them off. Then Meroe (being so named because she was a Taverner, and loved wel good wines) answered, Nay rather let him live, and bury the corpse of this poore wretch in some hole of the earth; and therewithall she turned the head of Socrates on the other side and thrust her sword up to the hilts into the left part of his necke, and received the bloud that gushed out, into a pot, that no drop thereof fell beside: which things I saw with mine own eyes, and as I think to the intent that she might alter nothing that pertained to sacrifice, which she accustomed to make, she thrust her hand down into the intrals of his body, and searching about, at length brought forth the heart of my miserable companion Socrates, who having his throat cut in such sort, yeelded out a dolefull cry, and gave up the ghost. Then Panthia stopped up the wide wound of his throat with the Sponge and said, O sponge sprung and made of the sea, beware that thou not pass by running river. This being said, one of them moved and turned up my bed, and then they strid over me, and clapped their buttocks upon my face, and all bepissed me until I was wringing wet. When this was over they went their wayes, and the doors closed fast, the posts stood in their old places, and the lockes and bolts were shut again. But I that lay upon the ground like one without soule, naked and cold, and wringing wet with pisse, like to one that were more than half dead, yet reviving myself, and appointed as I thought for the Gallowes, began to say Alasse what shall become of me to morrow, when my companion shall be found murthered here in the chamber? To whom shall I seeme to tell any similitude of truth, when as I shall tell the trueth in deed? They will say, If thou wert unable to resist the violence of the women, yet shouldest thou have cried for help; Wouldst thou suffer the man to be slain before thy face and say nothing? Or why did they not slay thee likewise? Why did they spare thee that stood by and saw them commit that horrible fact? Wherefore although thou hast escaped their hands, yet thou shalt not escape ours. While I pondered these things with myself the night passed on, and so I resolved to take my horse before day, and go forward on my journey.

Howbeit the wayes were unknown to me, and thereupon I took up my packet, unlocked and unbarred the doors, but those good and faithfull doors which in the night did open of their own accord, could then scantly be opened with their keyes. And when I was out I cried, O sirrah Hostler where art thou? Open the stable door for I will ride away by and by. The Hostler lying behinde the stable door upon a pallet, and half asleepe, What (quoth he) do you not know that the wayes be very dangerous? What mean you to rise at this time of night? If you perhaps guilty of some heynous crime, be weary of your life, yet think you not that we are such Sots that we will die for you. Then said I, It is well nigh day, and moreover, what can theeves take from him that hath nothing? Doest thou not know (Foole as thou art) if thou be naked, if ten giants should assaile thee, they could not spoil or rob thee? Whereunto the drowsie Hostler half asleepe, and turning on the other side, answered, What know I whether you have murthered your Companion whom you brought in yesternight, or no, and now seeke the means to escape away? O Lord, at that time I remember the earth seemed ready to open, and me thought I saw at hell gate the Dog Cerberus ready to devour me, and then I verily beleeved, that Meroe did not spare my throat, moved with pity, but rather cruelly pardoned me to bring me to the Gallowes. Wherefore I returned to my chamber, and there devised with myself in what sort I should finish my life. But when I saw that fortune should minister unto me no other instrument than that which my bed profered me, I said, O bed, O bed, most dear to me at this present, which hast abode and suffered with me so many miseries, judge and arbiter of such things as were done here this night, whom only I may call to witness for my innocency, render (I say) unto me some wholesome weapon to end my life, that am most willing to dye. And therewithal I pulled out a piece of the rope wherewith the bed was corded, and tied one end thereof about a rafter by the window, and with the other end I made a sliding knot, and stood upon my bed, and so put my neck into it, and leaped from the bed, thinking to strangle myself and so dye, behold the ropebeing old and rotten burst in the middle, and I fell down tumbling upon Socrates that lay under: And even at that same very time the Hostler came in crying with a loud voice, and said, Where are you that made such hast at midnight, and now lies wallowing abed? Whereupon (I know not whether it was by my fall, or by the great cry of the Hostler) Socrates as waking out of sleepe, did rise up first and said, It is not without cause that strangers do speake evill of all such Hostlers, for this Catife in his comming in, and with his crying out, I think under a colour to steale away something, hath waked me out of a sound sleepe. Then I rose up joyfull with a merry countenance, saying, Behold good Hostler, my friend, my companion and my brother, whom thou didst falsly affirme to be slain by me this might. And therewithall I embraced my friend Socrates and kissed him: but he smelling the stinke of the pisse wherewith those Hagges had embrued me, thrust me away and said, Clense thyself from this filthy odour, and then he began gently to enquire, how that noysome sent hapned unto me. But I finely feigning and colouring the matter for the time, did breake off his talk, and took him by the hand and said, Why tarry we? Why lose we the pleasure of this fair morning? Let us go, and so I took up my packet, and payed the charges of the house and departed: and we had not gone a mile out of the Town but it was broad day, and then I diligently looked upon Socrates throat, to see if I could espy the place where Meroe thrust in her sword: but when I could not perceive any such thing, I thought with myself, What a mad man am I, that being overcome with wine yester night, have dreamed such terrible things? Behold I see Socrates is sound, safe and in health. Where is his wound? Where is the Sponge? Where is his great and new cut? And then I spake to him and said, Verily it is not without occasion, that Physitians of experience do affirme, That such as fill their gorges abundantly with meat and drinke, shall dreame of dire and horrible sights: for I myself, not tempering my appetite yester night from the pots of wine, did seeme to see this night strange and cruel visions, that even yet I think myself sprinkled and wet with human blood: whereunto Socrates laughing made answer and said, Nay, thou art not wet with the blood of men, but art embrued with stinking pisse; and verily I dreamed that my throat was cut, and that I felt the pain of the wound, and that my heart was pulled out of my belly, and the remembrance thereof makes me now to feare, for my knees do so tremble that I can scarce go any further, and therefore I would faine eat somewhat to strengthen and revive my spirits. Then said I, behold here thy breakefast, and therewithall I opened my script that hanged upon my shoulder, and gave him bread and cheese, and we sat down under a greate Plane tree, and I eat part with him; and while I beheld him eating greedily, I perceived that he waxed meigre and pale, and that his lively colour faded away, insomuch thatbeing in great fear, and remembring those terrible furies of whom I lately dreamed, the first morsell of bread that I put in my mouth (that was but very small) did so stick in my jawes, that I could neither swallow it down, nor yet yeeld it up, and moreover the small time of our being together increased my feare, and what is he that seeing his companion die in the highway before his face, would not greatly lament and be sorry? But when that Socrates had eaten sufficiently he waxed very thirsty, for indeed he had well nigh devoured a whole Cheese: and behold evill fortune! There was behind the Plane tree a pleasant running water as cleere as Crystal, and I said unto him, Come hither Socrates to this water and drinke thy fill. And then he rose and came to the River, and kneeled down on the side of the banke to drinke, but he had scarce touched the water with lips, when as behold the wound in his throat opened wide, and the Sponge suddenly fell out into the water, and after issued out a little remnant of bloud, and his body being then without life, had fallen into the river, had not I caught him by the leg and so pulled him up. And after that I had lamented a good space the death of my wretched companion, I buried him in the Sands there by the river.

Which done, in great feare I rode through many Outwayes and desart places, and as culpable of the death of Socrates, I forsooke my country, my wife, and my children, and came to Etolia where I married another Wife.

This tale told Aristomenus, and his fellow which before obstinatly would give no credit unto him, began to say, Verily there was never so foolish a tale, nor a more absurd lie told than this. And then he spake unto me saying, Ho sir, what you are I know not, but your habit and countenance declareth that you should be some honest Gentleman, (speaking to Apuleius) do you beleeve this tale? Yea verily (quoth I), why not? For whatsoever the fates have appointed to men, that I beleeve shall happen. For may things chance unto me and unto you, and to diverse others, whichbeing declared unto the ignorant be accounted as lies. But verily I give credit unto his tale, and render entire thankes unto him, in that by the pleasant relation thereof we have quickly passed and shortned our journey, and I think that my horse was also delighted with the same, and hath brought me to the gate of this city without any pain at all. Thus ended both our talk and our journey, for they two turned on the left hand to the next villages, and I rode into the city.

The Sixth Chapter

How Apuleius came unto a city named Hipate, and was lodged in one Milo’s house, and brought him letters from one Demeas of Corinth.

After that those two Companions were departed I entred into the City: where I espied an old woman, of whom I inquired whether that city was called Hipata, or no: Who answered, Yes. Then I demanded, Whether she knew one Milo an Alderman of the city: Whereat she laughed and said: Verily it is not without cause that Milo is called an Elderman, and accounted as chief of those which dwell without the walls of the City. To whom I said again, I pray thee good mother do not mock, but tell me what manner of man he is, and where he dwelleth. Mary (quoth she) do you see these Bay windows, which on one side abut to the gates of the city, and on the other side to the next lane? There Milo dwelleth, very rich both in money and substance, but by reason of his great avarice and insatiable covetousness, he is evil spoken of, and he is a man that liveth all by usury, and lending his money upon pledges. Moreover he dwelleth in a small house, and is ever counting his money, and hath a wife that is a companion of his extreme misery, neither keepeth he more in his house than only one maid, who goeth apparelled like unto a beggar. Which when I heard, I laughed in myself and thought, In faith my friend Demeas hath served me well, which hath sent me being a stranger, unto such a man, in whose house I shall not be afeared either of smoke or of the scent of meat; and therewithal I rode to the door, which was fast barred, and knocked aloud. Then there came forth a maid which said, Ho sirrah that knocks so fast, in what kind of sort will you borrow money? Know you not that we use to take no gage, unless it be either plate or Jewels? To whom I answered, I pray you maid speak more gently, and tell me whether thy master be within or no? Yes (quoth she) that he is, why do you ask? Mary (said I) I am come from Corinth, and have brought him letters from Demeas his friend. Then said the Maid, I pray you tarry here till I tell him so, and therewithal she closed fast the door, and went in, and after a while she returned again and said, My master desireth you to alight and come in. And so I did, whereas I found him sitting upon a little bed, going to supper, and his wife sat at his feet, but there was no meat upon the table, and so by appointment of the maid I came to him and saluted him, and delivered the letters which I had brought from Demeas. Which when he had read he said, Verily, I thank my friend Demeas much, in that he hath sent me so worthy a guest as you are. And therewithal he commanded his wife to sit away and bid me sit in her place; which when I refused by reason of courtesy, he pulled me by my garment and willed me to sit down; for we have (quoth he) no other stool here, nor no other great store of household stuff, for fear of robbing. Then I according to his commandment, sat down, and he fell in further communication with me and said, Verily I do conjecture by the comely feature of your body, and by the maidenly shamefastness of your face that you are a Gentleman borne, as my friend Demeas hath no less declared the same in his letters. Wherefore I pray you take in good part our poor lodging, and behold yonder chamber is at your commandment, use it as your own, and if you be contented therewithal, you shall resemble and follow the virtuous qualities of your good father Theseus, who disdained not the slender and poor Cottage of Hecate.

And then he called his maid which was named Fotis, and said, Carry this Gentleman’s packet into the chamber, and lay it up safely, and bring water quickly to wash him, and a towel to rub him, and other things necessary, and then bring him to the next Baines, for I know that he is very weary of travel.

These things when I heard, I partly perceived the manners of Milo, and endeavouring to bring myself further into his favour, I said, Sir there is no need of any of these things, for they have been everywhere ministered unto me by the way, howbeit I will go into the Baines, but my chiefest care is that my horse be well looked to, for he brought me hither roundly, and therefore I pray thee Fotis take this money and buy some hay and oats for him.

The Seventh Chapter

How Apuleius going to buy fish, met with his companion Pythias.

When this was done, and all my things brought into the Chamber, I walked towards the Baines; but first I went to the market to buy some victuals for my supper, whereas I saw great plenty of fish set out to be sould: and so I cheapened part thereof, and that which they at first held at an hundred pence, I bought at length for twenty. Which when I had done, and was departing away, one of mine old acquaintance, and fellow at Athens, named Pithias, fortuned to pass by, and viewing me at a good space, in the end brought me to his remembrance, and gently came and kissed me, saying, O my deare friend Lucius, it is a great while past since we two saw one another, and moreover, from the time that we departed from our Master Vestius, I never heard any newes from you. I pray you Lucius tell me the cause of your peregrination hither. Then I answered and said, I will make relation thereof unto you tomorrow: but I pray you tell me, what meaneth these servitors that follow you, and these rods or verges which they bear, and this habit which you wear like unto a magistrate, verily I think you have obtained your own desire, whereof I am right glad. Then answered Pithias, I bear the office of the Clerke of the market, and therfore if you will have any pittance for your supper speake and I will purvey it for you. Then I thanked him heartily and said I had bought meat sufficient already. But Pithias when he espied my basket wherein my fish was, took it and shaked it, and demanded of me what I had paid for all my Sprots. In faith (quoth I), I could scarce inforce the fishmonger to sell them for twenty pence. Which when I heard, he brought me back again into the market, and enquired of me of whom I bought them. I showed him the old man which sat in a corner, whom by and by, by reason of his office, he did greatly blame, and said, Is it thus you serve and handle strangers, and specially our friends? Wherefore sell you this fish so deare, which is not worth a halfepenny? Now perceive I well, that you are an occasion to make this place, which is the principall city of all Thessaly, to be forsaken of all men, and to reduce it into an uninhabitable Desart, by reasone of your excessive prices of victuals, but assure yourself that you shall not escape without punishment, and you shall know what mine office is, and how I ought to punish such as offend. Then he took my basket and cast the fish on the ground, and commanded one of his Sergeants to tread them under his feet. This done he persuaded me to depart, and said that only shame and reproach done unto the old Caitife did suffice him, So I went away amazed and astonied, towards the Baines, considering with myself and devising of the grace of my companion Pythias. Where when I had well washed and refreshed my body, I returned again to Milo’s house, both without money and meat, and so got into my chamber. Then came Fotis immediately unto me, and said that her master desired me to come to supper. But I not ignorant of Milo’s abstinence, prayed that I might be pardoned since as I thought best to ease my wearied bones rather with sleepe and quietnesse, than with meat. When Fotis had told this to Milo, he came himself and took me by the hand, and while I did modestly excuse myself, I will not (quoth he) depart from this place, until such time as you shall go with me: and to confirm the same, he bound his words with an oath, whereby he enforced me to follow him, and so he brought me into his chamber, where he sat him down upon the bed, and demaunded of me how his friend Demeas did, his wife, his children, and all his family: and I made answer to him every question, specially he enquired the causes of my peregrination and travel, which when I had declared, he yet busily demanded of the state of my Country, and the chief magistrates there, and principally of our Lievtenant and Viceroy; who when he perceived that I was not only wearied by travel, but also with talke, and that I fell asleep in the midst of my tale, and further that I spake nothing directly or advisedly, he suffered me to depart to my chamber. So scaped I at length from the prating and hungry supper of this rank old man, and being compelled by sleepe and not by meat, and having supped only with talke, I returned into my chamber, and there betook me to my quiet and long desired rest.

The Eighth Chapter

How Apuleius fortuned to meet with his Cousin Byrrhena.

As soon as night was past, and the day began to spring, I fortuned to awake, and rose out of my bed as halfe amazed, and very desirous to know and see some marvelous and strange things, remembering with myself that I was in the middle part of all Thessaly, whereas by the common report of all the World, the Sorceries and enchantments are most used, I oftentimes repeated with myself the tale of my companion Aristomenus touching the manner of this City, and being moved by great desire, I viewed the whole situation thereof, neither was there anything which I saw there, but that I did believe to be the same which it was indeed, but everything seemed unto me to be transformed and altered into other shapes, by the wicked power of Sorcerie and enchantment, insomuch that I thought that the stones which I found were indurate, and turned from men into that figure, and that the birds which I heard chirping, and the trees without the walls of the city, and the running waters, were changed from men into such kinde of likenesss. And further I thought that the Statues, Images and Walls could go, and the Oxen and other brute beasts could speake and tell strange news, and that immediately I should see and hear some Oracles from the heavens, and from the gleed of the Sun. Thus being astonied or rather dismayed and vexed with desire, knowing no certain place whither I intended to go, I went from street to street, and at length (as I curiously gazed on everything) I fortuned unwares to come into the market place, whereas I espied a certain woman, accompanied with a great many servants, towards whom I drew nigh, and viewed her garments beset with gold and pretious stone, in such sort that she seemed to be some noble matron. And there was an old man which followed her, who as soon as he espied me, said to himself, Verily this is Lucius, and then he came and embraced me, by and by he went unto his mistresse and whispered in her ear, and came to me again saying, How is it Lucius that you will not salute your deere Cousin and singular friend? To whom I answered, Sir I dare not be so bold as to take acquaintance of an unknown woman. Howbeit as halfe ashamed I drew towards her, and she turned herself and said, Behold how he resembleth the very same grace as his mother Salvia doth, behold his countenance and stature, agreeing thereto in each point, behold his comely state, his fine slenderness, his Vermilion colour, his hair yellow by nature, his gray and quicke eye, like to the Eagle, and his trim and comely gate, which do sufficiently prove him to be the natural childe of Salvia. And moreover she said, Oh Lucius, I have nourished thee with mine own proper hand: and why not? For I am not only of kindred to thy mother by blood, but also by nourice, for we both descended of the line of Plutarch, lay in one belly, sucked the same paps, and were brought up together in one house. And further there is no other difference betweene us two, but that she is married more honourably than I: I am the same Byrrhena whom you have often heard named among your friends at home: wherfore I pray you to take so much pains as to come with me to my house, and use it as your own. At whose words I was partly abashed and said, God forbid Cosin that I should forsake mine Host Milo without any reasonable cause; but verily I will, as often as I have occasion to pass by thy house, come and see how you do. And while we were talking thus together, little by little we came to her house, and behold the gates of the same were very beautifully set with pillars quadrangle wise, on the top wherof were placed carved statues and images, but principally the Goddess of Victory was so lively and with such excellency portrayed and set forth, that you would have verily have thought that she had flyed, and hovered with her wings hither and thither. On the contrary part, the image of the Goddess Diana was wrought in white marble, which was a marvelous sight to see, for she seemed as though the winde did blow up her garments, and that she did encounter with them that came into the house. On each side of her were Dogs made of stone, that seemed to menace with their fiery eyes, their pricked ears, their bended nosethrils, their grinning teeth in such sort that you would have thought they had bayed and barked. An moreover (which was a greater marvel to behold) the excellent carver and deviser of this work had fashioned the dogs to stand up fiercely with their former feet, and their hinder feet on the ground ready to fight. Behinde the back of the goddess was carved a stone in manner of a Caverne, environed with mosse, herbes, leaves, sprigs, green branches and bowes, growing in and about the same, insomuch that within the stone it glistered and shone marvelously, under the brim of the stone hanged apples and grapes carved finely, wherein Art envying Nature, showed her great cunning. For they were so lively set out, that you would have thought if Summer had been come, they might have bin pulled and eaten; and while I beheld the running water, which seemed to spring and leap under the feet of the goddess, I marked the grapes which hanged in the water, which were like in every point to the grapes of the vine, and seemed to move and stir by the violence of the streame. Moreover, amongst the branches of the stone appeared the image of Acteon: and how that Diana (which was carved within the same stone, standing in the water) because he did see her naked, did turne him into an hart, and so he was torne and slain of his own hounds. And while I was greatly delighted with the view of these things, Byrrhena spake to me and said, Cousin all things here be at your commandement. And therewithal she willed secretly the residue to depart: who being gone she said, My most deare Cousin Lucius, I do sweare by the goddess Diana, that I do greatly tender your safety, and am as careful for you as if you were mine own natural childe, beware I say, beware of the evil arts and wicked allurements of that Pamphiles who is the wife of Milo, whom you call your Host, for she is accounted the most chief and principal Magitian and Enchantress living, who by breathing out certain words and charmes over bowes, stones and other frivolous things, can throw down all the powers of the heavens into the deep bottome of hell, and reduce all the whole world again to the old Chaos. For as soon as she espieth any comely young man, she is forthwith stricken with his love, and presently setteth her whole mind and affection on him. She soweth her seed of flattery, she invades his spirit and intangleth him with continual snares of unmeasurable love.

And then if any accord not to her filthy desire, or if they seeme loathsome in her eye, by and by in the moment of an houre she turneth them into stones, sheep or some other beast, as herself pleaseth, and some she presently slayeth and murdereth, of whom I would you should earnestly beware. For she burneth continually, and you by reason of your tender age and comely beauty are capable of her fire and love.

Thus with great care Byrrhena gave me in charge, but I (that always coveted and desired, after that I had heard talk of such Sorceries and Witchcrafts, to be experienced in the same) little esteemed to beware of Pamphiles, but willingly determined to bestow my money in learning of that art, and now wholly to become a Witch. And so I waxed joyful, and wringing myself out of her company, as out of linkes or chaines, I bade her farewell, and departed toward the house of mine host Milo, by the way reasoning thus with myself: Oh Lucius now take heed, be vigilant, have a good care, for now thou hast time and place to satisfy thy desire, now shake off thy childishness and show thyself a man, but especially temper thyself from the love of thine hostesse, and abstain from violation of the bed of Milo, but hardly attempt to winne the maiden Fotis, for she is beautiful, wanton and pleasant in talke. And soon when thou goest to sleepe, and when she bringeth you gently into thy chamber, and tenderly layeth thee down in thy bed, and lovingly covereth thee, and kisseth thee sweetly, and departeth unwillingly, and casteth her eyes oftentimes back, and stands still, then hast thou a good occasion ministred to thee to prove and try the mind of Fotis. Thus while I reasoned to myself I came to Milo’s door, persevering still in my purpose, but I found neither Milo nor his wife at home.

The Ninth Chapter

How Apuleius fell in love with Fotis.

When I was within the house I found my dear and sweet love Fotis mincing of meat and making pottage for her master and mistress, the Cupboard was all set with wines, and I thought I smelled the savor of some dainty meats: she had about her middle a white and clean apron, and she was girded about her body under the paps with a swathell of red silk, and she stirred the pot and turned the meat with her fair and white hands, in such sort that with stirring and turning the same, her loins and hips did likewise move and shake, which was in my mind a comely sight to see.

These things when I saw I was half amazed, and stood musing with myself, and my courage came then upon me, which before was scant. And I spake unto Fotis merrily and said, Oh Fotis how trimly you can stir the pot, and how finely, with shaking your buttocks, you can make pottage. Oh happy and twice happy is he to whom you give leave and licence but to touch you there. Then she being likewise merrily disposed, made answer, Depart I say, Miser from me, depart from my fire, for if the flame thereof do never so little blaze forth, it will burn thee extremely and none can extinguish the heat thereof but I alone, who in stirring the pot and making the bed can so finely shake myself. When she had said these words she cast her eyes upon me and laughed, but I did not depart from thence until such time as I had viewed her in every point. But what should I speak of others, when as I do accustom abroad to mark the face and hair of every dame, and afterwards delight myself therewith privately at home, and thereby judge the residue of their shape, because the face is the principal part of all the body, and is first open to our eyes. And whatsoever flourishing and gorgeous apparel doth work and set forth in the corporeal parts of a woman, the same doth the natural and comely beauty set out in the face. Moreover there be diverse, that to the intent to show their grace and feature, will cast off their partlets, collars, habiliments, fronts, cornets and krippins, and do more delight to show the fairness of their skin, than to deck themselves up in gold and precious stones. But because it is a crime unto me to say so, and to give no example thereof, know ye, that if you spoil and cut the hair of any woman or deprive her of the colour of her face, though she were never so excellent in beauty, though she were thrown down from heaven, sprung of the Seas, nourished of the floods, though she were Venus herself, though she were waited upon by all the Court of Cupid, though were girded with her beautiful scarf of Love, and though she smelled of perfumes and musks, yet if she appeared bald, she could in no wise please, no not her own Vulcanus.

Oh how well doth a fair colour and a shining face agree with glittering hair! Behold, it encountereth with the beams of the Sun, and pleaseth the eye marvelously. Sometimes the beauty of the hair resembleth the colour of gold and honey, sometimes the blew plumes and azured feathers about the necks of Doves, especially when it is either anointed with the gum of Arabia, or trimly tuft out with the teeth of a fine comb, which if it be tied up in the pole of the neck, it seemeth to the lover that beholdeth the same, as a glass that yieldeth forth a more pleasant and gracious comeliness than if it should be sparsed abroad on the shoulders of the woman, or hang down scattering behind. Finally there is such a dignity in the hair, that whatsoever she be, though she be never to bravely attired with gold, silks, precious stones, and other rich and gorgeous ornaments, yet if her hair be not curiously set forth she cannot seem fair. But in my Fotis, her garments unbraced and unlaced increased her beauty, her hair hanged about her shoulders, and was dispersed abroad upon her partlet, and in every part of her neck, howbeit the greater part was trussed upon her pole with a lace. Then I unable to sustain the broiling heat that I was in, ran upon her and kissed the place where she had thus laid her hair. Whereat she turned her face, and cast her rolling eyes upon me, saying, Oh Scholar, thou hast tasted now both honey and gall, take heed that thy pleasure do not turn unto repentance. Tush (quoth I) my sweet heart, I am contented for such another kiss to be broiled here upon this fire, wherewithal I embraced and kissed her more often, and she embraced and kissed me likewise, and moreover her breath smelled like Cinnamon, and the liquor of her tongue was like unto sweet Nectar, wherewith when my mind was greatly delighted I said, Behold Fotis I am yours, and shall presently die unless you take pity upon me. Which when I had said she eftsoone kissed me, and bid me be of good courage, and I will (quoth she) satisfy your whole desire, and it shall be no longer delayed than until night, when as assure yourself I will come and lie with you; wherefore go your ways and prepare yourself, for I intend valiantly and courageously to encounter with you this night. Thus when we had lovingly talked and reasoned together, we departed for that time.

The Tenth Chapter

How Byrrhena sent victuals unto Apuleius, and how he talked with Milo of Diophanes, and how he lay with Fotis.

When noone was come, Byrrhena sent to me a fat Pigge, five hennes, and a flagon of old wine. Then I called Fotis and sayd, Behold how Bacchus the egger and stirrer of Venery, doth offer himself of his owne accord, let us therefore drink up this wine, that we may prepare our selves and get us courage against soone, for Venus wanteth no other provision than this, that the Lamp may be all the night replenished with oyle, and the cups with wine. The residue of the day I passed away at the Bains and in banquetting, and towards evening I went to supper, for I was bid by Milo, and so I sat down at the table, out of Pamphiles sight as much as I could, being mindfull of the commandement of Byrrhena, and sometimes I would cast mine eyes upon her as upon the furies of hell, but I eftsoones turning my face behinde me, and beholding my Fotis ministring at the table, was again refreshed and made merry. And behold when Pamphiles did see the candle standing on the table, she said, Verily we shall have much raine to morrow. Which when her husband did heare, he demanded of her by what reason she knew it? Mary (quoth she) the light on the table showeth the same. Then Milo laughed and said, Verily we nourish a Sybel prophesier, which by the view of a candle doth divine of Celestiall things, and of the Sunne itself. Then I mused in my mind and said unto Milo, Of truth it is a good experience and proof of divination. Neither is it any marvell, for although this light is but a small light, and made by the hands of men, yet hath it a remembrance of that great and heavenly light, as of his parent, and doth show unto us what will happen in the Skies above. For I knew at Corinth a certain man of Assyria, who would give answers in every part of the City, and for the gaine of money would tell every man his fortune, to some he would tel the dayes of their marriages, to others he would tell when they should build, that their edifices should continue. To others, when they should best go about their affaires. To others, when they should go by sea or land: to me, purposing to take my journey hither, he declared many things strange and variable. For sometimes he sayd that I should win glory enough: sometimes he sayd I should write a great Historie: sometimes again he sayd that I should devise an incredible tale: and sometimes that I should make Bookes. Whereat Milo laughed again, and enquired of me, of what stature this man of Assyria was, and what he was named. In faith (quoth I) he is a tall man and somewhat blacke, and he is called Diophanes. Then sayd Milo, the same is he and no other, who semblably hath declared many things here unto us, whereby he got and obtained great substance and Treasure.

But the poore miser fell at length into the hands of unpittifull and cruell fortune: For beeing on a day amongst a great assembly of people, to tell the simple sort their fortune, a certain Cobler came unto him, and desired him to tel when it should be best for him to take his voyage, the which he promised to do: the Cobler opened his purse and told a hundred pence to him for his paines. Whereupon came a certain young gentleman and took Diophanes by the Garment. Then he turning himself, embraced and kissed him, and desired the Gentleman, who was one of his acquaintance, to sit down by him: and Diophanes being astonied with this sudden change, forgot what he was doing, and sayd, O deare friend you are heartily welcome, I pray you when arrived you into these parts? Then answered he, I will tell you soone, but brother I pray you tell me of your comming from the isle of Euboea, and how you sped by the way? Whereunto Diophanes this notable Assyrian (not yet come unto his mind, but halfe amased) soone answered and sayd, I would to god that all our enemies and evil willers might fall into the like dangerous peregrination and trouble. For the ship where we were in, after it was by the waves of the seas and by the great tempests tossed hither and thither, in great peril, and after that the mast and stern brake likewise in pieces, could in no wise be brought to shore, but sunk into the water, and so we did swim, and hardly escaped to land. And after that, whatsoever was given unto us in recompense of our losses, either by the pity of strangers, or by the benevolence of our friends, was taken away from us by theeves, whose violence when my brother Arisuatus did assay to resist, he was cruelly murthered by them before my face. These things when he had sadly declared, the Cobler took up his money again which he had told out to pay for the telling of his fortune, and ran away. The Diophanes comming to himself perceived what he had done, and we all that stood by laughed greatly. But that (quoth Milo) which Diophanes did tell unto you Lucius, that you should be happy and have a prosperous journey, was only true. Thus Milo reasoned with me. But I was not a little sorry that I had traind him into such a vaine of talke, that I lost a good part of the night, and the sweete pleasure thereof: but at length I boldly said to Milo, Let Diophanes fare well with his evil fortune, and get again that which he lost by sea and land, for I verily do yet feel the wearinesse of my travell, whereof I pray you pardon me, and give me licence to depart to bed: wherewithall I rose up and went unto my chamber, where I found all things finely prepared and the childrens bed (because they should not heare what we did in the night) was removed far off without the chamber door. The table was all covered with those meats that were left at supper, the cups were filled halfe full with water, to temper and delay the wines, the flagon stood ready prepared, and there lacked nothing that was necessary for the preparation of Venus. And when I was entring into the bed, behold my Fotis (who had brought her mistresse to bed) came in and gave me roses and floures which she had in her apron, and some she threw about the bed, and kissed me sweetly, and tied a garland about my head, and bespred the chamber with the residue. Which when she had done, she took a cup of wine and delaied it with hot water, and profered it me to drinke; and before I had drunk it all off she pulled it from my mouth, and then gave it me again, and in this manner we emptied the pot twice or thrice together. Thus when I had well replenished myself with wine, and was now ready unto Venery not onely in mind but also in body, I removed my clothes, and showing to Fotis my great impatiencie I sayd, O my sweet heart take pity upon me and helpe me, for as you see I am now prepared unto the battell, which you yourself did appoint: for after that I felt the first Arrow of cruell Cupid within my breast, I bent my bow very strong, and now feare, (because it is bended so hard) lest my string should breake: but that thou mayst the better please me, undresse thy hair and come and embrace me lovingly: whereupon she made no long delay, but set aside all the meat and wine, and then she unapparelled herself, and unattyred her hair, presenting her amiable body unto me in manner of faire Venus, when she goeth under the waves of the sea. Now (quoth she) is come the houre of justing, now is come the time of warre, wherefore show thyself like unto a man, for I will not retyre, I will not fly the field, see then thou bee valiant, see thou be couragious, since there is no time appointed when our skirmish shall cease. In saying these words she came to me to bed, and embraced me sweetly, and so we passed all the night in pastime and pleasure, and never slept until it was day: but we would eftsoones refresh our wearinesse, and provoke our pleasure, and renew our venery by drinking of wine. In which sort we pleasantly passed away many other nights following.

The Eleventh Chapter

How Apuleius supped with Byrrhena, and what a strange tale Bellephoron told at the table.

It fortuned on a day, that Byrrhena desired me earnestly to suppe with her; and she would in no wise take any excusation. Whereupon I went to Fotis, to aske counsel of her as of some Divine, who although she was unwilling that I should depart one foot from her company, yet at length she gave me license to be absent for a while, saying, Beware that you tarry not long at supper there, for there is a rabblement of common Barrettors and disturbers of the publique peace, that rove about in the streets and murder all such as they may take, neither can law nor justice redress them in any case. And they will the sooner set upon you, by reason of your comeliness and audacity, in that you are not afeared at any time to walke in the streets.

Then I answered and said, Have no care of me Fotis, for I esteeme the pleasure which I have with thee, above the dainty meats that I eat abroad, and therefore I will returne again quickly. Nevertheless I mind not to come without company, for I have here my sword, wherby I hope to defend myself.

And so in this sort I went to supper, and behold I found in Byrrhena’s house a great company of strangers, and the chiefe and principal of the city: the beds made of Citron and Ivory, were richly adorned and spread with clothe of gold, the Cups were garnished pretiously, and there were diverse other things of sundry fashion, but of like estimation and price: here stood a glasse gorgeously wrought, there stood another of Christall finely painted. There stood a cup of glittering silver, and there stood another of shining gold, and here was another of amber artificially carved and made with pretious stones. Finally, there was all things that might be desired: the Servitors waited orderly at the table in rich apparel, the pages arrayed in silke robes, did fill great gemmes and pearles made in the form of cups, with excellent wine. Then one brought in Candles and Torches, and when we were set down and placed in order, we began to talke, to laugh, and to be merry. And Byrrhena spake unto me and said, I pray you Cousine how like you our country? Verily I think there is no other City which hath the like Temples, Baynes, and other commodities which we have here. Further we have abundance of household stuffe, we have pleasure, we have ease, and when the Roman merchants arrive in this City they are gently and quietly entertained, and all that dwell within this province (when they purpose to solace and repose themselves) do come to this city. Whereunto I answered, Verily (quoth I) you tell truth, for I can find no place in all the world which I like better than this, but I greatly feare the blind inevitable trenches of witches, for they say that the dead bodies are digged out of their graves, and the bones of them that are burnt be stollen away, and the toes and fingers of such as are slain are cut off, and afflict and torment such as live. And the old Witches as soon as they hear of the death of any person, do forthwith go and uncover the hearse and spoil the corpse, to work their enchantments. Then another sitting at the table spake and said, In faith you say true, neither yet do they spare or favor the living. For I know one not far hence that was cruelly handled by them, who being not contented with cutting off his nose, did likewise cut off his ears, whereat all the people laughed heartily, and looked at one that sat at the boords end, who being amased at their gazing, and somewhat angry withall, would have risen from the table, had not Byrrhena spake unto him and said, I pray thee friend Bellerophon sit still and according to thy accustomed curtesie declare unto us the losse of thy nose and ears, to the end that my cousin Lucius may be delighted with the pleasantnes of the tale. To whom he answered, Madam in the office of your bounty shall prevaile herein, but the insolencie of some is not to be supported. This he spake very angerly: But Byrrhena was earnest upon him, and assured him he should have no wrong at any man’s hand. Whereby he was enforced to declare the same, and so lapping up the end of the Table clothe and carpet together, he leaned with his elbow thereon, and held out three forefingers of his right hand in manner of an orator, and said, When I was a young man I went unto a certain city called Milet, to see the games and triumphs there named Olympia, and being desirous to come into this famous province, after that I had travelled over all Thessaly, I fortuned in an evil hour to come to the City Larissa, where while I went up and down to view the streets to seeke some reliefe for my poore estate (for I had spent all my money) I espied an old man standing on a stone in the middest of the market place, crying with a loud voice and saying, that if any man would watch a dead corps that night he should be reasonably rewarded for this pains. Which when I heard, I said to one who passed by, What is here to do? Do dead men use to run away in this Country? Then answered he, Hold your peace, for you are but a Babe and a stranger here, and not without cause you are ignorant how you are in Thessaly, where the women Witches bite off by morsels the flesh and faces of dead men, and thereby work their sorceries and enchantments. Then quoth I, In good fellowship tell me the order of this custody and how it is. Marry (quoth he) first you must watch all the night, with your eyes bent continually upon the Corps, never looking off, nor moving aside. For these Witches do turn themselves into sundry kindes of beasts, whereby they deceive the eyes of all men, sometimes they are transformed into birds, sometimes into Dogs and Mice, and sometimes into flies. Moreover they will charme the keepers of the corps asleepe, neither can it be declared what means and shifts these wicked women do use, to bring their purpose to pass: and the reward for such dangerous watching is no more than foure or sixe shillings. But hearken further (for I had well-nigh forgotten) if the keeper of the dead body do not render on the morning following, the corps whole and sound as he received the same, he shall be punished in this sort: That is, if the corps be diminished or spoiled in any part of his face, hands or toes, the same shall be diminished and spoiled in the keeper. Which when I heard him I took a good heart, and went unto the Crier and bid him cease, for I would take the matter in hand, and so I demanded what I should have. Marry (quoth he) a thousand pence, but beware I say you young man, that you do well defend the dead corps from the wicked witches, for he was the son of one of the chiefest of the city. Tush (said I) you speak you cannot tell what, behold I am a man made all of iron, and have never desire to sleepe, and am more quicke of sight than Lynx or Argus. I had scarse spoken these words, when he took me by the hand and brought me to a certain house, the gate whereof was closed fast, so that I went through the wicket, then he brought me into a chamber somewhat dark, and showed me a Matron clothed in mourning vesture, and weeping in lamentable wise. And he spake unto her and said, Behold here is one that will enterprise to watch the corpes of your husband this night. Which when she heard she turned her blubbered face covered with hair unto me saying, I pray you good man take good heed, and see well to your office. Have no care (quoth I) so you will give me anything above that which is due to be given. Wherewith she was contented, and then she arose and brought me into a chamber whereas the corps lay covered with white sheets, and she called seven witnesses, before whom she showed the dead body, and every part and parcel thereof, and with weeping eyes desired them all to testifie the matter. Which done, she said these words of course as follow: Behold, his nose is whole, his eyes safe, his ears without scarre, his lips untouched, and his chin sound: all which was written and noted in tables, and subscribed with the hands of witnesses to confirme the same. Which done I said unto the matron, Madam I pray you that I may have all things here necessary. What is that? (quoth she). Marry (quoth I) a great lampe with oyle, pots of wine, and water to delay the same, and some other drinke and dainty dish that was left at supper. Then she shaked her head and said, Away fool as thou art, thinkest thou to play the glutton here and to looke for dainty meats where so long time hath not been seene any smoke at all? Commest thou hither to eat, where we should weepe and lament? And therewithal she turned back, and commanded her maiden Myrrhena to deliver me a lampe with oyle, which when she had done they closed the chamber door and departed. Now when I was alone, I rubbed mine eyes, and armed myself to keep the corpes, and to the intent I would not sleepe, I began to sing, and so I passed the time until it was midnight, when as behold there crept in a Wesel into the chamber, and she came against me and put me in very great feare, insomuch that I marvelled greatly at the audacity of so little a beast. To whom I said, get thou hence thou whore and hie thee to thy fellowes, lest thou feele my fingers. Why wilt thou not go? Then incontinently she ranne away, and when she was gon, I fell on the ground so fast asleepe, that Apollo himself could not discern which of us two was the dead corps, for I lay prostrat as one without life, and needed a keeper likewise. At length the cockes began to crow, declaring that it was day: wherewithal I awaked, and being greatly afeard ran to the dead body with the lamp in my hand, and I viewed him round about: and immediately came in the matron weeping with her Witnesses, and ran to the corps, and eftsoons kissing him, she turned his body and found no part diminished. Then she willed Philodespotus her steward to pay me my wages forthwith. Which when he had done he said, We thanke you gentle young man for your pains and verily for your diligence herein we will account you as one of the family. Whereunto I (being joyous of by unhoped gaine, and ratling my money in my hand) did answer, I pray you madam esteeme me as one of your servants, and if you want my service at any time, I am at your commandement. I had not fully declared these words, when as behold all the servants of the house were assembled with weapons to drive me away, one buffeted me about the face, another about the shoulders, some strook me in the sides, some kicked me, and some tare my garments, and so I was handled amongst them and driven from the house, as the proud young man Adonis who was torn by a Bore. And when I was come into the next street, I mused with myself, and remembered mine unwise and unadvised words which I had spoken, whereby I considered that I had deserved much more punishment, and that I was worthily beaten for my folly. And by and by the corps came forth, which because it was the body of one of the chiefe of the city, was carried in funeral pompe round about the market place, according to the right of the country there. And forthwith stepped out an old man weeping and lamenting, and ranne unto the Biere and embraced it, and with deep sighes and sobs cried out in this sort, Oh masters, I pray you by the faith which you professe, and by the duty which you owe unto the weale publique, take pity and mercy upon this dead corps, who is miserably murdered, and do vengeance on this wicked and cursed woman his wife which hath committed this fact: for it is she and no other which hath poisoned her husband my sisters sonne, to the intent to maintaine her whoredom, and to get his heritage. In this sort the old man complained before the face of all people. Then they (astonied at these sayings, and because the thing seemed to be true) cried out, Burne her, burne her, and they sought for stones to throw at her, and willed the boys in the street to do the same. But she weeping in lamentable wise, did swear by all the gods, that she was not culpable of this crime. No quoth the old man, here is one sent by the providence of God to try out the matter, even Zachlas an Egypptian, who is the most principal Prophecier in all this country, and who was hired of me for money to reduce the soule of this man from hell, and to revive his body for the trial hereof. And therewithal he brought forth a certain young man clothed in linnen raiment, having on his feet a pair of pantofiles, and his crown shaven, who kissed his hands and knees, saying, Oh priest have mercy, have mercy I pray thee by the Celestial Planets, by the Powers infernal, by the virtue of the natural elements, by the silences of the night, by the building of Swallows nigh unto the town Copton, by the increase of the flood Nilus, by the secret mysteries of Memphis, and by the instruments and trumpets of the Isle Pharos, have mercy I say, and call to life this dead body, and make that his eyes which he closed and shut, may be open and see. Howbeit we mean not to strive against the law of death, neither intend we to deprive the earth of his right, but to the end this fact may be known, we crave but a small time and space of life. Whereat this Prophet was moved, and took a certain herb and laid it three times against the mouth of the dead, and he took another and laid upon his breast in like sort. Thus when he had done he turned himself into the East, and made certain orisons unto the Sun, which caused all the people to marvel greatly, and to looke for this strange miracle that should happen. Then I pressed in amongst them nigh unto the biere, and got upon a stone to see this mysterie, and behold incontinently the dead body began to receive spirit, his principal veines did move, his life came again and he held up his head and spake in this sort: Why do you call me back again to this transitorie life, that have already tasted of the water of Lethe, and likewise been in the deadly den of Styx? Leave off, I pray, leave off, and let me lie in quiet rest. When these words were uttered by the dead corps, the Prophet drew nigh unto the Biere and said, I charge thee to tell before the face of all the people here the occasion of thy death: What, dost thou think that I cannot by my conjurations call up the dead, and by my puissance torment thy body? Then the corps moved his head again, and made reverence to the people and said, Verily I was poisoned by the means of my wicked wife, and so thereby yielded my bed unto an adulterer. Whereat his wife taking present audacity, and reproving his sayings, with a cursed mind did deny it. The people were bent against her sundry ways, some thought best that she should be buried alive with her husband: but some said that there ought no credit to be given to the dead body. Which opinion was cleane taken away, by the words which the corps spoke again and said, Behold I will give you some evident token, which never yet any other man knew, whereby you shall perceive that I declare the truth: and by and by he pointed towards me that stood on the stone, and said, When this the good Gard of my body watched me diligently in the night, and that the wicked Witches and enchantresses came into the chamber to spoil me of my limbes, and to bring such their purpose did transform themselves into the shape of beasts: and when as they could in no wise deceive or beguile his vigilant eyes, they cast him into so dead and sound a sleepe, that by their witchcraft he seemed without spirit or life. After this they did call me by my name, and never did cease til as the cold members of my body began by little and little and little to revive. Then he being of more lively soule, howbeit buried in sleep, in that he and I were named by one name, and because he knew not that they called me, rose up first, and as one without sence or perseverance passed by the dore fast closed, unto a certain hole, whereas the Witches cut off first his nose, and then his ears, and so that was done to him which was appointed to be done to me. And that such their subtleity might not be perceived, they made him a like pair of ears and nose of wax: wherfore you may see that the poore miser for lucre of a little mony sustained losse of his members. Which when he had said I was greatly astonied, and minding to prove whether his words were true or no, put my hand to my nose, and my nose fell off, and put my hand to my ears and my ears fell off. Wherat all the people wondred greatly, and laughed me to scorne: but I being strucken in a cold sweat, crept between their legs for shame and escaped away. So I disfigured returned home again, and covered the losse of mine ears with my long hair, and glewed this clout to my face to hide my shame. As soon as Bellephoron had told his tale, they which sat at the table replenished with wine, laughed heartily. And while they drank one to another, Byrrhena spake to me and said, from the first foundation of this city we have a custom to celebrate the festival day of the god Risus, and tomorrow is the feast when as I pray you to be present, to set out the same more honourably, and I would with all my heart that you could find or devise somewhat of yourself, that might be in honour of so great a god. To whom I answered, verily cousin I will do as you command me, and right glad would I be, if I might invent any laughing or merry matter to please or satisfy Risus withall. Then I rose from the table and took leave of Byrrhena and departed. And when I came into the first street my torch went out, that with great pain I could scarce get home, by reason it was so dark, for fear of stumbling: and when I was well-nigh come unto the dore, behold I saw three men of great stature, heaving and lifting at Milo’s gates to get in: and when they saw me they were nothing afeard, but assaied with more force to break down the dores whereby they gave me occasion, and not without cause, to think that they were strong thieves. Whereupon I by and by drew out my sword which I carried for that purpose under my cloak, and ran in amongst them, and wounded them in such sort that they fell down dead before my face. Thus when I had slain them all, I knocked sweating and breathing at the door til Fotis let me in. And then full weary with the slaughter of those Thieves, like Hercules when he fought against the king Gerion, I went to my chamber and laid me down to sleep.

The Twelfth Chapter

How Apuleius was taken and put in prison for murder.

When morning was come, and that I was awaked from sleep, my heart burned sore with remembrance of the murder I had committed the night before: and I rose and sat down on the side of the bed with my legs across, and wringing my hands, I wept in most miserable sort. For I imagined with myself, that I was brought before the judge in the judgment place, and that he awarded sentence against me, and that the hangman was ready to lead me to the gallows. And further I imagined and said, Alas what judge is he that is so gentle or benign, that will think that I am unguilty of the slaughter and murder of these three men. Howbeit the Assyrian Diophanes did firmly assure unto me, that my peregrination and voyage hither should be prosperous. But while I did thus unfold my sorrows, and greatly bewail my fortune, behold I heard a great noise and cry at the door, and in came the magistrates and officers, who commanded two sergeants to bind and lead me to prison, whereunto I was willingly obedient, and as they led me through the street, all the city gathered together and followed me, and although I looked always on the ground for very shame, yet sometimes I cast my head aside and marvelled greatly that among so many thousand people there was not one but laughed exceedingly. Finally, when they had brought me through all the streets of the city, in manner of those that go in procession, and do sacrifice to mitigate the ire of the gods, they placed me in the judgment hall, before the seat of the judges: and after that the crier had commanded all men to keep silence, and people desired the judges to give sentence in the great theatre, by reason of the great multitude that was there, whereby they were in danger of stifling. And behold the press of people increased still, some climbed to the top of the house, some got upon the beams, some upon the images, and some thrust their heads through the windows, little regarding the dangers they were in, so they might see me.

Then the officers brought me forth openly into the middle of the hall, that every man might behold me. And after that the crier had made a noise, and willed all such that would bring any evidence against me, should come forth, there stepped out an old man with a glass of water in his hand, dropping out softly, who desired that he might have liberty to speak during the time of the continuance of the water. Which when it was granted, he began his oration in this sort.

Chapter XVII

How Apuleius thinking to be turned into a bird, was turned into an ass, and how he was led away by thieves.

After that I had well rubbed every part and member of my body, I hovered with mine arms, and moved myself, looking still when I should be changed into a bird as Pamphiles was, and behold neither feathers nor appearance of feathers did burgeon out, but verily my hair did turn in ruggedness, and my tender skin waxed tough and hard, my fingers and toes losing the number of five, changed into hoofs, and out of mine arse grew a great tail, now my face became monstrous, my nostrils wide, my lips hanging down, and mine ears rugged with hair: neither could I see any comfort of my transformation, for my members increased likewise, and so without all help (viewing every part of my poor body) I perceived that I was no bird, but a plain ass.

Then I thought to blame Fotis, but being deprived as well of language as of human shape, I looked upon her with my hanging lips and watery eyes. Who as soon as she espied me in such sort, cried out, Alas poor wretch that I am, I am utterly cast away. The fear I was in, and my haste hath beguiled me, but especially the mistaking of the box, hath deceived me. But it forceth not much, in regard a sooner medicine may be gotten for this than for any other thing. For if thou couldst get a rose and eat it, thou shouldst be delivered from the shape of an ass, and become my Lucius again. And would to God I had gathered some garlands this evening past, according to my custom, then thou shouldst not continue an ass one nights’ space, but in the morning I shall seek some remedy. Thus Fotis lamented in pitiful sort, but I that was now a perfect ass, and for Lucius a brute beast, did yet retain the sense and understanding of a man. And did devise a good space with myself, whether it were best for me to tear this mischievous and wicked harlot with my mouth, or to kick and kill her with my heels. But a better thought reduced me from so rash a purpose: for I feared lest by the death of Fotis I should be deprived of all remedy and help. Then shaking mine head, and dissembling mine ire, and taking my adversity in good part, I went into the stable to my own horse, where I found another ass of Milo’s, sometime my host, and I did verily think that mine own horse (if there were any natural conscience or knowledge in brute beasts) would take pity on me, and proffer me lodging for that night: but it chanced far otherwise. For see, my horse and the ass as it were consented together to work my harm, and fearing lest I should eat up their provender, would in nowise suffer me to come nigh the manger, but kicked me with their heels from their meat, which I myself gave them the night before. Then I being thus handled by them, and driven away, got me into a corner of the stable, where while I remembered their uncourtesy, and how on the morrow I should return to Lucius by the help of a rose, when as I thought to revenge myself of mine own horse, I fortuned to espy in the middle of a pillar sustaining the rafters of the stable the image of the goddess Hipponoe, which was garnished and decked round about with fair and fresh roses: then in hope of present remedy, I leaped up with my forefeet as high as I could, stretching out my neck, and with my lips coveting to snatch some roses. But in an evil hour I did go about that enterprise, for behold the boy to whom I gave charge of my horse, came presently in, and finding me climbing upon the pillar, ran fretting towards me and said, How long shall we suffer this wild ass, that doth not only eat up his fellows’ meat, but also would spoil the images of the gods? Why do I not kill this lame thief and weak wretch? And therewithal looking about for some cudgel, he espied where lay a fagot of wood, and choosing out a crabbed truncheon of the biggest he could find, did never cease beating of me poor wretch, until such time as by great noise and rumbling, he heard the doors of the house burst open, and the neighbours crying in most lamentable sort, which enforced him being stricken in fear, to fly his way. And by and by a troupe of thieves entered in, and kept every part and corner of the house with weapons. And as men resorted to aid and help them which were within the doors, the thieves resisted and kept them back, for every man was armed with a sword and target in his hand, the glimpses whereof did yield out such light as if it had been day. Then they brake open a great chest with double locks and bolts, wherein was laid all the treasure of Milo, and ransacked the same: which when they had done they packed it up and gave every man a portion to carry: but when they had more than they could bear away, yet were they loath to leave any behind, but came into the stable, and took us two poor asses and my horse, and laded us with greater trusses than we were able to bear. And when we were out of the house, they followed us with great staves, and willed one of their fellows to tarry behind, and bring them tidings what was done concerning the robbery: and so they beat us forward over great hills out of the way. But I, what with my heavy burden and long journey, did nothing differ from a dead ass: wherefore I determined with myself to seek some civil remedy, and by invocation of the name of the prince of the country to be delivered from so many miseries: and on a time I passed through a great fair, I came among a multitude of Greeks, and I thought to call upon the renowned name of the emperor and say, Oh Caesar, and cried out aloud Oh, but Caesar I could in nowise pronounce. The Thieves little regarding my crying, did lay me on and beat my wretched skin in such sort, that after it was neither apt nor meet to make sieves or sarces. Howbeit at last Jupiter administered to me an unhoped remedy. For when we had passed through many towns and villages, I fortuned to espy a pleasant garden, wherein beside many other flowers of delectable hue, were new and fresh roses: and being very joyful, and desirous to catch some as I passed by, I drew nearer and nearer: and while my lips watered upon them, I thought of a better advice more profitable for me, lest if from an ass I should become a man, I might fall into the hands of the thieves, and either by suspicion that I were some witch, or for fear that I should utter their theft, I should be slain, wherefore I abstained for that time from eating of roses, and enduring my present adversity, I did eat hay as other asses did.

The Thirteenth Chapter

How Apuleius was accused by an old man, and how he answered for himself.

Oh most reverend and just judges, the thing which I propose to declare to you is no small matter, but toucheth the estate and tranquillity of this whole city, and the punishment thereof may be a right good example to others. Wherefore I pray you most venerable fathers, to whom and every one of whom it doth appertain, to provide for the dignity and safety of the commonweal, that you would in nowise suffer this wicked homicide, embrued with the blood of so many murdered citizens, to escape unpunished. And think you not that I am moved thereunto by envy or hatred, but by reason of my office, in that I am captain of the night watch, and because no man alive should accuse me to be remiss in the same I will declare all the whole matter, orderly as it was done last night.

This night past, when as at our accustomed hour I diligently searched every part of the city, behold I fortuned to espy this cruel young man drawing out his sword against three citizens, and after a long combat foughten between them, he murdered one after another miserably: which when he had done, moved in his conscience at so great a crime he ran away, and aided by the reason of darkness, slipped into a house, and there lay hidden all night, but by the providence of the gods, which suffereth no heinous offence to pass unpunished, he was taken by us this morning before he escaped any further, and so brought hither to your honourable presence to receive his desert accordingly.

So have you here a guilty person, a culpable homicide, and an accused stranger, wherefore pronounce you judgment against this man being an alien, when as you would most severely and sharply revenge such an offence found in a known citizen. In this sort the cruel accuser finished and ended his terrible tale. Then the crier commanded me to speak, if I had anything to say for myself, but I could in nowise utter any word at all for weeping. And on the other side I esteemed not so much his rigorous accusation, as I did consider mine own miserable conscience. Howbeit, being inspired by divine audacity, at length I gan say, Verily I know that it is an hard thing for him that is accused to have slain three persons, to persuade you that he is innocent, although he should declare the whole truth, and confess the matter how it was indeed, but if your honours will vouchsafe to give me audience, I will show you, that if I am condemned to die, I have not deserved it as mine own desert, but that I was moved by fortune and reasonable cause to do that fact. For returning somewhat late from supper yesternight (being well tippled with wine, which I will not deny) and approaching nigh to my common lodging, which was in the house of one Milo a citizen of this city, I fortuned to espy three great thieves attempting to break down his walls and gates, and to open the locks to enter in. And when they had removed the doors out of the hooks, they consulted amongst themselves, how they would handle such as they found in the house. And one of them being of more courage, and of greater stature than the rest, spake unto his fellows and said, Tush you are but boys, take men’s hearts unto you, and let us enter into every part of the house, and such as we find asleep let us kill, and so by that means we shall escape without danger. Verily ye three judges, I confess that I drew out my sword against those three citizens, but I thought it was the office and duty of one that beareth goodwill to this wealpublic, so to do, especially since they put me in great fear, and assayed to rob and spoil my friend Milo. But when those cruel and terrible men would in no case run away, nor fear my naked sword, but boldly resist against me, I ran upon them and fought valiantly. One of them which was the captain invaded me strongly, and drew me by the hair with both his hands, and began to beat me with a great stone: but in the end I proved the hardier man, and threw him down at my feet and killed him. I took likewise the second that clasped me about the legs and bit me, and slew him also. And the third that came running violently against me, after that I had stricken him under the stomach fell down dead. Thus when I had delivered myself, the house, mine host, and all his family from this present danger, I thought that I should not only escape unpunished, but also have some great reward of the city for my pains.

Moreover, I that have always been clear and unspotted of crime, and that have esteemed mine innocence above all the treasure of the world, can find no reasonable cause why upon mine accusation I should be condemned to die, since first I was moved to set upon the thieves by just occasion. Secondly, because there is none that can affirm, that there hath been at any time either grudge or hatred between us. Thirdly, we were men mere strangers and of no acquaintance. Last of all, no man can prove that I committed that fact for lucre or gain.

When I had ended my words in this sort, behold, I wept again piteously, and holding up my hands I prayed all the people by the mercy of the commonweal and for the love of my poor infants and children, to show me some pity and favour. And when their hearts were somewhat relented and moved by my lamentable tears, I called all the gods to witness that I was unguilty of the crime, and so to their divine providence, I committed my present estate, but turning myself again, I perceived that all the people laughed exceedingly, and especially my good friend and host Milo. Then thought I with myself, Alas where is faith? Where is remorse of conscience? Behold I am condemned to die as a murderer, for the safeguard of mine Host Milo and his family. Yet is he not contented with that, but likewise laugheth me to scorn, when otherwise he should comfort and help me.

The Fourteenth Chapter

How Apuleius was accused by two women, and how the slain bodies were found blown bladders.

When this was done, out came a woman in the middle of the Theatre arrayed in mourning vesture, and bearing a child in her arms. And after her came an old woman in ragged robes, crying and howling likewise: and they brought with them the Olive boughs wherewith the three slain bodies were covered on the Bier, and cried out in this manner: Oh right Judges, we pray by the justice and humanity which is in you, to have mercy upon these slain persons, and succor our Widowhood and loss of our dear husbands, and especially this poor infant, who is now an Orphan, and deprived of all good fortune: and execute your justice by order and law, upon the blood of this Thief, who is the occasion of all our sorrows. When they had spoken these words, one of the most ancient Judges did rise and say, Touching this murder, which deserveth great punishment, this malefactor himself cannot deny, but our duty is to inquire and try out, whether he had Coadjutors to help him. For it is not likely that one man alone could kill three such great and valiant persons, wherefore the truth must be tried out by the rack, and so we shall learn what other companions he hath, and root out the nest of these mischievous murderers. And there was no long delay, but according to the custom of Grecia, the fire, the wheel, and many other torments were brought in. Then my sorrow increased or rather doubled, in that I could not end my life with whole and unperished members. And by and by the old woman, who troubled all the Court with her howling, desired the Judges, that before I should be tormented on the rack, I might uncover the bodies which I had slain, that every man might see their comely shape and beauty, and that I might receive condign and worthy punishment, according to the quality of my offence: and therewithal she made a sign of joy. Then the Judge commanded me forthwith to discover the bodies of the slain, lying upon the bier, with mine own hands, but when I refused a good space, by reason I would not make my fact apparent to the eyes of all men, the Sergeant charged me by commandment of the Judges, and thrust me forward to do the same. I being then forced by necessity, though it were against my will, uncovered the bodies: but Oh good Lord what a strange sight did I see, what a monster? What sudden change of all my sorrows? I seemed as though I were one of the house of Proserpina and of the family of death, insomuch that I could not sufficiently express the form of this new sight, so far was I amazed and astonied thereat: for why, the bodies of the three slain men were no bodies, but three blown bladders mangled in diverse places, and they seemed to be wounded in those parts where I remembered I wounded the thieves the night before. Whereat the people laughed exceedingly: some rejoiced marvelously at the remembrance thereof, some held their stomachs that ached with joy, but every man delighted at this passing sport, so passed out of the theatre. But I from the time that I uncovered the bodies stood still as cold as ice, no otherwise than as the other statues and images there, neither came I into my right senses, until such time as Milo my Host came and took me by the hand, and with civil violence led me away weeping and sobbing, whether I would or no. And because that I might be seen, he brought me through many blind ways and lanes to his house, where he went about to comfort me, being sad and yet fearful, with gentle entreaty of talk. But he could in no wise mitigate my impatience of the injury which I conceived within my mind. And behold, by and by the Magistrates and Judges with their ensigns entered into the house, and endeavoured to pacify me in this sort, saying, Oh Lucius, we are advertised of your dignity, and know the genealogy of your ancient lineage, for the nobility of your Kin do possess the greatest part of all this Province: and think not that you have suffered the thing wherefore you weep, to any reproach and ignominy, but put away all care and sorrow out of your mind. For this day, which we celebrate once a year in honour of the god Risus, is always renowned with some solemn novel, and the god doth continually accompany with the inventor thereof, and will not suffer that he should be sorrowful, but pleasantly bear a joyful face. And verily all the City for the grace that is in you, intend to reward you with great honours, and to make you a Patron. And further that your statue or image may be set up for a perpetual remembrance.

To whom I answered, As for such benefits as I have received of the famous City of Thessaly, I yield and render the most entire thanks, but as touching the setting up of any statues or images, I would wish that they should be reserved for mine Ancients, and such as are more worthy than I.

And when I had spoken these words somewhat gravely, and showed myself more merry than I was before, the Judges and magistrates departed, and I reverently took my leave of them, and bid them farewell. And behold, by and by there came one running unto me in haste, and said, Sir, your cousin Byrrhena desireth you to take the pains according to your promise yesternight, to come to supper, for it is ready. But I greatly fearing to go any more to her house in the night, said to the messenger, My friend I pray you tell to my cousin your mistress, that I would willingly be at her commandment, but for breaking my troth and credit. For mine host Milo enforced me to assure him, and compelled me by the feast of this present day, that I should not depart from his company, wherefore I pray you to excuse, and to defer my promise to another time.

And while I was speaking these words, Milo took me by the hand, and led me towards the next Bain: but by the way I went couching under him, to hide myself from the sight of men, because I had ministered such an occasion of laughter. And when I had washed and wiped myself, and returned home again, I never remembered any such thing, so greatly was I abashed at the nodding and pointing of every person. Then went I to supper with Milo, where God wot we fared but meanly. Wherefore feigning that my head did ache by reason of my sobbing and weeping all day, I desired license to depart to my Chamber, and so I went to bed.

The Fifteenth Chapter

How Fotis told to Apuleius, what witchcraft her mistress did use.

When I was abed I began to call to mind all the sorrows and griefs that I was in the day before, until such time as my love Fotis, having brought her mistress to sleep, came into the chamber, not as she was wont to do, for she seemed nothing pleasant neither in countenance nor talk, but with sour face and frowning look, gan speak in this sort, Verily I confess that I have been the occasion of all thy trouble this day, and therewith she pulled out a whip from under her apron, and delivered it unto me saying, Revenge thyself upon me mischievous harlot, or rather slay me.

And think you not that I did willingly procure this anguish and sorrow unto you, I call the gods to witness. For I had rather mine own body to perish, than that you should receive or sustain any harm by my means, but that which I did was by the commandment of another, and wrought as I thought for some other, but behold the unlucky chance fortuned on you by my evil occasion.

Then I, very curious and desirous to know the matter, answered, In faith (quoth I), this most pestilent and evil-favoured whip which thou hast brought to scourge thee withal, shall first be broken in a thousand pieces, than it should touch or hurt thy delicate and dainty skin. But I pray you tell me how have you been the cause and mean of my trouble and sorrow? For I dare swear by the love that I bear unto you, and I will not be persuaded, though you yourself should endeavour the same, that ever you went to trouble or harm me: perhaps sometimes you imagined an evil thought in your mind, which afterwards you revoked, but that is not to be deemed as a crime.

When I had spoken these words, I perceived by Fotis eyes being wet with tears and well-nigh closed up that she had a desire unto pleasure and specially because she embraced and kissed me sweetly. And when she was somewhat restored unto joy she desired me that she might first shut the chamber door, least by the untemperance of her tongue, in uttering any unfitting words, there might grow further inconvenience. Wherewithal she barred and propped the door, and came to me again, and embracing me lovingly about the neck with both her arms, spake with a soft voice and said, I do greatly fear to discover the privities of this house, and to utter the secret mysteries of my dame. But I have such confidence in you and in your wisdom, by reason that you are come of so noble a line, and endowed with so profound sapience, and further instructed in so many holy and divine things, that you will faithfully keep silence, and that whatsoever I shall reveal or declare unto you, you would close them within the bottom of your heart, and never discover the same: for I ensure you, the love that I bear unto you, enforceth me to utter it. Now shall you know all the estate of our house, now shall you know the hidden secrets of my mistress, unto whom the powers of hel do obey, and by whom the celestial planets are troubled, the gods made weak, and the elements subdued, neither is the violence of her art in more strength and force, than when she espieth some comely young man that pleaseth her fancy, as oftentimes it happeneth, for now she loveth one Boetian a fair and beautiful person, on whom she employs all her sorcery and enchantment, and I heard her say with mine own ears yesternight, that if the Sun had not then presently gone down, and the night come to minister convenient time to work her magical enticements, she would have brought perpetual darkness over all the world herself. And you shall know, that when she saw yesternight, this Boetian sitting at the Barbers a polling, when she came from the Baines she secretly commanded me to gather up some of the hairs of his head which lay dispersed upon the ground, and to bring it home. Which when I thought to have done the Barber espied me, and by reason it was bruted throughout all the City that we were Witches and Enchantresses, he cried out and said, Will you never leave off stealing of young men's hairs? In faith I assure you, unless you cease your wicked sorceries, I will complain to the Justices. Wherewithal he came angrily towards me, and took away the hair which I had gathered, out of my apron: which grieved me very much, for I knew my Mistresses' manners, that she would not be contented but beat me cruelly.

Wherefore I intended to run away, but the remembrance of you put always the thought out of my mind, and so I came homeward very sorrowful: but because I would not seem to come to my mistress' sight with empty hands, I saw a man shearing of blown goat skins, and the hair which he had shorn off was yellow, and much resembled the hair of the Boetian, and I took a good deal thereof, and colouring of the matter, I brought it to my mistress. And so when night came, before your return from supper, she to bring her purpose to pass, went up to a high Gallery of her house, opening to the East part of the world, and preparing herself according to her accustomed practice, she gathered together all substance for fumigations, she brought forth plates of metal carved with strange characters, she prepared the bones of such as were drowned by tempest in the seas, she made ready the members of dead men, as the nostrils and fingers, she set out the lumps of flesh of such as were hanged, the blood which she had reserved of such as were slain and the jaw bones and teeth of wild beasts, then she said certain charms over the hair, and dipped it in diverse waters, as in well water, Cow milk, mountain honey, and other liquor. Which when she had done, she tied and lapped it up together, and with many perfumes and smells threw it into an hot fire to burn. Then by the great force of this sorcery, and the violence of so many confections, those bodies whose hair was burning in the fire, received human shape, and felt, heard and walked: And smelling the scent of their own hair, came and rapped at our doors instead of Boetius. Then you being well tippled, and deceived by the obscurity of the night, drew out your sword courageously like furious Ajax, and killed not as he did, whole heard of beasts, but three blown skins, to the intent that I, after the slaughter of so many enemies, without effusion of blood might embrace and kiss, not an homicide but an Utricide.

Thus when I was pleasantly mocked and taunted by Fotis, I said unto her, verily now may I for this achieved enterprise be numbered as Hercules, who by his valiant prowess performed the twelve notable Labors, as Gerion with three bodies, and as Cerberus with three heads, for I have slain three blown goat skins. But to the end that I may pardon thee of that thing which thou hast committed, perform, the thing which I most earnestly desire of thee, that is, bring me that I may see and behold when thy mistress goeth about any Sorcery or enchantment, and when she prayeth unto the gods: for I am very desirous to learn that art, and as it seemeth unto me, thou thyself hath some experience in the same. For this I know and plainly feel, That whereas I have always irked and loathed the embrace of Matrons, I am so stricken and subdued with thy shining eyes, ruddy cheeks, glittering hair, sweet kisses, and lily white paps, that I have neither mind to go home, nor to depart hence, but esteem the pleasure which I shall have with thee this night, above all the joys of the world. Then (quoth she) Oh my Lucius, how willing would I be to fulfill your desire, but by reason she is so hated, she getteth herself into solitary places, and out of the presence of every person, when she mindeth to work her enchantments. Howbeit I regard more to gratify your request, than I do esteem the danger of my life: and when I see opportunity and time I will assuredly bring you word, so that you shall see all her enchantments, but always upon this condition, that you secretly keep close such things as are done.

Thus as we reasoned together the courage of Venus assailed, as well our desires as our members, and so she unarrayed herself and came to bed, and we passed the night in pastime and dalliance, till as by drowsy and unlusty sleep I was constrained to lie still.

The Sixteenth Chapter

How Fotis brought Apuleius to see her Mistresse enchant.

On a day Fotis came running to me in great feare, and said that her mistresse, to work her sorceries on such as she loved, intended the night following to transform herself into a bird, and to fly whither she pleased. Wherefore she willed me privily to prepare myself to see the same. And when midnight came she led me softly into a high chamber, and bid me look thorow the chink of a door: where first I saw how she put off all her garments, and took out of a certain coffer sundry kindes of boxs, of the which she opened one, and tempered the ointment therein with her fingers, and then rubbed her body therewith from the sole of the foot to the crown of the head, and when she had spoken privily with herself, having the candle in her hand, she shaked the parts of her body, and behold, I perceived a plume of feathers did burgen out, her nose waxed crooked and hard, her nailes turned into clawes, and so she became an Owle. Then she cried and screeched like a bird of that kinde, and willing to proove her force, moved herself from the ground by little and little, til at last she flew quite away.

Thus by her sorcery she transformed her body into what shape she would. Which when I saw I was greatly astonied: and although I was inchanted by no kind of charme, yet I thought that I seemed not to have the likeness of Lucius, for so was I banished from my sences, amazed in madness, and so I dreamed waking, that I felt mine eyes, whether I were asleepe or no. But when I was come again to myself, I took Fotis by the hand, and moved it to my face and said, I pray thee while occasion doth serve, that I may have the fruition of the fruits of my desire, and grant me some of this ointment. O Fotis I pray thee by thy sweet paps, to make that in the great flames of my love I may be turned into a bird, so I will ever hereafter be bound unto you, and obedient to your commandement. Then said Fotis, Will you go about to deceive me now, and inforce me to work my own sorrow? Are you in the mind that you will not tarry in Thessaly? If you be a bird, where shall I seek you, and when shall I see you? Then answered I, God forbid that I should commit such a crime, for though I could fly in the air as an Eagle or though I were the messenger of Jupiter, yet would I have recourse to nest with thee: and I swear by the knot of thy amiable hair, that since the time I first loved thee, I never fancied any other person: moreover, this commeth to my mind, that if by the virtue of the ointment I shall become an Owle, I will take heed I will come nigh no man’s house: for I am not to learn, how these matrons would handle their lovers, if they knew that they were transformed into Owles: Moreover, when they are taken in any place they are nayled upon posts, and so they are worthily rewarded, because it is thought that they bring evil fortune to the house. But I pray you (which I had almost forgotten) to tell me by what means when I am an Owle, I shall return to my pristine shape, and become Lucius again. Feare not (quoth she) for my mistres hath taught me the way to bring that to pass, neither think you that she did it for any good will and favour, but to the end that I might help her, and minister some remedy when she returneth home.

Consider I pray you with yourself, with what frivolous trifles so marvelous a thing is wrought: for by Hercules I swear I give her nothing else save a little Dill and Lawrell leaves, in Well water, the which she drinketh and washeth herself withall. Which when she had spoken she went into the chamber and took a box out of the coffer, which I first kissed and embraced, and prayed that I might [have] good success in my purpose. And then I put off all my garments, and greedily thrust my hand into the box, and took out a good deale of ointment and rubbed myself withall.

The Seventeenth Chapter

How Apuleius thinking to be turned into a Bird, was turned into an Asse, and how he was led away by Theves.

After that I had well rubbed every part and member of my body, I hovered with mine armes, and moved myself, looking still when I should bee changed into a Bird as Pamphiles was, and behold neither feathers nor appearance of feathers did burgen out, but verily my hair did turne in ruggednesse, and my tender skin waxed tough and hard, my fingers and toes losing the number of five, changed into hoofes, and out of mine arse grew a great taile, now my face became monstrous, my nosthrils wide, my lips hanging down, and mine eares rugged with hair: neither could I see any comfort of my transformation, for my members encreased likewise, and so without all helpe (viewing every part of my poore body) I perceived that I was no bird, but a plaine Asse.

Then I thought to blame Fotis, but being deprived as wel of language as of humane shape, I looked upon her with my hanging lips and watery eyes. Who as soon as she espied me in such sort, cried out, Alas poore wretch that I am, I am utterly cast away. The feare I was in, and my haste hath beguiled me, but especially the mistaking of the box, hath deceived me. But it forceth not much, in regard a sooner medicine may be gotten for this than for any other thing. For if thou couldst get a rose and eat it, thou shouldst be delivered from the shape of an Asse, and become my Lucius again. And would to God I had gathered some garlands this evening past, according to my custome, then thou shouldst not continue an Asse one nights space, but in the morning I shall seek some remedy. Thus Fotis lamented in pittifull sort, but I that was now a perfect asse, and for Lucius a brute beast, did yet retaine the sence and understanding of a man. And did devise a good space with myself, whether it were best for me to teare this mischievous and wicked harlot with my mouth, or to kicke and kill her with my heels. But a better thought reduced me from so rash a purpose: for I feared lest by the death of Fotis I should be deprived of all remedy and help. Then shaking mine head, and dissembling mine ire, and taking my adversity in good part, I went into the stable to my own horse, where I found another asse of Milos, somtime my host, and I did verily think that mine own horse (if there were any natural conscience or knowledge in brute beasts) would take pity on me, and profer me lodging for that night: but it chanced far otherwise. For see, my horse and the asse as it were consented together to work my harm, and fearing lest I should eat up their provender, would in no wise suffer me to come nigh the manger, but kicked me with their heels from their meat, which I myself gave them the night before. Then I being thus handled by them, and driven away, got me into a corner of the stable, where while I remembred their uncurtesie, and how on the morrow I should return to Lucius by the help of a Rose, when as I thought to revenge myself of mine own horse, I fortuned to espy in the middle of a pillar sustaining the rafters of the stable the image of the goddess Hippone, which was garnished and decked round about with fair and fresh roses: then in hope of present remedy, I leaped up with my fore feet as high as I could, stretching out my neck, and with my lips coveting to snatch some roses. But in an evill houre I did go about that enterprise, for behold the boy to whom I gave charge of my horse, came presently in, and finding me climbing upon the pillar, ranne fretting towards me and said, How long shall we suffer this wild Asse, that doth not onely eat up his fellowes meat, but also would spoil the images of the gods? Why do I not kill this lame theefe and weake wretch? And therewithall looking about for some cudgel, he espied where lay a fagot of wood, and choosing out a crabbed truncheon of the biggest he could finde, did never cease beating of me poore wretch, until such time as by great noise and rumbling, he heard the doors of the house burst open, and the neighbours crying in most lamentable sort, which enforced him being stricken in feare, to fly his way. And by and by a troupe of theeves entred in, and kept every part and corner of the house with weapons. And as men resorted to aid and help them which were within the doors, the theeves resisted and kept them back, for every man was armed with a sword and target in his hand, the glimpses whereof did yeeld out such light as if it had bin day. Then they brake open a great chest with double locks and bolts, wherein was laid all the treasure of Milo, and ransackt the same: which when they had done they packed it up and gave every man a portion to carry: but when they had more than they could beare away, yet were they loth to leave any behind, but came into the stable, and took us two poore asses and my horse, and laded us with greater trusses than we were able to beare. And when we were out of the house, they followed us with great staves, and willed one of their fellows to tarry behind, and bring them tidings what was done concerning the robbery: and so they beat us forward over great hils out of the way. But I, what with my heavy burden and long journy, did nothing differ from a dead asse: wherfore I determined with myself to seek some civil remedy, and by invocation of the name of the prince of the country to be delivered from so many miseries: and on a time I passed through a great fair, I came among a multitude of Greeks, and I thought to call upon the renowned name of the Emperor and say, O Cesar, and cried out aloud O, but Cesar I could in no wise pronounce. The Theeves little regarding my crying, did lay me on and beat my wretched skinne in such sort, that after it was neither apt nor meet to make Sives or Sarces. Howbeit at last Jupiter administred to me an unhoped remedy. For when we had passed through many towns and villages, I fortuned to espy a pleasant garden, wherein beside many other flowers of delectable hiew, were new and fresh roses: and being very joyful, and desirous to catch some as I passed by, I drew neerer and neerer: and while my lips watered upon them, I thought of a better advice more profitable for me, lest if from an asse I should become a man, I might fall into the hands of the theeves, and either by suspition that I were some witch, or for feare that I should utter their theft, I should be slain, wherefore I abstained for that time from eating of Roses, and enduring my present adversity, I did eat hay as other Asses did.

Chapter XX

How Thrasileon was disguised in a bear’s skin, and how he was handled.

When the skin was a drying we made merry with the flesh, and then we devised with ourselves, that one of us being more valiant than the rest both in body and courage (so that he would consent thereto) should put on the skin, and feigning that he were a bear, should be led to Demochares’ house in the night, by which means we thought to be received and let in. Many were desirous to play the bear, but especially one Thrasileon of a courageous mind would take this enterprise in hand. Then we put him into the Bear’s skin, which fitted him finely in every point, we buckled it fast under his belly, and covered the seam with the hair, that it might not be seen. After this we made little holes through the bear’s head, and through his nostrils and eyes, for Thrasileon to see out and take wind at, in such sort that he seemed a very lively and natural beast: when this was done we went into a cave which we hired for the purpose, and he crept in after like a bear with a good courage. Thus we began our subtlety, and then we imagined thus, we feigned letters as though they came from one Nicanor which dwelt in the country of Thracia, which was of great acquaintance with this Demochares, wherein we wrote, that he had sent him being his friend, the first fruits of his coursing and hunting. When night was come, which was a meet time for our purpose, we brought Thrasileon and our forged letters and presented them to Demochares. When Demochares beheld this mighty bear, and saw the liberality of Nicanor his friend, he commanded his servants to deliver unto us ten crowns, having great store in his coffers. Then (as the novelty of a thing doth accustom to stir men’s minds to behold the same) many persons came on every side to see this bear: but Thrasileon, lest they should by curious viewing and prying perceive the truth, ran upon them to put them in fear that they durst not come nigh. The people said, Verily Demochares is right happy, in that after the death of so many beasts, he hath gotten meager fortunes head, so goodly a bear. Then Demochares commanded him with all care to be put in the park with all the other beasts: but immediately I spake unto him and said, Sir I pray you take heed how you put a beast tired with the heat of the sun and with long travel, among others which as I hear say have diverse maladies and diseases, let him rather lie in some open place in your house nigh some water, where he may take air and ease himself, for do you not know that such kind of beasts do greatly delight to couch under the shadow of trees and hillocks near pleasant wells and waters? Hereby Demochares admonished, and remembering how many he had before that perished, was contented that we should put the bear where we would. Moreover we said unto him, that we ourselves were determined to lie all night near the bear, to look unto him, and to give him meat and drink at his due hour.

Then he answered, Verily masters you need not put yourselves to such pains, for I have men that serve for nothing but that purpose. So we took leave of him and departed: and when we were come without the gates of the town, we perceived before us a great sepulchre standing out of the highway in a privy and secret place, and thither we went and opened the mouth thereof, whereas we found the sides covered with the corruption of man, and the ashes and dust of his long buried body, wherein we got ourselves to bring our purpose to pass, and having respect to the dark time of night, according to our custom, when we thought that everyone was asleep, we went with our weapons and besieged the house of Demochares round about. Then Thrasileon was ready at hand, and leaped out of the cavern, and went to kill all such as he found asleep: but when he came to the porter, he opened the gates and let us in, and then he showed us a large counter, wherein we saw the night before a great abundance of treasure: which when by violence we had broke open, I bid every one of my fellows take as much gold and silver as they could carry away: and bear it to the sepulchre, and still as they carried away I stood at the gate, watching diligently when they would return. The bear running about the house, to make such of the family afeared as fortuned to wake and come out. For who is he that is so puissant and courageous, that at the ugly sight of so great a monster will not quail and keep his chamber especially in the night? But when we had brought this matter to so good a point, there chanced a pitiful case, for as I looked for my companions that should come from the sepulchre, behold there was a boy of the house that fortuned to look out of a window, and espied the bear running about, and he went and told all the servants of the house. Whereupon incontinently they came forth with torches, lanterns, and other lights, that they might see all the yard over: they came with clubs, spears, naked swords, greyhounds, and mastiffs to slay the poor beast. Then I during this brawl thought to run away, but because I would see Thrasileon fight with the dogs, I lay behind the gate to behold him. And although I might perceive that he was well-nigh dead, yet remembered he his own faithfulness and ours, and valiantly resisted the gaping and ravenous mouths of the hellhounds, so took he in gree the pageant which willingly he took in hand himself, and with much ado tumbled at length out of the house: but when he was at liberty abroad yet could he not save himself, for all the dogs of the street joined themselves to the greyhounds and mastiffs of the house, and came upon him.

Alas what a pitiful sight it was to see our poor Thrasileon thus environed and compassed with so many dogs that tore and rent him miserably. Then I impatient of so great a misery, ran in among the press of people, and aiding him with my words as much as I might, exhorted them all in this manner: Oh great and extreme mischance, what a precious and excellent beast have we lost. But my words did nothing prevail, for there came out a tall man with a spear in his hand, that thrust him clean through, and afterwards many that stood by drew out their swords, and so they killed him. But verily our good captain Thrasileon, the honour of our comfort, received his death so patiently, that he would not bewray the league between us, either by crying, howling, or any other means, but being torn with dogs and wounded with weapons, did yield forth a doleful cry, more like unto a beast than a man. And taking his present fortune in good part, with courage and glory enough did finish his life, with such a terror unto the assembly, that no person was hardy until it was day, as to touch him, though he were stark dead: but at last there came a butcher more valiant than the rest, who opening the paunch of the beast, slit out an hardy and venturous thief.

In this manner we lost our captain Thrasileon, but he left not his fame and honour.

When this was done we packed up our treasure, which we committed to the sepulchre to keep, and got out of the bounds of Platea, thus thinking with ourselves, that there was more fidelity amongst the dead than amongst the living, by reason that our prize were so surely kept in the sepulchre. So being wearied with the weight of our burdens, and well-nigh tired with long travel, having lost three of our soldiers, we are come home with these present cheats.

Thus when they had spoken in memory of their slain companions, they took cups of gold, and sung hymns unto the god Mars, and laid them down to sleep. Then the old woman gave us fresh barley without measure, insomuch that my horse fed so abundantly that he might well think he was at some banquet that day. But I that was accustomed to eat bran and flour, thought that but a sour kind of meat. Wherefore espying a corner where lay loaves of bread for all the house I got me thither and filled my hungry guts therewith.

The Nineteenth Chapter

How Apuleius was prevented of his purpose, and how the Thieves came to their den.

Not long after, the thieves laded us again, but especially me, and brought us forth of the stable, and when we had gone a good part of our journey what with the long way, my great burden, the beating of staves, and my worn hooves, I was so weary that I could scantly go. Then I saw a little before me a river running with fair water, and I said to myself, Behold, now I have found a good occasion: for I will fall down when I come yonder, and surely I will not rise again, neither with scourging nor with beating, for I had rather be slain there presently, than go any further.

And the cause why I had determined so to do was this, I thought that the thieves when they did see me so feeble and weak that I could not travel, to the intent they would not stay in their journey, they would take the burden from my back and put it on my fellowes, and so for my further punishment to leave me as a prey to the wolves and ravening beasts. But evil fortune prevented so good a consideration; for the other Ass being of the same purpose that I was of, by feigned and coloured weariness fell down first, with all his burden on the ground as though he were dead, and he would not rise neither with beating nor with pricking, nor stand upon his legs, though they pulled him by the tail, by his legs, and by his ears: which when the thieves beheld, as without all hope they said one unto another, What should we stand here so long about a dead or rather a stony asse? let us be gone: and so they took his burden, and divided some to me, and some to my horse. And then they drew out their swords and cut off his legs, and threw his body from the point of a hill down into a great valley. Then I considering with myself of the evil fortune of my poor companion, and purposed now to forget all subtleity and deceit, and to play the good Ass to get my masters favour, for I perceived by their talke that we were come home well-nigh at our journeys end. And after that we had passed over a little hill, we came to our appointed place, and when we were unladen of our burdens, and all things carried in, I tumbled and wallowed in the dust, to refresh myself in stead of water. The thing and the time compelleth me to make description of the places, and especially of the den where the thieves did inhabit, I will prove my wit in what I can do, and the consider you whether I was an Ass in judgement and sence, or no. For first there was an exceeding great hill compassed about with big trees very high, with many turning bottoms full of sharp stones, whereby it was inaccessible. There was many winding and hollow valleys, environed with thickets and thornes, and naturaly fortressed round about. From the top of the hill ranne a running water as clear as silver, that watered all the valleyes below, that it seemed like unto a sea enclosed, or a standing flood. Before the denne where was no hill stood an high tower, and at the foot thereof were sheep-coats fenced and walled with clay. Before the gate of the house were pathes made in stead of wals, in such sort that you could easily judge it to be a very den for thieves, and there was nothing else except a little coat covered with thatch, wherein the thieves did nightly accustom to watch by order, as I after perceived. And when they were all crept into the house, and we were all tied fast with halters at the dore, they began to chide with an old woman there, crooked with age, who had the government and rule of all the house, and said, How is it old witch, old trot, and strumpet, that thou sittest idley all day at home, and having no regard to our perilous labours, hast provided nothing for our suppers, but sittest eating and swilling thyself from morning till night? Then the old woman trembled, and scantly able to speak gan say, Behold my puissant and faithful masters, you shall have meat and pottage enough by and by: here is first store of bread, wine plenty, filled in cleane rinsed pots, likewise here is hot water prepared to bathe you.

Which when she had said, they put off all their garments and refreshed themselves by the fire. And after they were washed and noynted with oyle, they sat down at the table garnished with all kind of dainty meats. They were no sooner sat down, but in came another company of young men more in number than was before, who seemed likewise to be Thieves, for they brought in their preyes of gold and silver, Plate, jewels, and rich robes, and when they had likewise washed, they sat among the rest, and served one another by order. Then they drank and eat exceedingly, laughing, crying and making much noise, that I thought that I was among the tyrannous and wild Lapithes, Thebans, and Centaures. At length one of them more valiant than the rest, spake in this sort, We verily have manfully conquered the house of Milo of Hippata, and beside all the riches and treasure which by force we have brought away, we are all come home safe, and are increased the more by this horse and this Asse. But you that have roved about in the country of Boetia, have lost your valiant captaine Lamathus, whose life I more regarded than all the treasure which you have brought: and therfore the memory of him shall be renowned forever amongst the most noble kings and valiant captains: but you accustom when you go abroad, like men with ganders hearts to creep through every corner and hole for every trifle. Then one of them that came last answered, Why are you only ignorant, that the greater the number is, the sooner they may rob and spoil the house? And although the family be dispersed in diverse lodgings, yet every man had rather to defend his own life, than to save the riches of his master: but when there be but a few thieves, then will they not only rather regard themselves, but also their substance, how little or great soever it be. And to the intent you may believe me I will show you an example: we were come nothing nigh to Thebes, where is the fountain of our art and science, but we learned where a rich Chuff called Chriseros did dwell, who for fear of offices in the publique well dissembled his estate, and lived sole and solitary in a small coat, howbeit replenished with aboundance of treasure, and went daily in ragged and torn apparel. Wherefore we devised with ourselves to go to his house and spoil him of all his riches. And when night came we drew towards the dore, which was so strongly closed, that we could neither move it, nor lift it out of the hooks, and we thought it best not to break it open lest by the noise we should raise up to our harm the neighbours by. Then our strong and valiant captaine Lamathus trusting in his own strength and force, thrust in his hand through a hole in the dore, and thought to pull back the bolt: but the covetous caitif Chriseros being awake, and making no noise came softly to the dore and caught his hand and with a great nail nailed it fast to the post: which when he had done, he ran up to the high chamber and called every one of his neighbours by name, desiring them to succour him with all possible speed, for his own house was on fire. Then everyone for fear of his own danger came running out to aid him, wherewith we fearing our present peril, knew not what was best to be don, whether we should leave our companion there, or yield ourselves to die with him: but we by his consent devised a better way, for we cut off his arm by the elbow and so let it hang there: then we bound his wound with clouts, lest we should be traced by the drops of blood: which don we took Lamathus and led him away, for fear we would be taken: but being so nigh pursued that we were in present danger, and that Lamathus could not keepe our company by reason of faintness; and on the other side perceiving that it was not for his profit to linger behind, he spake unto us as a man of singular courage and virtue, desiring us by much entreaty and prayer and by the puissance of the god Mars, and the faith of our confederacy, to deliver his body from torment and miserable captivity: and further he said, How is it possible that so courageous a Captaine can live without his hand, wherewith he could somtime rob and slay so many people? I would think myself sufficiently happy if I could be slain by one of you. But when he saw that we all refused to commit any such fact, he drew out his sword with his other hand, and after that he had often kissed it, he drove it clean through his body. Then we honoured the corps of so puissant a man, and wrapped it in linnen clothes and threw it into the sea. So lieth our master Lamathus, buried and did in the grave of water, and ended his life as I have declared. But Alcinus, though he were a man of great enterprise, yet could he not beware by Lamathus, nor voide himself from evil fortune, for on a day when he had entred into an old woman’s house to rob her, he went up into a high chamber, where he should first have strangled her: but he had more regard to throw down the bags of mony and gold out at a window, to us that stood under; and when he was so greedy that he would leave nothing behind, he went into the old woman’s bed where she lay asleep, and would have taken off the coverlet to have thrown down likewise, but she awaked, and kneeling on her knees, desired him in this manner: Oh sir I pray you cast not away such torn and ragged clouts into my neighbours houses, for they are rich enough, and need no such things. Then Alcinus thinking her words to be true, was brought in beliefe, that such things as he had thrown out already, and such things as he should throw out after, was not fallen down to his fellowes, but to other mens houses, wherefore he went to the window to see, and as he thought to behold the places round about, thrusting his body out of the window, the old woman marked him welL, and came behind him softly, and though she had but small strength, yet with sudden force she took him by the heels and thrust him out headlong, and so he fell upon a marvelous great stone and burst his ribs, whereby he vomited and spewed great flakes of blood, and presently died. Then we threw him to the river likewise, as we had done Lamathus before.

When we had thus lost two of our companions, we liked not Thebes, but marched towards the next city called Platea, where we found a man of great fame called Demochares, that purposed to set forth a great game, where should be a trial of all kind of weapons: he was come of a good house, marvelous rich, liberal, and well deserved that which he had and had prepared many showes and pleasures for the Common people, insomuch that there is no man can either by wit or eloquence show in words his worthy preparations: for first he had provided all sorts of armes, he greatly delighted in hunting and chasing, he ordained great towers and Tables to move hither and thither: he made many places to chase and encounter in: he had ready a great number of men and wild beasts, and many condemned persons were brought from the Judgement place, to try and fight with those beasts. But amongst so great preparations of noble price, he bestowed the most part of his patrimony in buying of Bears, which he nourished to his great cost, and esteemed more than all the other beasts, which either by chasing he caught himself, or which he dearely bought, or which were given him from diverse of his friends.

Howbeit for all his sumptuous cost, he could not be free from the malitious eyes of envy, for some of them were well-nigh dead with too long tying up, some meagre with the broiling heat of the sun, some languished with lying, but all having sundry diseases, were so afflicted that they died one after another, and there was well-nigh none left, in such sort that you might see them lying in the streets pittiously dead. And the common people having no other meat to feed on, little regarding any curiosity, would come forth and fill their bellies with the flesh of the bears. Then by and by Babulus and I devised a pretty sport, we drew one of the greatest of the Bears to our lodging, as though we would prepare to eat thereof, where we flayed of his skinne, and kept his ungles whole, but we medled not with the head, but cut it off by the neck, and so let it hang to the skinne. Then we rased off the flesh from the neck, and cast dust thereon, and set it in the sun to dry.

The Twentieth Chapter

How Thrasileon was disguised in a Bears skin, and how he was handled.

When the skin was a drying we made merry with the flesh, and then we devised with ourselves, that one of us being more valiant than the rest both in body and courage (so that he would consent thereto) should put on the skin, and feigning that he were a Bear, should be led to Demochares house in the night, by which means we thought to be received and let in. Many were desirous to play the Bear, but especially one Thrasileon of a couragious mind would take this enterprise in hand. Then we put in into the Bears skin, which him finely in every point, we buckled it fast under his belly, and covered the seam with the hair, that it might not be seen. After this we made little holes through the bears head, and through his nosthrils and eyes, for Thrasileon to see out and take wind at, in such sort that he seemed a very lively and natural beast: when this was don we went into a cave which we hired for the purpose, and he crept in after like a bear with a good courage. Thus we began our subtleity, and then we imagined thus, we feigned letters as though they came from one Nicanor which dwelt in the Country of Thracia, which was of great acquaintance with this Demochares, wherein we wrote, that he had sent him being his friend, the first fruits of his coursing and hunting. When night was come, which was a meet time for our purpose, we brought Thrasileon and our forged letters and presented them to Demochares. When Demochares beheld this mighty Bear, and saw the liberality of Nicanor his friend, he commanded his servants to deliver unto us x crowns, having great store in his coffers. Then (as the novelty of a thing doth accustom to stir mens minds to behold the same) many persons came on every side to see this bear: but Thrasileon, lest they should by curious viewing and prying perceive the truth, ran upon them to put them in fear that they durst not come nigh. The people said, Verily Demochares is right happy, in that after the death of so many beasts, he hath gotten maugre fortunes head, so goodly a bear. Then Demochares commanded him with all care to be put in the park with all the other beasts: but immediately I spake unto him and said, Sir I pray you take heed how you put a beast tired with the heat of the sun and with long travel, among others which as I hear say have diverse maladies and diseases, let him rather lie in some open place in your house nie some water, where he may take air and ease himself, for do you not know that such kind of beasts do greatly delight to couch under the shadow of trees and hillocks neer pleasant wells and waters? Hereby Demochares admonished, and remembering how many he had before that perished, was contented that we should put the bear where we would. Moreover we said unto him, that we ourselves were determined to lie all night neer the Bear, to look unto him, and to give him meat and drink at his due hour.

Then he answered, Verily masters you need not put yourselves to such pains, for I have men that serve for nothing but that purpose. So we took leave of him and departed: and when we were come without the gates of the town, we perceived before us a great sepulchre standing out of the highway in a privy and secret place, and thither we went and opened the mouth thereof, whereas we found the sides covered with the corruption of man, and the ashes and dust of his long buried body, wherein we got ourselves to bring our purpose to pass, and having respect to the dark time of night, according to our custom, when we thought that everyone was asleep, we went with our weapons and besieged the house of Demochares round about. Then Thrasileon was ready at hand, and leaped out of the cavern, and went to kill all such as he found asleep: but when he came to the Porter, he opened the gates and let us in, and then he showed us a large Counter, wherein we saw the night before a great aboundance of treasure: which when by violence we had broke open, I bid every one of my fellows take as much gold and silver as they could carry away: and bear it to the sepulchre, and still as they carried away I stood at the gate, watching diligently when they would return. The Bear running about the house, to make such of the family afeared as fortuned to wake and come out. For who is he that is so puissant and couragious, that at the ougly sight of so great a monster will not quayle and keep his chamber especially in the night? But when we had brought this matter to so good a point, there chanced a pitiful case, for as I looked for my companions that should come from the sepulchre, behold there was a Boy of the house that fortuned to look out of a window, and espied the Bear running about, and he went and told all the servants of the house. Whereupon incontinently they came forth with Torches, Lanternes, and other lights, that they might see all the yard over: they came with clubs, spears, naked swords, Greyhounds, and Mastifes to slay the poor beast. Then I during this broil thought to run away, but because I would see Thrasileon fight with the Dogs, I lay behind the gate to behold him. And although I might perceive that he was well-nigh dead, yet remembered he his own faithfulnes and ours, and valiantly resisted the gaping and ravenous mouths of the hell hounds, so took he in gree the pagiant which willingly he took in hand himself, and with much ado tumbled at length out of the house: but when he was at liberty abroad yet could he not save himself, for all the dogs of the Street joined themselves to the greyhounds and mastifes of the house, and came upon him.

Alas what a pitiful sight it was to see our poor Thrasileon thus environed and compassed with so many dogs that tare and rent him miserably. Then I impatient of so great a misery, ranne in among the prease of people, and aiding him with my words as much as I might, exhorted them all in this manner: Oh great and extreame mischance, what a pretious and excellent beast have we lost. But my words did nothing prevail, for there came out a tall man with a spear in his hand, that thrust him clean through, and afterwards many that stood by drew out their swords, and so they killed him. But verily our good Captain Thrasileon, the honour of our comfort, received his death so patiently, that he would not bewray the league between us, either by crying, howling, or any other means, but being torn with dogs and wounded with weapons, did yield forth a doleful cry, more like unto a beast than a man. And taking his present fortune in good part, with courage and glory enough did finish his life, with such a terror unto the assembly, that no person was hardy until it was day, as to touch him, though he were stark dead: but at last there came a Butcher more valiant than the rest, who opening the panch of the beast, slit out an hardy and ventrous thief.

In this manner we lost our Captain Thrasileon, but he left not his fame and honour.

When this was done we packed up our treasure, which we committed to the sepulchre to keep, and got out of the bounds of Platea, thus thinking with ourselves, that there was more fidelity amongst the dead than amongst the living, by reason that our preyes were so surely kept in the sepulchre. So being wearied with the weight of our burdens, and well-nigh tired with long travel, having lost three of our soldiers, we are come home with these present cheats.

Thus when they had spoken in memory of their slain companions, they took cups of gold, and sung hymns unto the god mars, and laid them down to sleep. Then the old woman gave us fresh barley without measure, insomuch that my horse fed so abundantly that he might well think he was at some banquet that day. But I that was accustomed to eat bran and flower, thought that but a sower kind of meat. wherefore espying a corner where lay loaves of bread for all the house I got me thither and filled my hungry guts therewith.

The Twenty-First Chapter

How the Thieves stole away a Gentlewoman, and brought her to their den.

When night was come the Thieves awaked and rose up, and when they had buckled on their weapons, and disguised their faces with visards, they departed. And yet for all the great sleep that came upon me, I could in no wise leave eating: and whereas when I was a man I could be contented with one or two loaves at the most, now my huts were so greedy that three panniers full would scantly serve me, and while I considered these things the morning came, and being led to a river, notwithstanding my Assie shamefastness I quencht my thirst. And suddenly after, the Thieves returned home careful and heavy, bringing no burdens with them, no not so much as traffe or baggage, save only a maiden, that seemed by her habit to be some gentlewoman borne, and the daughter of some worthy matron of that country, who was so fair and beautiful, that though I were an Asse, yet I had a great affection for her. The virgin lamented and tare her hair, and rent her garments, for the great sorrow she was in; but the thieves brought her within the cave, and assisted her to comfort in this sort, Weep not fair gentlewoman we pray you, for be you assured we will do no outrage or violence to your person: but take patience a while for our profit, for necessity and poor estate hath compelled us to do this enterprise: we warrant you that your parents, although they be covetous, will be contented to give us a great quantity of mony to redeem and ransom you from our hands.

With such and like flattering words they endeavoured to appease the gentlewoman, howbeit she would in no case be comforted, but put her head betwixt her knees, and cried pittiously. Then they called the old woman, and commanded her to sit by the maiden, and pacify her dolor as much as she might. And they departed away to rob, as they were accustomed to do, but the virgin would not asswage her griefs, nor mitigate her sorrow by any entreaty of the old woman, but howled and sobbed in such sort, that she made me poor Ass likewise to weep, and thus she said, Alas can I poor wench live any longer, that am come of so good a house, forsaken of my parents, friends, and family, made a rapine and prey, closed servilely in this stony prison, deprived of all pleasure, wherein I have been brought up, thrown in danger, ready to be rent in pieces among so many sturdy thieves and dreadful robbers, can I (I say) cease from weeping, and live any longer? Thus she cried and lamented, and after she had wearied herself with sorrow and blubbered her face with tears, she closed the windowes of her hollow eyes, and laid her down to sleep. And after that she had slept, she rose again like a furious and mad woman, and beat her breast and comely face more that she did before.

Then the old woman inquired the causes of her new and sudden lamentation. To whom sighing in pitiful sort she answered, Alas now I am utterly undone, now am I out of all hope, Oh give me a knife to kill me, or a halter to hang me. Whereat the old [woman] was more angry, and severely commanded her to tell her the cause of her sorrow, and why after her sleep, she should renew her dolour and miserable weeping. What, think you (quoth she) to deprive our young men of the price of your ransom? No, no therefore cease your crying, for the Thieves do little esteem your howling, and if you do not, I will surely burn you alive. Hereat the maiden was greatly feared, and kissed her hand and said, Oh mother take pity upon me and my wretched fortune, and give me license a while to speak, for I think I shall not long live, let there be mercy ripe and frank in thy venerable hoare head, and hear the sum of my calamity.

There was a comely young man, who for his bounty and grace was beloved entirely of all the town, my cousin Germane, and but three years older than I; we two were nourished and brought up in one house, lay under one roof, and in one chamber, and at length by promise of marriage, and by consent of our parents we were contracted together. The marriage day was come, the house was garnished with laurel, and torches were set in every place in the honour of Hymeneus, my espouse was accompanied by his parents, kinfolk, and friends, and made sacrifices in the temples and publique places. And when my unhappy mother pampered me in her lap, and decked me like a bride, kissing me sweetly, and making me a parent for Children, behold there came in a great multitude of thieves armed like men of warre, with naked swords in their hands, who went not about to do any harm, neither to take anything away, but brake into the chamber where I was, and violently took me out of my mother’s arms, when none of our family would resist for feare.

In this sort was our marriage disturbed, like the marriage of Hyppodame and Perithous. But behold my good mother, now my unhappy fortune is renewed and increased: For I dreamed in my sleep, that I was pulled out of our house, out of our chamber, and out of my bed, and that I removed about in solitary and unknown places, calling upon the name of my unfortunate husband, and how that he, as soon as he perceived that he was taken away, even smelling with perfumes and crowned with garlands, did trace me by the steppes, desiring the aid of the people to assist him, in that his wife was violently stollen away, and as he went crying up and down, one of the thieves moved with indignation, by reason of his pursuit, took up a stone that lay at his feet, and threw it at my husband and killed him. By the terror of which sight, and the fear of so dreadful a dream, I awaked.

Then the old woman rendring out like sighes, began to speak in this sort: My daughter take a good heart unto you, and be not afeared at feigned and strange visions and dreams, for as the visions of the day are accounted false and untrue, so the visions of the night do often change contrary. And to dream of weeping, beating, and killing, is a token of good luck and prosperous change. Whereas contrary to dream of laughing, carnal dalliance, and good cheer, is a sign of sadness, sickness, loss of substance, and displeasure. But I will tell thee a pleasant tale, to put away all thy sorrow, and to revive thy spirits. And so she began in this manner.

The Twenty-Second Chapter

The most pleasant and delectable tale of the marriage of Cupid and Psyches.

There was sometimes a certain King, inhabiting in the West parts, who had to wife a noble Dame, by whom he had three daughters exceeding fair: of whom the two elder were of such comly shape and beauty, as they did excel and pass all other women living, whereby they were thought worthily to deserve the praise and commendation of every person, and deservedly to be preferred above the residue of the common sort. Yet the singular passing beauty and maidenly majesty of the youngest daughter did so far surmount and excel then two, as no earthly creature could by any means sufficiently express or set out the same.

By reason whereof, after the fame of this excellent maiden was spread about in every part of the City, the Citisens and strangers therebeing inwardly pricked by the zealous affection to behold her famous person, came daily by thousands, hundreths, and scores, to her fathers palace, who was astonied with admiration of her incomparable beauty, did no less worship and reverence her with crosses, signs, and tokens, and other divine adorations, according to the custom of the old used rites and ceremonies, than if she were the Lady Venus indeed, and shortly after the fame was spread into the next cities and bordering regions, that the goddess whom the deep seas had born and brought forth, and the froth of the waves had nourished, to the intent to show her high magnificence and divine power on earth, to such as erst did honour and worship her, was now conversant among mortal men, or else that the earth and not the sea, by a new concourse and influence of the celestial planets, had budded and yielded forth a new Venus, endued with the flower of virginity.

So daily more and more increased this opinion, and now is her flying fame dispersed into the next Island, and well-nigh unto every part and province of the whole world. Whereupon innumerable strangers resorted from far Countries, adventuring themselves by long journies on land and by great perils on water, to behold this glorious virgin. By occasion whereof such a contempt grew towards the goddess Venus, that no person travelled unto the Town Paphos, nor to the Isle Gyndos, nor to Cythera to worship her. Her ornaments were thrown out, her temples defaced, her pillowes and cushions torn, her ceremonies neglected, her images and Statues uncrowned, and her bare altars unswept, and fowl with the ashes of old burnt sacrifice. For why, every person honoured and worshipped this maiden in stead of Venus, and in the morning at her first coming abroad offered unto her oblations, provided banquets, called her by the name of Venus, which was not Venus indeed, and in her honour presented flowers and garlands in most reverend fashion.

This sudden change and alteration of celestial honour, did greatly inflame and kindle the love of very Venus, who unable to temper herself from indignation, shaking her head in raging sort, reasoned with herself in this manner, Behold the original parent of all these elements, behold the Lady Venus renowned throughout all the world, with whom a mortal maiden is joined now partaker of honour: my name registred in the city of heaven is profaned and made vile by terrene absurdities. If I shall suffer any mortal creature to present my Majesty on earth, or that any shall bear about a false surmised shape of her person, then in vain did Paris the sheepheard (in whose judgement and competence the great Jupiter had affiance) preferre me above the residue of the goddesss, for the excellency of my beauty: but she, whatever she be that hath usurped mine honour, shal shortly repent her of her unlawful estate. And by and by she called her winged sonne Cupid, rash enough and hardy, who by his evil manners condemning all publique justice and law, armed with fire and arrowes, running up and down in the nights from house to house, and corrupting the lawful marriages of every person, doth nothing but that which is evil, who although that he were of his own proper nature sufficiently prone to work mischief, yet she egged him forward with words and brought him to the city, and showed him Psyches (for so the maid was called) and having told the cause of her anger, not without great rage, I pray thee (quoth she) my dear childe, by motherly bond of love, by the sweet wounds of thy piercing darts, by the pleasant heat of thy fire, revenge the injury which is done to thy mother by the false and disobedient beauty of a mortal maiden, and I pray thee, that without delay she may fall in love with the most miserablest creature living, the most poor, the most crooked, and the most vile, that there may be none found in all the world of like wretchedness. When she had spoken these words she embraced and kissed her sonne, and took her voyage toward the sea.

When she came upon the sea she began to cal the gods and goddesss, who were obedient at her voice. For incontinent came the daughters of Nereus, singing with tunes melodiously: Portunus with his bristled and rough beard, Salita with her bosom full of fish, Palemon the driver of the Dolphin, the Trumpetters of Tryton, leaping hither and thither, and blowing with heavenly noise: such was the company which followed Venus, marching towards the ocean sea.

In the mean season Psyches with all her beauty received no fruit of honor. She was wondred at of all, she was praised of all, but she perceived that no King nor Prince, nor any one of the superior sort did repair to woo her. Everyone marvelled at her divine beauty, as it were some Image well painted and set out. Her other two sisters, which were nothing so greatly exalted by the people, were royally married to two Kings: but the virgin Psyches, sitting alone at home, lamented her solitary life, and being disquieted both in mind and body, although she pleased all the world, yet hated she in herself her own beauty. Whereupon the miserable father of this unfortunate daughter, suspecting that the gods and powers of heaven did envy her estate, went to the town called Milet to receive the Oracle of Apollo, where he made his prayers and offered sacrifice, and desired a husband for his daughter: but Apollo though he were a Grecian, and of the country of Ionia, because of the foundation of Milet, yet he gave answer in Latin verse, the sence whereof was this:—

Let Psyches corps be clad in mourning weed,
And set on rock of yonder hill aloft:
Her husband is no wight of human seed,
But Serpent dire and fierce as might be thought.
Who flies with wings above in starry skies,
And doth subdue each thing with feiry flight.
The gods themselves, and powers that seem so wise,
With mighty Jove, be subject to his might,
The rivers black, and deadly floods of pain,
And darkness eke, as thrall to him remain.

The King, sometimes happy when he heard the prophesie of Apollo, returned home sad and sorrowful, and declared to his wife the miserable and unhappy fate of his daughter. Then they began to lament and weep, and passed over many days in great sorrow. But now the time approached of Psyches marriage, preparation was made, black torches were lighted, the pleasant songs were turned into pitiful cries, the melody of Hymeneus was ended with deadly howling, the maid that should be married did wipe her eyes with her vaile. All the family and people of the city weeped likewise, and with great lamentation was ordained a remiss time for that day, but necessity compelled that Psyches should be brought to her appointed place, according to the divine appointment.

And when the solemnity was ended, they went to bring the sorrowful spouse, not to her marriage, but to her final end and burial. And while the father and mother of Psyches did go forward weeping and crying unto this enterprise, Psyches spake unto them in this sort: Why torment your unhappy age with continual dolour? Why trouble you your spirits, which are more rather mine than yours? Why soyle ye your faces with tears, which I ought to adore and worship? Why tear you my eyes in yours? why pull you your hory hairs? Why knock ye your breasts for me? Now you see the reward of my excellent beauty: now, now you perceive, but too late, the plague of envy. When the people did honour me, and call me new Venus, then yee should have wept, then you should have sorrowed as though I had been dead: for now I see and perceive that I am come to this misery by the only name of Venus, bring me, and as fortune has appointed, place me on the top of the rock, I greatly desire to end my marriage, I greatly covet to see my husband. Why do I delay? why should I refuse him that is appointed to destroy all the world.

Thus ended she her words, and thrust herself among the people that followed. Then they brought her to the appointed rock of the high hill, and set [her] hereon, and so departed. The Torches and lights were put out with the tears of the people, and every man gone home, the miserable Parents well-nigh consumed with sorrow, gave themselves to everlasting darkness.

Thus poor Psyches being left alone, weeping and trembling on the toppe of the rock, was blown by the gentle air and of shrilling Zephyrus, and carried from the hill with a meek wind, which retained her garments up, and by little and little bought her down into a deep valley, where she was laid in a bed of most sweet and fragrant flowers.

Thus fair Psyches being sweetly couched among the soft and tender hearbs, as in a bed of sweet and fragrant flowers, and having qualified the thoughts and troubles of her restless mind, was now well reposed. And when she had refreshed herself sufficiently with sleep, she rose with a more quiet and pacified mind, and fortuned to espy a pleasant wood environed with great and mighty trees. She espied likewise a running river as clear as crystal: in the midst of the wood well-nigh at the fall of the river was a princely Edifice, wrought and builded not by the art or hand of man, but by the mighty power of God: and you would judge at the first entry therin, that it were some pleasant and worthy mansion for the powers of heaven. For the embowings above were of Citron and Ivory, propped and undermined with pillars of gold, the walls covered and seeled with silver, diverse sorts of beasts were graven and carved, that seemed to encounter with such as entered in. All things were so curiously and finely wrought, that it seemed either to be the work of some Demy god, or of God himself. The pavement was all of pretious stones, divided and cut one from another, whereon was carved diverse kinds of pictures, in such sort that blessed and thrice blessed were they that might go upon such a pavement: Every part and angle of the house was so well adorned, that by reason of the pretious stones and inestimable treasure there, it glittered and shone in such sort, that the chambers, porches, and doors gave light as it had been the Sun. Neither otherwise did the other treasure of the house disagree unto so great a majesty, that verily it seemed in every point an heavenly Palace, fabricate and built for Jupiter himself.

Then Psyches moved with delectation approched nigh and taking a bold heart entred into the house, and beheld everything there with great affection, she saw storehouses wrought exceedingly fine, and replenished with aboundance of riches. Finally, there could nothing be devised which lacked there: but among such great store of treasure this was most marvelous, that there was no closure, bolt, nor lock to keep the same. And when with great pleasure she had viewed all these things, she heard a voice without anybody, that said, Why do you marvel Madame at so great riches? behold, all that you see is at your commandment, wherefore go you into the chamber, and repose yourself upon the bed, and desire what bath you will have, and we whose voices you hear be your servants, and ready to minister unto you according to your desire. In the mean season, royal meats and dainty dishes shall be prepared for you.

Then Psyches perceived the felicity of divine providence, and according to the advertisement of the incorporeal voices she first reposed herself upon the bed, and then refreshed her body in the baines. This done, she saw the table garnished with meats, and a chair to sit down.

When Psyches was set down, all sorts of divine meats and wines were brought in, not by anybody, but as it were with a wind, for she saw no person before her, but only heard voices on every side. After that all the services were brought to the table, one came in and sung invisibly, another played on the harp, but she saw no man. The harmony of the Instruments did so greatly shrill in her ears, that though there were no manner of person, yet seemed she in the midst of a multitude of people.

All these pleasures finished, when night aproched Psyches went to bed, and when she was laid, that the sweet sleep came upon her, she greatly feared her virginity, because she was alone. Then came her unknown husband and lay with her: and after that he had made a perfect consummation of the marriage, he rose in the morning before day, and departed. Soon after came her invisible servants, and presented to her such things as were necessary for her defloration. And thus she passed forth a great while, and as it happeneth, the novelty of the things by continual custom did increase her pleasure, but especially the sound of the instruments was a comfort to her being alone.

During this time that Psyches was in this place of pleasures, her father and mother did nothing but weep and lament, and her two sisters hearing of her most miserable fortune, came with great dolour and sorrow to comfort and speak with her parents.

The night following, Psyches husband spake unto her (for she might feel his eyes, his hands, and his ears) and said, Oh my sweet Spouse and dear wife, fortune doth menace unto thee imminent danger, whereof I wish thee greatly to beware: for know that thy sisters, thinking that thou art dead, be greatly troubled, and are coming to the mountain by thy steps. Whose lamentations if thou fortune to hear, beware that thou do in no wise make answer, or look up towards them, for if thou do thou shalt purchase to me great sorrow, and to thyself utter destruction. Psyches hearing her Husband, was contented to do all things as he had commanded.

After that he was departed and the night passed away, Psyches lamented and lamented all the day following, thinking that now she was past all hopes of comfort, in that she was closed within the walls of a prison, deprived of human conversation, and commanded not to aid her sorrowful Sisters, no nor once to see them. Thus she passed all the day in weeping, and went to bed at night, without any refection of meat or baine.

Incontinently after came her husband, who when he had embraced her sweetly, began to say, Is it thus that I find you perform your promise, my sweet wife? What do I find heere? Pass you all the day and the night in weeping? And will you not cease in your husbands arms? go too, do what ye will, purchase your own destruction, and when you find it so, then remember my words, and repent but too late. Then she desired her husband more and more, assuring him that she should die, unless he would grant that she might see her sisters, whereby she might speak with them and comfort them, whereat at length he was contented, and moreover he willed that she should give them as much gold and jewels as she would. But he gave her a further charge saying, Beware that ye covet not (being moved by the pernicious counsel of you sisters) to see the shape of my person, lest by your curiosity you deprive yourself of so great and worthy estate. Psyches being glad herewith, rendered unto him most entire thanks, and said, Sweet husband, I had rather die than to be separated from you, for whosoever you be, I love and retain you within my heart, as if you were mine own spirit or Cupid himself: but I pray you grant this likewise, that you would command your servant Zephyrus to bring my sisters down into the valley as he brought me.

Wherewithal she kissed him sweetly, and desired him gently to grant her request, calling him her spouse, her sweetheart, her Joy and her Solace. Whereby she enforced him to agree to her mind, and when morning came he departed away.

After long search made, the sisters of Psyches came unto the hill where she was set on the rock, and cried with a loud voice in such sort that the stones answered again. And when they called their sister by her name, that their lamentable cries came unto her ears, she came forth and said, Behold, heere is she for whom you weep, I pray you torment yourselves no more, cease your weeping. And by and by she commanded Zephyrus by the appointment of her husband to bring them down. Neither did he delay, for with gentle blasts he retained them up and laid them softly in the valley. I am not able to express the often embracing, kissing and greeting which was between them three, all sorrows and tears were then laid apart.

Come in (quoth Psyches) into our house, and refresh your afflicted minds with your sister.

After this she showed them the storehouses of treasure, she caused them to hear the voices which served her, the bain was ready, the meats were brought in, and when they had filled themselves with divine delecates, they conceived great envy within their hearts, and one of them being curious, did demand what her husband was, of what estate, and who was Lord of so pretious a house? But Psyches remembering the promise which she had made to her husband, feigned that he was a young man, of comely stature, with a flaxen beard, and had great delight in hunting the dales and hills by. And lest by her long talk she should be found to trip or fail in her words, she filled their laps with gold, silver, and Jewels, and commanded Zephyrus to carry them away.

When they were brought up to the mountain, they made their ways homeward to their own houses, and murmured with envy that they bare against Psyches, saying, behold cruel and contrary fortune, behold how we, borne all of one Parent, have diverse destinies: but especially we that are the elder two be married to strange husbands, made as handmaidens, and as it were banished from our Country and friends. Whereas our younger sister hath great abundance of treasure, and hath gotten a god to her husband, although she hath no skill how to use such great plenty of riches. Saw you not sister what was in the house, what great store of jewels, what glittering robes, what Gemmes, what gold we trod on? That if she hath a husband according as she affirmeth, there is none that liveth this day more happy in all the world than she. And so it may come to pass, at length for the great affection which he may bear unto her that he may make her a goddess, for by Hercules, such was her countenance, so she behaved herself, that as a goddess she had voices to serve her, and the winds did obey her.

But I poor wretch have first married an husband elder than my father, more bald than a Coot, more weak than a childe, and that locketh me up all day in the house.

Then said the other sister, And in faith I am married to a husband that hath the gout, twyfold, crooked, nor couragious in paying my debt, I am fain to rub and mollify his stony fingers with diverse sorts of oils, and to wrap them in playsters and salves, so that I soyle my white and dainty hands with the corruption of filthy clouts, not using myself like a wife, but more like a servant. And you my sister seem likewise to be in bondage and servitude, wherefore I cannot abide to see our younger sister in such felicity; saw you not I pray you how proudly and arrogantly she handled us even now? And how in vaunting herself she uttered her presumptuous mind, how she cast a little gold into our laps, and being weary of our company, commanded that we should be borne and blown away?

Verily I live not, nor am a woman, but I will deprive her of all her bliss. And if you my sister be so far bent as I, let us consult together, and not to utter our mind to any person, no not to our parents, nor tell that ever we saw her. For it sufficeth that we have seen her, whom it repenteth to have seen. Neither let us declare her good fortune to our father, nor to any other, since as they seem not happy whose riches are unknown: so shall she know that she hath sisters no Abjects, but worthier than she.

But now let us go home to our husbands and poor houses, and when we are better instructed, let us return to suppress her pride. So this evil counsel pleased these two evil women, and they hid the treasure which Psyches gave them, and tare their hair, renewing their false and forged tears. When their father and mother beheld them weep and lament still, they doubled their sorrowes and griefs, but full of ire and forced with Envy, they took their voyage homeward, devising the slaughter and destruction of their sister.

In the mean season the husband of Psyches did warn her again in the night with these words: Seest thou not (quoth he) what peril and danger evil fortune doth threaten unto thee, whereof if thou take not good heed it will shortly come upon thee. For the unfaithful harlots do greatly endeavor to set their snares to catch thee, and their purpose is to make and persuade thee to behold my face, which if thou once fortune to see, as I have often told, thou shalt see no more. Wherefore if these naughty hags, armed with wicked minds, do chance to again (as I think no otherwise but that they will) take heed that thou talk not with them but simply suffer them to speak what they will, howbeit if thou canst not refrain thyself, beware that thou have no communication of thy husband, nor answer a word if they fortune to question of me, so will we increase our stock, and this young and tender childe, couched in this young and tender belly of thine, shall be made an immortal god, otherwise a mortal creature. Then Psyches was very glad that she should bring forth a divine babe, and very joyful in that she should be honored as a mother. She reckened and numbered carefully the days and months that passed, and being never with child before, did marvel greatly that in so short a time her belly should swel so big. But those pestilent and wicked furies breathing out their Serpentine poison, took shipping to bring their enterprise to pass. The Psyches was warned again by her husband in this sort: Behold the last day, the extream case, and the enemies of thy blood, hath armed themselves against us, pitched their camp, set their host in array, and are marching towards us, for now thy two sisters have drawn their swords and are ready to slay thee. Oh with what force are we assaild on this day! Oh sweet Psyches I pray thee to take pity on thyself, of me, and deliver thy husband and this infant within thy belly from so great danger, and see not, neither hear these cursed women, which are not worthy to be called thy sisters, for their great hatred and breach of sisterly amity, for they will come like Syrens to the mountains, and yield out their pittious and lamentable cries. When Psyches had heard these words she sighed sorrowfully and said, Oh dear husband this long time have you had experience and trial of my faith, and doubt you not that I will persever in the same, wherefore command your wind Zephyrus, that he may do as he hath done before, to the intent that where you have charged me not to behold your venerable face, yet that I may comfort myself with the sight of my sisters. I pray you by these beautiful hairs, by these round cheekes delicate and tender, by your pleasant hot breast, whose shape and face I shall learn at length by the childe in my belly, grant the fruit of my desire, refresh your dear Spouse Psyches with joy, who is bound and linked unto you forever. I little esteem to see your visage and figure, little do I regard the night and darkness thereof, for you are my only light.

Her husband being as it were enchanted with these words and compelled by violence of her often embracing, wiping away her tears with his hair, did yield unto his wife. And when morning came, departed as he was accustomed to do.

Now her sisters arrived on land, and never rested til they came to the rock, without visiting their parents, and leapt down rashly from the hill themselves. Then Zephyrus according to the divine commandment brought them down, although it were against his will, and laid them in the vally without any harm: by and by they went into the palace to their sister without leave, and when they had eftsoone embraced their prey, and thanked her with flattering words for the treasure which she gave them, they said, Oh dear sister Psyches, know you that you are now no more a child, but a mother: Oh what great joy bear you unto us in your belly? What a comfort will it be unto all the house? How happy shall we be, that shall see this Infant nourished amongst so great plenty of Treasure? That if he be like his parents, as it is necessary he should, there is no doubt but a new cupid shall be borne. By this kind of measures they went about to winne Psyches by little and little, but because they were wearie with travel, they sat them down in chairs, and after that they had washed their bodies in baines they went into a parlour, where all kind of meats were ready prepared. Psyches commanded one to play with his harp, it was done. Then immediately others sung, others tuned their instruments, but no person was seen, by whose sweet harmony and modulation the sisters of Psyches were greatly delighted.

Howbeit the wickedness of these cursed women was nothing suppressed by the sweet noise of these instruments, but they settled themselves to work their treasons against Psyches, demanding who was her husband, and of what Parentage. Then she having forgotten by too much simplicity, what she had spoken before of her husband, invented a new answer, and said that her husband was of a great province, a merchant, and a man of middle age, having his beard intersparsed with grey hairs. Which when she had spoken (because she would have no further talk) she filled their laps with Gold and Silver, and bid Zephyrus to bear them away.

In their return homeward they murmured within themselves, saying, How say you sister to so apparent a lye of Psyches? First she said that her husband was a young man of flourishing years, and had a flaxen beard, and now she sayth that he is half grey with age. What is he that in so short a space can become so old? You shall find it no otherwise my sister, but that either this cursed queane hath invented a great lie, or else that she never saw the shape of her husband. And if it be so that she never saw him, then verily she is married to some god, and hath a young god in her belly. But if it be a divine babe, and fortune to come to the ears of my mother (as God forbid it should) then may I go and hang myself: wherefore let us go to our parents, and with forged lies let us colour the matter.

After they were thus inflamed, and had visited their Parents, they returned again to the mountain, and by the aid of the wind Zephyrus were carried down into the valley, and after they had streined their eye lids, to enforce themselves to weep, they called unto Psyches in this sort, Thou (ignorant of so great evil) thinkest thyself sure and happy, and sittest at home nothing regarding thy peril, whereas we go about thy affairs and are careful lest any harm should happen unto you: for we are credibly informed, neither can we but utter it unto you, that there is a great serpent full of deadly poison, with a ravenous gaping throat, that lieth with thee every night. Remember the Oracle of Apollo, who pronounced that thou shouldest be married to a dire and fierce Serpent, and many of the Inhabitants hereby, and such as hunt about in the country, affirm that they saw him yesternight returning from pasture and swimming over the River, whereby they do undoubtedly say, that he will not pamper thee long with delicate meats, but when the time of delivery shall approach he will devour both thee and thy child: wherefore advise thyself whether thou wilt agree unto us that are careful of thy safety, and so avoid the peril of death, be contented to live with thy sisters, or whether thou remain with the Serpent and in the end be swallowed into the gulf of his body. And if it be so that thy solitary life, thy conversation with voices, this servile and dangerous pleasure, and the love of the Serpent do more delight thee, say not but that we have played the parts of natural sisters in warning thee.

Then the poor and simple miser Psyches was moved with the fear of so dreadful words, and being amazed in her mind, did clean forget the admonitions of her husband, and her own promises made unto him, and throwing herself headlong into extreame misery, with a wanne and sallow countenance, scantly uttering a third word, at length gan say in this sort: Oh my most dear sisters, I heartily thank you for your great kindness toward me, and I am now verily persuaded that they which have informed you hereof hath informed you of nothing but truth, for I never saw the shape of my husband, neither know I from whence he came, only I hear his voice in the night, insomuch that I have an uncertain husband, and one that loveth not the light of the day: which causeth me to suspect that he is a beast, as you affirm. Moreover, I do greatly fear to see him, for he doth menace and threaten great evil unto me, if I should go about to spy and behold his shape wherefore my loving sisters if you have any wholeome remedy for your sister in danger, give it now presently. Then they opened the gates of their subtlel minds, and did put away all privy guile, and egged her forward in her fearefull thoughts, persuading her to do as they would have her whereupon one of them began and said, Because that we little esteem any peril or danger, to save your life we intend to show you the best way and mean as we may possibly do. Take a sharp razor and put it under the pillow of your bed; and see that you have ready a privy burning lamp with oyle, hid under some part of the hanging of the chamber, and finely dissembling the matter when according to his custom he commeth to bed and sleepth soundly, arise you secretly, and with your bare feet go and take the lamp, with the Razor in your right hand and with valiant force cut off the head of the poisonous serpent, wherein we will aid and assist you: and when by the death of him you shall be made safe, we will marry you to some comely man.

After they had thus inflamed the heart of their sister fearing lest some danger might happen unto them by reason of their evil counsel, they were carried by the wind Zephyrus to the top of the mountain, and so they ran away and took shipping.

When Psyches was left alone (saving that she seemed not to be alone, being stirred by so many furies) she was in a tossing mind like the waves of the sea, and although her will was obstinate, and resisted to put in execution the counsel of her Sisters, yet she was in l and diverse opinions touching her calamity. Sometime she would, sometime she would not, sometime she is bold, sometime she feareth, sometime she mistrusteth, somtime she is moved, somtime she hateth the beast, somtime she loveth her husband: but at length night came, when as she prepared for her wicked intent.

Soon after her husband Came, and when he had kissed and embraced her he fell asleep. Then Psyches (somwhat feeble in body and mind, yet moved by cruelty of fate) received boldnes and brought forth the lamp, and took the razor, so by her audacity she changed her mind: but when she took the lamp and came to the bed side, she saw the most meek and sweetest beast of all beasts, even fair Cupid couched fairly, at whose sight the very lamp increased his light for joy, and the razor turned his edge.

But when Psyches saw so glorious a body she greatly feared, and amazed in mind, with a pale countenance all trembling fel on her knees and thought to hide the razor, yea verily in her own heart, which doubtless she had done, had it not through fear of so great an enterprise fallen out of her hand. And when she saw and beheld the beauty of the divine visage she was well recreated in her mind, she saw his hairs of gold, that yielded out a sweet savor, his neck more white than milk, his purple cheeks, his hair hanging comely behind and before, the brightness whereof did darken the light of the lamp, his tender plume feathers, dispersed upon his sholders like shining flours, and trembling hither and thither, and his other parts of his body so smooth and so soft, that it did not repent Venus to bear such a childe. At the beds feet lay his bow, quiver, and arrowes, that be the weapons of so great a god: which when Psyches did curiously behold, she marvelling at her husbands weapons, took one of the arrows out of the quiver, and pricked herself withall, wherewith she was so grievously wounded that the blood followed, and thereby of her own accord she added love upon love; then more broiling in the love of Cupid she embraced him and kissed him and kissed him a thousand times, fearing the measure of his sleep. But alas while she was in this great joy, whether it were for envy for desire to touch this amiable body likewise, there fell out a droppe of burning oyle from the lamp upon the right shoulder of the god. Oh rash and bold lamp, the vile ministery of love, how darest thou be so bold as to burn the god of all fire? When as he invented thee, to the intent that all lovers might with more joy pass the nights in pleasure.

The godbeing burned in this sort, and perceiving that promise and faith was broken, be fled away without utterance of any word, from the eyes and hands of his most unhappy wife. But Psyches fortuned to catch him as he was rising by the right thigh, and held him fast as he flew above in the air, until such time as constrained by weariness she let go and fell down upon the ground. But Cupid followed her down, and lighted upon the top of a Cypress tree, and angerly spake unto her in this manner: Oh simple Psyches, consider with thyself how I, little regarding the commandment of my mother (who willed me that thou shouldst be married to a man of base and miserable condition) did come myself from heaven to love thee, and wounded mine own body with my proper weapons, to have thee to my Spouse: And did I seem a beast unto thee, that thou shouldst go about to cut off my head with a razor, who loved thee so well? Did not I always give thee a charge? Did not I gently will thee to beware? But those cursed aides and Counselors of thine shall be worthily rewarded for their pains. As for thee thou shalt be sufficiently punished by my absence. When he had spoken these words he took his flight into the air. Then Psyches fell flat on the ground, and as long as she could see her husband she cast her eyes after him into the air, weeping and lamenting pitteously: but when he was gone out of her sight she threw herself into the next running river, for the great anguish and dolour that she was in for the lack of her husband, howbeit the water would not suffer her to be drowned, but took pity upon her, in the honour of Cupid which accustomed to broil and burn the river, and threw her upon the bank amongst the herbs.

Then Pan the rustical god sitting on the river side, embracing and [instructing] the goddess Canna to tune her songs and pipes, by whom were feeding the young and tender Goats, after that he perceived Psyches in sorrowful case, not ignorant (I know not by what means) of her miserable estate, endeavored to pacific her in this sort: Oh fair maid, I am a rustic and rude heardsman, howbeit by reason of my old age expert in many things, for as far as I can learnt by conjecture (which according as wise men do term is called divination) I perceive by your uncertain gate, your pale hew, your sobbing sighes, and your watery eyes, that you are greatly in love. Wherefore hearken to me, and go not about to slay yourself, nor weep not at all, but rather adore and worship the great god Cupid, and winne him unto you by your gentle promise of service.

When the god of Shepherds had spoken these words, she gave no answer, but made reverence to him as to a god, and so departed.

After that Psyches had gone a little way, she fortuned unawares to come to a city where the husband of one of her Sisters did dwell. Which when Psyches did understand, she caused that her sister had knowledge of her coming, and so they met together, and after great embracing and salutation, the sister of Psyches demanded the cause of her travel thither. Marry (quoth she) do you not remember the counsel you gave me, whereby you would that I should kill the beast which under colour of my husband did lie with me every night? You shall understand, that as soon as I brought forth the lamp to see and behold his shape, I perceived that he was the sonne of Venus, even Cupid himself that lay with me. Then I being stricken with great pleasure, and desirous to embrace him, could not thoroughly asswage my delight, but alas by evil ill chance the oyle of the lamp fortuned to fall on his shoulder which caused him to awake, and seeing me armed with fire and weapons, gan say, How darest thou be so bold to do so great a mischief? Depart from me and take such things as thou didst bring: for I will have thy sister (and named you) to my wife, and she shall be placed in thy felicity, and by and by he commanded Zephyrus to carry me away from the bounds of his house.

Psyches had scantly finished her tale but her sister pierced with the prick of carnal desire and wicked envy ran home, and feigning to her husband that she had heard word of the death of her parents took shipping and came to the mountain. And although there blew a contrary wind, yet being brought in a vain hope she cried Oh Cupid take me a more worthy wife, and thou Zephyrus bear down thy mistress, and so she cast herself headlong from the mountain: but she fell not into the valley neither alive nor dead, for all the members and parts of her body were torn amongst the rocks, whereby she was made prey unto the birds and wild beasts, as she worthily deserved.

Neither was the vengeance of the other delayed, for Psyches travelling in that country, fortuned to come to another city where her other sister did dwel; to whom when she had declared all such things as she told to her other sister she ran likewise unto the rock and was slain in like sort. Then Psyches travelled about in the country to seek her husband Cupid, but he was gotten into his mother’s chamber and there bewaild the sorrowful wound which he caught by the oyle of a burning lamp.

Then the white bird the Gull, which swims on the waves of the water, flew toward the Ocean sea, where he found Venus washing and bathing herself: to whom she declared that her son was burned and in danger of death, and moreover that it was a common brute in the mouth of every person (who spake evil of all the family of Venus) that her son doth nothing but haunt harlots in the mountain, and she herself lasciviously use to ryot in the sea: whereby they say that they are now become no more gratious, pleasant nor gentle, but incivile, monstrous and horrible. Moreover, that marriages are not for any amity, or for love of procreation, but full of envy, discord, and debate. This the curious Gul did clatter in the ears of Venus, reprehending her son. But Venus began to cry and said, What hath my sonne gotten any Love? I pray thee gentle bird that doest serve me so faithfully, tell me what she is, and what is her name that hath troubled my son in such sort? whether she be any of the Nymphs, of the number of the goddesss, of the company of the Muses, or of the mistery of the Graces? To whom the bird answered, Madam I know not what she is, but this I know that she is called Psyches. Then Venus with indignation cried out, What is it she? the usurper of my beauty, the Vicar of my name? What did he think that I was a bawd, by whose show he fell acquainted with the maid? And immediately she departed and went to her chamber, where she found her son wounded as it was told unto her, whom when she beheld she cries out in this sort.

Is this an honest thing, is this honourable to thy parents? is this reason, that thou hast violated and broken the commandment of thy mother and soveraign mistress: and whereas thou shouldst have vexed my enemy with loathsom love, thou hast done otherwise?

For being of tender and unripe years, thou hast with too licentious appetite embraced my most mortal Foe, to whom I shall be made a mother, and she a Daughter.

Thou presumest and thinkest, thou trifling boy, thou Varlet, and without all reverence, that thou art most worthy and excellent, and that I am not able by reason of mine age to have another son, which if I should have, thou shouldst well understand that I would bear a more worthier than thou. But to work thee a greater despight, I do determine to adopt one of my servants, and to give him these wings, this fire, this bow, and these Arrowes, and all other furniture which I gave to thee, not to this purpose, neither is anything given thee of thy father for this intent: but first thou hast been evil brought up and instructed in thy youth thou hast thy hands ready and sharp. Thou hast often offended thy ancients, and especially me that am thy mother, thou hast pierced me with thy darts thou condemnest me as a widow, neither dost thou regard thy valiant and invincible father, and to anger me more, thou art amorous of harlots and wenches: hot I will cause that thou shalt shortly repent thee, and that this marriage shal be dearly bought. To what a point am I now driven? What shall I do? Whither shall I go? How shall I repress this beast? Shall I ask aid of mine enemy Sobriety, whom I have often offended to engender thee? Or shall I seek for counsel of every poor rustical woman? No, no, yet had I ratherdie, howbeit I will not cease my vengeance, to her must I have recourse for help, and to none other (I mean to Sobriety), who may correct thee sharply, take away thy quiver, deprive thee of thy arrowes, unbend thy bow, quench thy fire, and which is more subdue thy body with punishment: and when that I have rased and cut off this thy hair, which I have dressed with mine own hands, and made to glitter like gold, and when I have clipped thy wings, which I myself have caused to burgen, then shall I think to have revenged myself sufficiently upon thee for the injury which thou hast done. When she had spoken these words she departed in a great rage out of her chamber.

Iimmediately as she was going away came Juno and Ceres, demanding the cause of her anger. Then Venus answered, Verily you are come to comfort my sorrow, but I pray you with all diligence to seek out one whose name is Psyches, who is a vagabond, and runneth about the Countries, and (as I think) you are not ignorant of the brute of my son Cupid, and of his demeanour, which I am ashamed to declare. Then they understanding the whole matter, endeavoured to mitigate the ire of Venus in this sort: What is the cause Madam, or how hath your son so offended, that you shold so greatly accuse his love, and blame him by reason that he is amorous? and why should you seek the death of her, whom he doth fancie? We most humbly intreat you to pardon his fault if he have accorded to the mind of any maiden: what do you not know that he is a young man? Or have you forgotten of what years he is? Doth he seem always unto you to be a childe? You are his mother, and a kind woman, will you continually search out his dalliance? Will you blame his luxury? Will you bridle his love? and will you reprehend your own art and delights in him? What God or man is he, that can endure that you should sowe or disperse your seed of love in every place, and to make restraint thereof within your own doors? certes you will be the cause of the suppression of the publike paces of young Dames. In this sort this goddess endeavoured to pacifie her mind, and to excuse Cupid with al their power (although he were absent) for fear of his darts and shafts of love. But Venus would in no wise asswage her heat, but (thinking that they did rather trifle and taunt at her injuries) she departed from them, and took her voiage towards the sea in all haste. In the mean season Psyches hurled herself hither and thither, to seek her husband, the rather because she thought that if he would not be appeased with the sweet flattery of his wife, yet he would take mercy on her at her servile and continual prayers. And (espying a Church on the top of a high hill) she said, What can I tell whether my husband and master be there or no? wherefore she went thitherward, and with great pain and travel, moved by hope, after that she climbed to the top of the mountain, she came to the temple, and went in, whereas behold she espied sheffes of corn lying on a heap, blades withered with garlands, and reeds of barly, moreover she saw hooks, sithes, sickles, and other instruments, to reap, but everything lay out of order, and as it were cast in by the hands of laborers which when Psyches saw she gathered up and put everything in order, thinking that she would not despise or condemne the temples of any of the Gods, but rather get the favour and benevolence of them all: by and by Ceres came in, and beholding her busy and curious in her chapel, cried out a far off, and said, Oh Psyches needful of mercy, Venus searcheth for thee in every place to revenge herself and to punish thee grievously, but thou hast more mind to be heere, and carest for nothing less, then for thy safety. Then Psyches fell on her knees before her, watring her feet with her tears, wiping the ground with her hair, and with great weeping and lamentation desired pardon, saying, Oh great and holy Goddess, I pray thee by thy plenteous and liberal right hand, by the joyful ceremonies of thy harvest, by the secrets of thy Sacrifice, by the flying chariots of thy dragons, by the tillage of the ground of Sicilie, which thou hast invented, by the marriage of Proserpin, by the diligent inquisition of thy daughter, and by the other secrets which are within the temple of Eleusis in the land of Athens, take pity on me thy servant Psyches, and let me hide myself a few days amongst these sheffes of corn, until the ire of so great a Goddess be past, or until that I be refreshed of my great labour and travel. Then answered Ceres, Verely Psyches, I am greatly moved by thy prayers and tears, and desire with all my heart to aide thee, but if I should suffer thee to be hidden here, I should increase the displeasure of my Cosin, with whom I have made a treaty of peace, and an ancient promise of amity: wherefore I advise thee to depart hence and take it not in evil part in that I will not suffer thee to abide and remain here within my temple. Then Psyches driven away contrary to her hope, was double afflicted with sorrow and so she returned back again. And behold she perceived a far off in a vally a Temple standing within a Forest, fair and curiously wrought, and minding to overpass no place whither better hope did direct her, and to the intent she would desire pardon of every God, she approached nigh unto the sacred door, whereas she saw pretious riches and vestiments engraven with letters of gold, hanging upon branches of trees, and the posts of the temple testifying the name of the goddess Juno, to whom they were dedicate, then she kneeled down upon her knees, and embraced the Alter with her hands, and wiping her tears, gan pray in this sort: Oh deere spouse and sister of the great God Jupiter which art adored and worshipped amongst the great temples of Samos, called upon by women with child, worshipped at high Carthage, because thou wast brought from heaven by the lyon, the rivers of the flood Inachus do celebrate thee: and know that thou art the wife of the great god, and the goddess of goddesss; all the east part of the world have thee in veneration, all the world calleth thee Lucina: I pray thee to be my advocate in my tribulations, deliver me from the great danger which pursueth me, and save me that am weary with so long labours and sorrow, for I know that it is thou that succorest and helpest such women as are with child and in danger. Then Juno hearing the prayers of Psyches, appeared unto her in all her royalty, saying, Certes Psyches I would gladly help thee, but I am ashamed to do anything contrary to the will of my daughter in law Venus, whom alwaies I have loved as mine own child, moreover I shall incurre the danger of the law, entitled, De servo corrupto, whereby am forbidden to retain any servant fugitive, against the will of his Master. Then Psyches cast off likewise by Juno, as without all hope of the recovery of her husband, reasoned with herself in this sort: Now what comfort or remedy is left to my afflictions, when as my prayers will nothing avail with the goddesss? what shall I do? whither shall I go? In what cave or darkness shall I hide myself, to avoid the furor of Venus? Why do I not take a good heart, and offer myself with humility unto her, whose anger I have wrought? What do I know whether he (whom I seek for) be in his mother’s house or no? Thus being in doubt, poor Psyches prepared herself to her own danger, and devised how she might make her orison and prayer unto Venus. After that Venus was weary with searching by Sea and Land for Psyches, she returned toward heaven, and commanded that one should prepare her Chariot, which her husband Vulcanus gave unto her by reason of marriage, so finely wrought that neither gold nor silver could be compared to the brightness therof. Four white pigeons guided the chariot with great diligence, and when Venus was entred in a number of sparrowes flew chirping about, making sign of joy, and all other kind of birds sang sweetly, foreshewing the coming of the great goddess: the clouds gave place, the heavens opened, and received her joyfully, the birds that followed nothing feared the Eagle, Hawkes, or other ravenous foules of the air. Incontinently she went unto the royal Pallace of God Jupiter, and with a proud and bold petition demanded the service of Mercury, in certain of her affairs, whereunto Jupiter consented: then with much joy she descended from Heaven with Mercury, and gave him an earnest charge to put in execution her words, saying: Oh my Brother, borne in Arcadia, thou knowest well, that I (who am thy sister) did never enterprise to do anything without thy presence, thou knowest also how long I have sought for a girl and cannot find her, wherefore there resteth nothing else save that thou with thy trumpet do pronounce the reward to such as take her: see thou put in execution my commandment, and declare that whatsoever he be that retaineth her wittingly, against my will shall not defend himself by any mean or excusation: which when she had spoken, she delivered unto him a libel, wherein was contained the name of Psyches, and the residue of his publication, which done, she departed away to her lodging. By and by, Mercurius (not delaying the matter) proclaimed throughout all the world, that whatsoever he were that could tell any tidings of a Kings fugitive Daughter, the servant of Venus, named Psyches, should bring word to Mercury, and for reward of his pains, he should receive seaven sweet kisses of Venus. After that Mercury had pronounced these things, every man was enflamed with desire to search out Psyches.

This proclamation was the cause that put all doubt from Psyches, who was scantly come in the sight of the house of Venus, but one of her servants called Custome came out, who espying Psyches, cried with a loud voice, saying: Oh wicked harlot as thou art, now at length thou shalt know that thou hast a mistress above thee. What, dost thou make thyself ignorant, as though thou didst not understand what travel we have taken in searching for thee? I am glad that thou art come into my hands, thou art now in the golfe of hell, and shalt abide the pain and punishment of thy great contumacy, and therewithal she took her by the hair, and brought her in, before the presence of the goddess Venus. When Venus spied her, she began to laugh, and as angry persons accustom to do, she shaked her head, and scratched her right ear saying, Oh goddess, goddess, you are now come at length to visit your husband that is in danger of death, by your means: be you assured, I will handle you like a daughter: where be my maidens, Sorrow and Sadness? To whom (when they came) she delivered Psyches to be cruelly tormented; then they fulfilled the commandment of their mistress, and after they had piteously scourged her with rods and whips, they presented her again before Venus; then she began to laugh again, saying: Behold she thinketh (that by reason of her great belly, which she hath gotten by playing the whore) to move me to pity, and to make me a grandmother to her childe. Am not I happy, that in the flourishing time of al mine age, shall be called a grandmother, and the sonne of a vile harlot shall be accounted the nephew of Venus: howbeit I am a fool to tearm him by the name of my son, since as the marriage was made between unequal persons, in the field without witnesses, and not by the consent of parents, wherefore the marriage is illegitimate, and the childe (that shall be borne) a bastard; if we fortune to suffer thee to live so long till thou be delivered. When Venus had spoken these words she leaped upon the face of poor Psyches, and (tearing her apparel) took her by the hair, and dashed her head upon the ground. Then she took a great quantity of wheat, of barly, poppy seed, peason, lintles, and beanes, and mingled them altogether on a heap saying: Thou evil favoured girl, thou seemest unable to get the grace of thy lover, by no other means, but only by diligent and painfull service, wherefore I will prove what thou canst do: see that thou separate all these grains one from another, disposing them orderly in their quantity, and let it be done before night. When she had appointed this task unto Psyches, she departed to a great banket that was prepared that day. But Psyches went not about to dissever the grain, (as being a thing impossible to be brought to pass by reason it lay so confusedly scattered) but being astonyed at the cruel commandment of Venus, sat still and said nothing. Then the little pismire the emote, taking pity of her great difficulty and labour, cursing the cruelness of the daughter of Jupiter, and of so evil a mother, ran about, hither and thither, and called to all her friends, Yee quick sons of the ground, the mother of all things, take mercy on this poor maid, espouse to Cupid, who is in great danger of her person, I pray you help her with all diligence. Incontinently one came after another, dissevering and dividing the grain, and after that they had put each kind of corn in order, they ranne away again in all haste. When night came, Venus returned home from the banket well tippled with wine, smelling of balm, and crowned with garlands of roses, who when she had espied what Psyches had done, gan say, This is not the labour of thy hands, but rather of his that is amorous of thee: then she gave her a morsel of brown bread, and went to sleep. In the mean season, Cupid was closed fast in the surest chamber of the house, partly because he should not hurt himself with wanton dalliance, and partly because he should not speak with his love: so these two lovers were divided one from another. When night was passed Venus called Psyches, and said, Seest thou yonder Forest that extendeth out in length with the river? there be great sheep shining like gold, and kept by no manner of person. I command thee that thou go thither and bring me home some of the wool of their fleeces. Psyches arose willingly not to do her commandment, but to throw herself headlong into water to end her sorrows. Then a green reed inspired by divine inspiration, with a gratious tune and melody gan say, Oh Psyches I pray thee not to trouble or pollute my water by the death of thee, and yet beware that thou go not towards the terrible sheep of this coast, until such time as the heat of the sun be past, for when the sun is in his force, then seem they most dreadful and furious, with their sharp horns, their stony foreheads and their gaping throats, wherewith they arm themselves to the destruction of mankind. But until they have refreshed themselves in the river, thou must hide thyself here by me, under this great plain tree, and as soon as their great fury is past, thou maist go among the thickets and bushes under the wood side and gather the locks their golden Fleeces, which thou shalt find hanging upon the briers. Then spake the gentle and benign reed, showing a mean to Psyches to save her life, which she bore well in memory, and with all diligence went and gathered up such locks as she found, and put them in her apron, and carried them home to Venus. Howbeit the danger of this second labour did not please her, nor give her sufficient witness of the good service of Psyches, but with a sower resemblance of laughter, did say: Of a certain I know that this is not thy fact, but I will prove if that thou be of so stout, so good a courage, and singular prudency as thou seemest to be. Then Venus spake unto Psyches again saying: Seest thou the toppe of yonder great Hill, from whence there runneth down waters of black and deadly colour, which nourisheth the floods of Stix, Cocytus? I charge thee to go thither, and bring me a vessel of that water: wherewithal she gave her a bottle of Christall, menacing and threatening her rigorously. Then poor Psyches went in all haste to the top of the mountain, rather to end her life, then to fetch any water, and when she was come up to the ridge of the hill, she perceived that it was impossible to bring it to pass: for she saw a great rock gushing out most horrible fountains of waters, which ran down and fell by many stops and passages into the valley beneath: on each side she did see great Dragons, which were stretching out their long and bloody Necks, that did never sleep, but appointed to keep the river there: the waters seemed to themselves likewise saying, Away; away, what wilt thou do? flie, flie, or else thou wilt be slain. Then Psyches (seeing the impossibility of this affair) stood still as though she were transformed into a stone and although she was present in body, yet was she absent in spirit and sense, by reason of the great peril which she saw, insomuch that she could not comfort herself with weeping, such was the present danger that she was in. But the royal bird of great Jupiter, the Eagle remembering his old service which he had done, when as by the prick of Cupid he brought up the boy Ganimedes, to the heavens, to be made butler of Jupiter, and minding to show the like service in the person of the wife of Cupid, came from the high-house of the Skies, and said unto Psyches, Oh simple woman without all experience, doest thou think to get or dip up any drop of this dreadful water? No, no, assure thyself thou art never able to come nigh it, for the Gods themselves do greatly fear at the sight thereof. What, have you not heard, that it is a custom among men to swear by the puissance of the Gods, and the Gods do swear by the majesty of the river Stix? but give me thy bottle, and sodainly he took it, and filled it with the water of the river, and taking his flight through those cruel and horrible dragons, brought it unto Psyches: who being very joyful thereof, presented it to Venus, who would not yet be appeased, but menacing more and more said, What, thou seemest unto me a very witch and enchantress, that bringest these things to pass, howbeit thou shalt do nothing more. Take this box and to Hell to Proserpina, and desire her to send me a little of her beauty, as much as will serve me the space of one day, and say that such as I had is consumed away since my sonne fell sick, but return again quickly, for I must dress myself therewithal, and go to the Theatre of the Gods: then poor Psyches perceived the end of all fortune, thinking verely that she should never return, and not without cause, when as she was compelled to go to the gulf and furies of hell. Wherefore without any further delay, she went up to an high tower to throw herself down headlong (thinking that it was the next and readiest way to hell) but the tower (as inspired) spake unto her saying, Oh poor miser, why goest thou about to slay thyself? Why dost thou rashly yield unto thy last peril and danger? know thou that if thy spirit be once separated from thy body, thou shalt surely go to hell, but never to return again, wherefore harken to me; Lacedemon a City in Greece is not far hence: go thou thither and inquire for the hill Tenarus, whereas thou shalt find a hold leading to hell, even to the Pallace of Pluto, but take heed thou go not with empty hands to that place of darkness: but Carry two sops sodden in the flour of barley and Honney in thy hands, and two halfepence in thy mouth. And when thou hast passed a good part of that way, thou shalt see a lame Ass carrying of wood, and a lame fellow driving him, who will desire thee to give him up the sticks that fall down, but pass thou on and do nothing; by and by thou shalt come unto a river of hell, whereas Charon is ferriman, who will first have his fare paied him, before he will carry the souls over the river in his boat, whereby you may see that avarice reignth amongst the dead, neither Charon nor Pluto will do anything for nought: for if it be a poor man that would pass over and lacketh money, he shal be compelled to die in his journey before they will show him any relief, wherefore deliver to carraine Charon one of the halfpence (which thou bearest for thy passage) and let him receive it out of thy mouth. And it shall come to pass as thou sittest in the boat thou shalt see an old man swimming on the top of the river, holding up his deadly hands, and desiring thee to receive him into the bark, but have no regard to his piteous cry; when thou art passed over the flood, thou shalt espie old women spinning, who will desire thee to help them, but beware thou do not consent unto them in any case, for these and like baits and traps will Venus set to make thee let fall one of thy sops, and think not that the keeping of thy sops is a light matter, for if thou leese one of them thou shalt be assured never to return again to this world. Then shalt thou see a great and marvailous dogge, with three heads, barking continually at the souls of such as enter in, but he can do them no other harm, he lieth day and night before the gate of Proserpina, and keepeth the house of Pluto with great diligence, to whom if thou cast one of thy sops, thou maist have access to Proserpina without all danger: she will make thee good cheer, and entertain thee with delicate meat and drink, but sit thou upon the ground, and desire brown bread, and then declare thy message unto her, and when thou hast received such beauty as she giveth, in thy return appease the rage of the dogge with thy other sop, and give thy other half penny to covetous Charon, and come the same way again into the world as thou wentest: but above all things have a regard that thou look not in the box, neither be not too curious about the treasure of the divine beauty. In this manner tire tower spake unto Psyches, and advertised her what she should do: and immediately she took two half pence, two sops, and all things necessary, and went to the mountain Tenarus to go towards hell. After that Psyches had passed by the lame Asse, paid her half penny for passage, neglected the old man in the river, denied to help the woman spinning, and filled the ravenous month of the dogge with a sop, she came to the chamber of Proserpina. There Psyches would not sit in any royal seat, nor eat any delicate meats, but kneeled at the feet of Proserpina, only contented with course bread, declared her message, and after she had received a mystical secret in a box, she departed, and stopped the mouth of the dogge with the other sop, and paied the boatman the other half penny. When Psyches was returned from hell, to the light of the world, she was ravished with great desire, saying, Am not I a fool, that knowing that I carry here the divine beauty, will not take a little thereof to garnish my face, to please my love withall? And by and by she opened the box where she could perceive no beauty nor anything else, save only an infernal and deadly sleep, which immediatly invaded all her members as soon as the box was uncovered, in such sort that she fell down upon the ground, and lay there as a sleeping corps.

But Cupid being now healed of his wound and Maladie, not able to endure the absence of Psyches, got him secretly out at a window of the chamber where he was enclosed, and (receiving his wings,) took his flight towards his loving wife, whom when he had found, he wiped away the sleep from her face, and put it again into the box, and awaked her with the tip of one of his arrows, saying: Oh wretched Caitife, behold thou wert well-nigh perished again, with the overmuch curiosity: well, go thou, and do thy message to my Mother, and in the mean season, I will provide for all things accordingly: wherewithal he took his flight into the air, and Psyches brought her present to Venus.

Cupid being more and more in love with Psyches, and fearing the displeasure of his Mother, did pearce into the heavens, and arrived before Jupiter to declare his cause: then Jupiter after that he had eftsoone embraced him, gan say in this manner: Oh my well beloved sonne, although thou haste not given due reverence and honour unto me as thou oughtest to do, but haste rather spoiled and wounded this my brest (whereby the laws and order of the Elements and Planets be disposed) with continual assaults, of Terren luxury and against all laws, and the discipline Julia, and the utility of the publike weal, in transforming my divine beauty into serpents, fire, savage beasts, birds, and into Bulles: howbeit remembering my modesty, and that I have nourished thee with mine own proper hands, I will do and accomplish all thy desire, so that thou canst beware of spiteful and envious persons. And if there be any excellent Maiden of comely beauty in the world, remember yet the benefit which I shall show unto thee by recompence of her love towards me again. When he had spoken these words he commanded Mercury to call all the gods to counsel, and if any of the celestial powers did fail of appearance he would be condemned in ten thousand pounds: which sentence was such a terror to all the goddesss, that the high Theatre was replenished, and Jupiter began to speak in this sort: Oh yee gods, registred in the books of the Muses, you all know this young man Cupid whom I have nourished with mine own hands, whose raging flames of his first youth, I thought best to bridle and restrain. It sufficeth that he is defamed in every place for his adulterous living, wherefore all occasion ought to be taken away by mean of marriage: he hath chosen a Maiden that fancieth him well, and hath bereaved her of her virginity, let him have her still, and possess her according to his own pleasure: then he returned to Venus, and said, And you my daughter, take you no care, neither fear the dishonour of your progeny and estate, neither have regard in that it is a mortal marriage, for it seemeth unto me just, lawful, and legitimate by the law civil. Incontinently after Jupiter commanded Mercury to bring up Psyches, the spouse of Cupid, into the Pallace of heaven. And then he took a pot of immortality, and said, Hold Psyches, and drink, to the end thou maist be immortal, and that Cupid may be thine everlasting husband. By and by the great banket and marriage feast was sumptuously prepared, Cupid sat down with his dear spouse between his arms: Juno likewise with Jupiter, and all the other gods in order, Ganimedes filled the pot of Jupiter, and Bacchus served the rest. Their drink was Nectar the wine of the gods, Vulcanus prepared supper, the howers decked up the house with roses and other sweet smells, the graces threw about blame, the Muses sang with sweet harmony, Apollo tuned pleasantly to the Harp, Venus danced finely: Satirus and Paniscus plaid on their pipes; and thus Psyches was married to Cupid, and after she was delivered of a child whom we call Pleasure. This the trifling old woman declared unto the captive maiden: but I poor Asse, not standing far of, was not a little sorry in that I lacked pen and ink to write so worthy a tale.

The Twenty-Third Chapter

How Apuleius carried away the Gentlewoman, and how they were taken again by the theeves, and what a kind of death was invented for them.

By and by the theeves came home laden with treasure, and many of them which were of strongest courage (leaving behind such as were lame and wounded, to heale and air themselves) said they would returne back again to fetch the rest of their pillage, which they had hidden in a certain cave, and so they snatched up their dinner greedily, and brought us forth into the way and beate us before them with staves. About night (after that we had passed over many hilles and dales) we came to a great cave, where they laded us with mighty burdens, and would not suffer us to refresh ourselves any season but brought us again in our way, and hied so fast homeward, that what with their haste and their cruell stripes, I fell down upon a stone by the way side, then they beate me pittifully in lifting me up, and hurt my right thigh and my left hoofe, and one of them said, What shall we do with this lame Ill favoured Asse, that is not worth the meate he eats? And other said, Since the time that we had him first he never did any good, and I think he came unto our house with evill lucke, for we have had great wounds since, and losse of our valiant captaines, and other said, As soon as he hath brought home his burden, I will surely throw him out upon the mountaine to be a pray for wild beasts: While these gentlemen reasoned together of my death, we fortuned to come home, for the feare that I was in, caused my feet to turne into wings: after that we were discharged of our burdens, they went to their fellowes that were wounded, and told them of our great tardity and slowness by the way, neither was I brought into small anguish, when I perceived my death prepared before my face: Why standest thou still Lucius? Why dost thou not looke for thy death? Knowst thou not that the theeves have ordained to slay thee? seest thou not these sharpe and pointed flints which shall bruise and tear thee in peeces, if by adventure thou happen upon them? Thy gentle Magitian hath not only given thee the shape and travel of an Asse, but also a skinne so soft and tender as it were a swallow: why dost thou not take courage and run away to save thyself? Art thou afraid of the old woman more then halfe dead, whom with a stripe of thy heele thou maist easily dispatch? But whither shall I fly? What lodging shall I seek? See my Assy cogitation. Who is he that passeth by the way and will not take me up? While I devised these things, I brake the halter wherewith I was tied and ran away with all my force, howbeit I could not escape the kitish eyes of the old woman, for she ran after me, and with more audacity then becommeth her kind age, caught me by the halter and thought to pull me home: but I not forgetting the cruell purpose of the theeves, was moved with small pity, for I kicked her with my hinder heeles to the ground and had welnigh slain her, who (although she was thrown and hurled down) yet she held still the halter, and would not let me go; then she cried with a loud voice and called for succour, but she little prevailed, because there was no person that heard her, save only the captive gentlewoman, who hearing the voice of the old woman, came out to see what the matter was, and perceiving her hanging at the halter, took a good courage and wrested it out of her hand, and (entreating me with gentle words) got upon my back. Then I began to runne, and she gently kicked me forward, whereof I was nothing displeased, for I had as great a desire to escape as shee: insomuch that I seemed to scowre away like a horse. And when the Gentlewoman did speake, I would answere her with my neighing, and oftentimes (under colour to rub my back) I would sweetly kisse her tender feet. Then she fetching a sigh from the bottome of her heart, lifted up her eyes to the heavens, saying: O sovereign Gods, deliver me if it be your pleasure, from these present dangers: and thou cruell fortune cease thy wrath, let the sorrow suffice thee which I have already sustained. And thou little Asse, that art the occasion of my safety and liberty, if thou canst once render me safe and sound to my parents, and to him that so greatly desireth to have me to his wife, thou shalt see what thankes I will give: with what honour I will reward thee, and how I will use thee. First, I will bravely dress the hairs of thy forehead, and then will I finely combe thy maine, I will tye up thy rugged tayle trimly, I will decke thee round about with golden trappes, in such sort that thou shalt glitter like the starres of the skie, I will bring thee daily in my apron the kirnels of nuts, and will pamper thee up with delicates; I will set store by thee, as by one that is the preserver of my life: Finally, thou shalt lack no manner of thing. Moreover amongst thy glorious fare, thy great ease, and the bliss of thy life, thou shalt not be destitute of dignity, for thou shalt be chronicled perpetually in memory of my present fortune, and the providence divine. All the whole history shall be painted upon the wall of our house, thou shalt be renowned throughout all the world. And it shall be registred in the books of Doctours, that an Ass saved the life of a young maiden that was captive amongst Theeves: Thou shalt be numbred amongst the ancient miracles: we beleeve that by like example of truth Phryxus saved himself from drowning upon the Ram, Arion escaped upon a Dolphin, and that Europa was delivered by the Bull. If Jupiter transformed himself into a Bull, why may it not be that under the shape of this Asse, is hidden the figure of a man, or some power divine? While that the Virgin did thus sorrowfully unfold her desires, we fortuned to come to a place where three wayes did meet, and she took me by the halter, and would have me to turne on the right hand to her fathers house: but I (knowing that the theeves were gone that way to fetch the residue of their pillage) resisted with my head as much as I might, saying within myself: What wilt thou do unhappy maiden? Why wouldst thou go so willingly to hell? Why wilt thou run into destruction by mean of my feet? Why dost thou seek thine own harme, and mine likewise? And while we strived together whether way we might take, the theeves returned, laiden with their pray, and perceived us a far off by the light of the Moon: and after they had known us, one of them gan say, Whither go you so hastely? Be you not afraid of spirits? And you (you harlot) do you not go to see your parents? Come on, we will bear you company? And therewithall they took me by the hatter, and drave me back again, beating me cruelly with a great staffe (that they had) full of knobs: then I returning again to my ready destruction, and remembering the griefe of my hoofe, began to shake my head, and to waxe lame, but he that led me by the halter said, What, dost thou stumble? Canst thou not go? These rotten feet of thine ran well enough, but they cannot walke: thou couldest mince it finely even now with the gentlewoman, that thou seemedst to pass the horse Pegasus in swiftnesse. In saying of these words they beat me again, that they broke a great staffe upon me. And when we were come almost home, we saw the old woman hanging upon a bow of a Cipresse tree; then one of them cut down the bowe whereon she hanged, and cast her into the bottome of a great ditch: after this they bound the maiden and fell greedily to their victuals, which the miserable old woman had prepared for them. At which time they began to devise with themselves of our death, and how they might be revenged; diverse was the opinions of this diverse number: the first said, that he thought best the Maid should be burned alive: the second said she should be thrown out to wild beasts: the third said, she should be hanged upon a gibbet: the fourth said she should be flead alive: thus was the death of the poore Maiden scanned betweene them foure. But one of the theeves after every man had declared his judgement, did speake in this manner: it is not convenient unto the oath of our company, to suffer you to waxe more cruell then the quality of the offence doth merit, for I would that she should not be hanged nor burned, nor thrown to beasts, nor dye any sodaine death, but by my council I would have her punished according to her desert. You know well what you have determined already of this dull Asse, that eateth more then he is worth, that faineth lamenesse, and that was the cause of the flying away of the Maid: my mind is that he shall be slain to morrow, and when all the guts and entrailes of his body is taken out, let the Maide be sowne into his belly, then let us lay them upon a great stone against the broiling heate of the Sun, so they shall both sustaine all the punishments which you have ordained: for first the Ass shall be slain as you have determined, and she shall have her members torne and gnawn with wild beasts, when as she is bitten and rent with wormes, she shall endure the pain of the fire, when as the broiling heat of the Sun shall scortch and parch the belly of the Asse, she shall abide the gallows when the Dogs and Vultures shall have the guts of her body hanging in their ravenous mouthes. I pray you number all the torments which she shall suffer: First she shall dwell within the paunch of an Asse: secondly her nosethrilles shall receive a carraine stinke of the beast: thirdly she shall dye for hunger: last of all, she shall find no mean to ridde herself from her pains, for her hand shalt be sowen up within the skinne of the Asse: This being said, all the Theeves consented, and when I (poore Asse) heard and understood all their device, I did nothing else but lament and bewayle my dead carkasse, which should be handled in such sort on the next morrow.

The Twenty-Ninth Chapter

How Apuleius was accused of lechery by the boy.

A few days after, the boy invented another mischief: for when he had sold all the wood which I bare, to certain men dwelling in a village by, he led me homeward unladen: And then he cried that he was not able to rule me, and that he would not drive me any longer to the hill for wood, saying: Do you not see this slow and dull ass, who besides all the mischiefs that he hath wrought already, inventeth daily more and more. For he espyeth any woman passing by the way, whether she be old or married, or if it be a young child, he will throw his burden from his back, and runneth fiercely upon them. And after that he hath thrown them down, he will stride over them to commit his buggery and beastly pleasure, moreover he will feign as though he would kiss them, but he will bite their faces cruelly, which thing may work us great displeasure, or rather to be imputed unto us as a crime: and even now when he espied an honest maiden passing by the highway, he by and by threw down his wood and run after her: And when he had thrown her down upon the ground, he would have ravished her before the face of all the world, had it not been that by reason of her crying out, she was succored and pulled from his heels, and so delivered. And if it had so come to pass that this fearful maid had been slain by him, what danger had we been in? By these and like lies, he provoked the shepherds earnestly against me, which grieved me (God wot) full sore that said nothing. Then one of the shepherds said: Why do we not make sacrifice of this common adulterous ass? My son (quoth he) let us kill him and throw his guts to the dogs, and reserve his flesh for the labourers supper. Then let us cast dust upon his skin, and carry it home to our master, and say that the wolves have devoured him. The boy that was my evil accuser made no delay, but prepared himself to execute the sentence of the shepherd, rejoicing at my present danger, but oh how greatly did I then repent that the stripe which I gave him with my heel had not killed him. Then he drew out his sword and made it sharp upon the whetstone to slay me, but another of the shepherds gan say, Verily it is a great offence to kill so fair an ass, and so (by accusation of luxury and lascivious wantonness) to lack so necessary his labour and service, where otherwise if ye would cut off his stones, he might not only be deprived of his courage but also become gentle, that we should be delivered from all fear and danger. Moreover he would be thereby more fat and better in flesh. For I know myself as well many asses, as also most fierce horses, that by reason of their wantonness have been most mad and terrible, but (when they were gelded and cut) they have become gentle and tame, and tractable to all use. Wherefore I would counsel you to geld him. And if you consent thereto, I will by and by, when I go to the next market fetch mine irons and tools for the purpose: and I ensure you after that I have gelded and cut off his stones, I will deliver him unto you as tame as a lamb. When I did perceive that I was delivered from death, and reserved to be gelded, I was greatly sorry, insomuch that I thought all the hinder part of my body and my stones did ache for woe, but I sought about to kill myself by some manner of means, to the end if I should die, I would die with unperished members.

The Thirty-First Chapter

How Apuleius was cruelly beaten by the mother of the boy that was slain.

In the mean season, while the parents of the boy did lament and for the death of their son, the shepherd (according to his promise) came with his instruments and tools to geld me. Then one of them said, Tush we little esteem the mischief he did yesterday, but now we are contented that tomorrow his stones shall not only be cut off, but also his head. So was it brought to pass, that my death was delayed till the next morrow, but what thanks did I give to that good boy, who (being so slain) was the cause of my pardon for one short day. Howbeit I had no time then to rest myself, for the mother of the boy, weeping and lamenting for his death, attired in mourning vesture, tore her hair and beat her breast, and came presently into the stable, saying, Is it reason that this careless beast should do nothing all day but hold his head in the manger, filling and belling his guts with meat without compassion of my great misery, or remembrance of the pitiful death of his slain master: and condemning my age and infirmity, thinketh that I am unable to revenge his mischiefs, moreover he would persuade me, that he were not culpable. Indeed, it is a convenient thing to look and plead for safety, when as the conscience doeth confess the offence, as thieves and malefactors accustom to do. But oh good Lord, thou cursed beast, if thou couldest utter the contents of thine own mind, whom (though it were the veriest fool in all the world) mightest thou persuade that this murder was void or without thy fault, when as it lay in thy power, either to keep off the thieves with thy heels, or else to bite and tear them with thy teeth? Couldest not thou (that so often in his lifetime diddest spurn and kick him) defend him now at the point of death by the like mean? Yet at least, thou shouldest have taken him upon thy back, and so brought him from the cruel hands of the thieves: where contrary thou runnest away alone, forsaking thy good master, thy pastor and conductor. Knowest thou not, that such as deny their wholesome help and aid to them which lie in danger of death, ought to be punished, because they have offended against good manners, and the law natural? But I promise thee, thou shalt not long rejoice at my harms, thou shalt feel the smart of thy homicide and offence, I will see what I can do. And therewithal she unclosed her apron, and bound all my feet together, to the end I might not help myself, then she took a great bar, which accustomed to bar the stable door, and never ceased beating me till she was so weary that the bar fell out of her hands, whereupon she (complaining of the soon faintness of her arms) ran to her fire and brought a firebrand and thrust it under my tail, burning me continually, till such time as (having but one remedy) I all arrayed her face and eyes with my dirty dung, whereby (what with the stink thereof, and what with the filthiness that fell in her eyes) she was well-nigh blinded: so I enforced the quean to leave off, otherwise I had died as Meleager did by the stick, which his mad mother Althaea cast into the fire.

The Twenty-Fifth Chapter

How the death of the Asse, and the Gentlewoman was stayed.

After supper they began to talke, and declare unto him the going away of the Gentlewoman, and how I bare her upon my back, and what death was ordained for us two. Then he desired to see her, whereupon the Gentlewoman was brought forth fast bound, whom as soon as he beheld, he turned himself wringing his nose, and blamed them saying: I am not so much a beast, or so rash a fellow to drive you quite from your purpose, but my conscience will not suffer me to conceal anything that toucheth your profit, since I am as careful for you, howbeit if my counsel do displease you, you may at your liberty proceed in your enterprise. I doubt not but all thieves, and such as have a good judgement, will preferre their own lucre and gain above all things in the world, and above their vengeance, which purchaseth damage to diverse persons. Therefore if you put this virgin in the Asses belly, you shall but execute your indignation against her, without all manner of profit; But I would advise you to carry the virgin to some town and to sell her: and such a brave girl as she is, may be sold for a great quantity of money. And I myself know certain bawdy Marchants, amongst whom peradventure one will give us summes of gold for her. This is my opinion touching this affair: but advise you what you intend to do, for you may rule me in this case. In this manner the good thief pleaded and defended our cause, being a good Patron to the silly virgin, and to me poor Asse. But they staied hereupon a good space, with long deliberation, which made my heart (God wot) and spirit greatly to quail. Howbeit in the end they consented to his opinion, and by and by the Maiden was unloosed of her bonds, who seeing the young man, and hearing the name of brothels and bawdy Merchants, began to wax joyful, and smiled with herself. Then began I to deem evil of the generation of women, when as I saw the Maiden (who was appointed to be married to a young Gentleman, and who so greatly desired the same) was now delighted with the talke of a wicked brothel house, and other things dishonest. In this sort the consent and manners of women depended in the judgement of an Asse.

The Twenty-Sixth Chapter

How all the Theeves were brought asleepe by their new companion.

Then the young man spake again, saying, Masters, why go we not about to make our prayers unto Mars, touching this selling of the Maiden, and to seeke for other companions. But as farre as I see, here is no other manner of beast to make sacrifice withall, nor wine sufficient for us to drinke. Let me have (quoth he) tenne more with me, and we will go to the next Castle, to provide for meat and other things necessary. So he and tenne more with him, went their way: In the mean season, the residue made a great fire and an Alter with greene turfes in the honour of Mars. By and by after they came again, bringing with them bottles of wine, and a great number of beasts, amongst which there was a big Ram Goat, fat, old, and hairy, which they killed and offered unto Mars. Then supper was prepared sumptuously, and the new companion said unto the other, You ought to accompt me not onely your Captaine in robbery and fight, but also in pleasures and jolity, whereupon by and by with pleasant cheere he prepared meat, and trimming up the house he set all things in order, and brought the pottage and dainty dishes to the Table: but above all he plied them wel with great pots and jugs of wine. Sometimes (seeming to fetch somewhat) he would go to the Maiden and give her pieces of meate, which he privily took away, and would drinke unto her, which she willingly took in good part. Moreover, he kissed her twice or thrice whereof she was well pleased but I (not well contented thereat) thought in myself: O wretched Maid, thou hast forgotten thy marriage, and doest esteeme this stranger and bloudy theefe above thy husband which thy Parents ordained for thee, now perceive I well thou hast no remorse of conscience, but more delight to tarry and play the harlot heere amongst so many swords. What? knowest thou not how the other theeves if they knew thy demeanour would put thee to death as they had once appointed, and so work my destruction likewise? Well now I perceive thou hast a pleasure in the dammage and hurt of other. While I did angerly devise with myself all these things, I perceived by certain signes and tokens (not ignorant to so wise an Asse) that he was not the notable theefe Hemus, but rather Lepolemus her husband, for after much communication he beganne to speake more franckly, not fearing at all my presence, and said, Be of good cheere my sweete friend Charites, for thou shalt have by and by all these thy enemies captive unto thee. Then he filled wine to the theeves more and more, and never ceased, till as they were all overcome with abundance of meat and drinke, when as he himself abstained and bridled his own appetite. And truely I did greatly suspect, least he had mingled in their cups some deadly poison, for incontinently they all fell down asleepe on the ground one after an other, and lay as though they had beene dead.

The Twenty-Ninth Chapter

How Apuleius was accused of Lechery by the boy.

A few dayes after, the boy invented another mischiefe: For when he had sold all the wood which I bare, to certain men dwelling in a village by, he lead me homeward unladen: And then he cried that he was not able to rule me, and that he would not drive me any longer to the hill for wood, saying: Do you not see this slow and dulle Asse, who besides all the mischiefes that he hath wrought already, inventeth daily more and more. For he espyeth any woman passing by the way, whether she be old or married, or if it be a young child, he will throw his burden from his back, and runneth fiercely upon them. And after that he hath thrown them down, he will stride over them to commit his buggery and beastly pleasure, moreover he will faine as though he would kisse them, but he will bite their faces cruelly, which thing may work us great displeasure, or rather to be imputed unto us as a crime: and even now when he espyed an honest maiden passing by die high way, he by and by threw down his wood and runne after her: And when he had thrown her down upon the ground, he would have ravished her before the face of all the world, had it not beene that by reason of her crying out, she was succored and pulled from his heeles, and so delivered. And if it had so come to passe that this fearefull maid had beene slain by him, what danger had we beene in? By these and like lies, he provoked the shepheards earnestly against me, which grieved me (God wot) full sore that said nothing. Then one of the shepheards said: Why do we not make sacrifice of this common adulterous Asse? My sonne (quoth he) let us kill him and throw his guts to the dogges, and reserve his flesh for the labourers supper. Then let us cast dust upon his skinne, and carry it home to our master, and say that the Woolves have devoured him. The boy that was my evill accuser made no delay, but prepared himself to execute the sentence of the shepheard, rejoicing at my present danger, but O how greatly did I then repent that the stripe which I gave him with my heele had not killed him. Then he drew out his sword and made it sharp upon the whetstone to slay me, but another of the shepheards gan say, Verely it is a great offence to kill so fair an Asse, and so (by accusation of luxurie and lascivious wantonnesse) to lack so necessarie his labour and service, where otherwise if ye would cut off his stones, he might not onely be deprived of his courage but also become gentle, that we should be delivered from all feare and danger. Moreover he would be thereby more fat and better in flesh. For I know myself as well many Asses, as also most fierce horses, that by reason of their wantonnesse have beene most mad and terrible, but (when they were gelded and cut) they have become gentle and tame, and tractable to all use. Wherefore I would counsell you to geld him. And if you consent thereto, I will by and by, when I go to the next market fetch mine irons and tooles for the purpose: And I ensure you after that I have gelded and cut off his stones, I will deliver him unto you as tame as a lambe. When I did perceive that I was delivered from death, and reserved to be gelded, I was greatly sorrie, insomuch that I thought all the hinder part of my body and my stones did ake for woe, but I sought about to kill myself by some manner of meanes, to the end if I should die, I would die with unperished members.

The Thirtieth Chapter

How the boy that led Apuleius to the field, was slain in the wood.

While I devised with myself in what manner I might end my life, the roperipe boy on the next morrow led me to the same hill again, and tied me to a bough of a great Oke, and in the mean season he took his hatchet and cut wood to load me withal, but behold there crept out of a cave by, a marvelous great Bear, holding out his mighty head, whom when I saw, I was suddenly stricken in fear, and (throwing all the strength of my body into my hinder heels) lifted up my strained head and brake the halter, wherewith I was tied. Then there was no need to bid me run away, for I scoured not only on foot, but tumbled over the stones and rocks with my body till I came into the open fields, to the intent I would escape from the terrible Bear, but especially from the boy that was worse than the Bear. Then a certain stranger that passed by the way (espying me alone as a stray Ass) took me up and road upon my back, beating me with a staff (which he bare in his hand) through a wide and unknown lane, whereat I was nothing displeased, but willingly went forward to avoid the cruel pain of gelding, which the shepherds had ordained for me, but as for the stripes I was nothing moved, since I was accustomed to be beaten so every day. But evil fortune would not suffer me to continue in so good estate long: For the shepherds looking about for a Cow that they had lost (after they had sought in diverse places) fortuned to come upon us unawares, who when they espied and knew me, they would have taken me by the halter, but he that rode upon my back resisted them saying, Oh Lord masters, what intend you to do? Will you rob me? Then said the shepherds, What? thinkest thou we handle thee otherwise then thou deservest, which hast stolen away our Ass? Why dost thou not rather tell us where thou hast hidden the boy whom thou hast slain? And therewithal they pulled him down to the ground, beating him with their fists, and spurning him with their feet. Then he answered unto them saying, that he saw no manner of boy, but only found the Ass loose and straying abroad, which he took up to the intent to have some reward for the finding of him and to restore him again to his Master. And I would to God (quoth he) that this Ass (which verily was never seen) could speak as a man to give witness of mine innocence: Then would you be ashamed of the injury which you have done to me. Thus (reasoning for Himself) he nothing prevailed, for they tied the halter about my neck, and (meager his face) pulled me quite away, and led me back again through the woods of the hill to the place where the boy accustomed to resort. And after they could find him in no place, at length they found his body rent and torn in pieces, and his members dispersed in sundry places, which I well knew was done by the cruel Bear: and verily I would have told it if I might have spoken, but (which I could only do) I greatly rejoiced at his death, although it came too late. Then they gathered together the pieces of his body and buried them. By and by they laid the fault to my new Master, that took me up by the way, and (bringing him home fast bound to their houses) purposed on the next morrow to accuse him of murder, and to lead him before the Justices to have judgment of death.

The Thirty-First Chapter

How Apuleius was cruelly beaten by the Mother of the boy that was slain.

In the mean season, while the Parents of the boy did lament and weepe for the death of their sonne, the shepheard (according to his promise) came with his instruments and tooles to geld me. Then one of them said, Tush we little esteeme the mischiefe he did yesterday, but now we are contented that to morrow his stones shall not onely be cut off, but also his head. So was it brought to passe, that my death was delayed till the next morrow, but what thanks did I give to that good boy, who (being so slain) was the cause of my pardon for one short day. Howbeit I had no time then to rest myself, for the Mother of the boy, weeping and lamenting for his death, attired in mourning vesture, tare her hair and beat her breast, and came presently into the stable, saying, Is it reason that this careless beast should do nothing all day but hold his head in the manger, filling and belling his guts with meat without compassion of my great miserie, or remembrance of the pittiful death of his slain Master: and contemning my age and infirmity, thinketh that I am unable to revenge his mischiefs, moreover he would perswade me, that he were not culpable. Indeed, it is a convenient thing to looke and plead for safety, when as the conscience doeth confess the offence, as theeves and malefactors accustome to do. But O good Lord, thou cursed beast, if thou couldest utter the contents of thine owne mind, whom (though it were the veriest foole in all the world) mightest thou perswade that this murther was voide or without thy fault, when as it lay in thy power, either to keepe off the theeves with thy heeles, or else to bite and teare them with thy teeth? Couldest not thou (that so often in his life time diddest spurne and kicke him) defend him now at the point of death by the like meane? Yet at least, thou shouldest have taken him upon thy back, and so brought him from the cruell hands of the theeves: where contrary thou runnest away alone, forsaking thy good Master, thy pastor and conductor. Knowest thou not, that such as denie their wholsome help and aid to them which lie in danger of death, ought to be punished, because they have offended against good manners, and the law naturall? But I promise thee, thou shalt not long rejoice at my harmes, thou shalt feele the smart of thy homicide and offence, I will see what I can do. And therewithall she unclosed her apron, and bound all my feete together, to the end I might not help myself, then she took a great barre, which accustomed to bar the stable door, and never ceased beating me till she was so weary that the bar fell out of her hands, whereupon she (complaining of the soone faintnesse of her armes) ran to her fire and brought a firebrand and thrust it under my taile, burning me continually, till such time as (having but one remedy) I arayed her face and eies with my durty dunge, whereby (what with the stinke thereof, and what with the filthinesse that fell in her eies) she was welnigh blinded: so I enforced the queane to leave off, otherwise I had died as Meleager did by the sticke, which his mad mother Althea cast into the fire.

Chapter XXXII

How a young man came and declared the miserable death of Lepolemus and his wife Charites.

About midnight came a young man, which seemed to be one of the family of the good woman Charites, who sometimes endured so much misery and calamity with me amongst the thieves, who after that he had taken a stool, and sat down before the fireside, in the company of the servants, began to declare many terrible things that had happened unto the house of Charites, saying: Oh ye housekeepers, shepherds and cowherds, you shall understand that we have lost our good mistress Charites miserably and by evil adventure: and to the end you may learn and know all the whole matter, I purpose to tell you the circumstances of every point, whereby such as are more learned then I (to whom fortune hath ministered more copious style) may paint it out in paper in form of an history. There was a young gentleman dwelling in the next city, born of good parentage, valiant in prowess, and rich in substance, but very much given and addicted to whore-hunting, and continual revelling. Whereby he fell in company with thieves, and had his hand ready to the effusion of human blood; his name was Thrasillus. The matter was this according to the report of every man. He demanded Charites in marriage, who although he were a man more comely then the residue that wooed her, and also had riches abundantly, yet because he was of evil fame, and a man of wicked manners and conversation, he had the repulse and was put off by Charites, and so she married with Lepolemus. Howbeit this young man secretly loved her, yet moved somewhat at her refusal, he busily searched some means to work his damnable intent. And (having found occasion and opportunity to accomplish his purpose, which he had long time concealed) brought to pass, that the same day that Charites was delivered by the subtle mean and valiant audacity of her husband, from the puissance of the thieves, he mingled himself among the assembly, feigning that he was glad of the new marriage, and coming home again of the maiden, whereby (by reason that he came of so noble parents) he was received and entertained into the house as one of their chief and principal friends: howbeit under cloak of a faithful well-willer, he dissimuled his mischievous mind and intent: in continuance of time by much familiarity and often conversation and banqueting together, he fell more and more in favour, like as we see it fortuneth to lovers, who first do little delight themselves in love: till as by continual acquaintance they kiss and embrace each other. Thrasillus perceiving that it was a hard matter to break his mind secretly to Charites, whereby he was wholly barred from the accomplishment of his luxurious appetite, and on the other side perceiving that the love of her and her husband was so strongly linked together, that the bond between them might in nowise be dissevered, moreover, it was a thing impossible to ravish her, although he had consented thereto, yet was he still provoked forward by vehement lust, when as he saw himself unable to bring his purpose to pass. Howbeit at length the thing which seemed so hard and difficill, thorough hope of his fortified love, did now appear easy and facill: but mark I pray you diligently to what end the furious force of his inordinate desire came. On a day Lepolemus went to the chase with Thrasillus, to hunt for goats, for his wife Charites desired him earnestly to meddle with no other beasts, which were of more fierce and wild nature. When they were come within the chase to a great thicket fortressed about with briers and thorns, they compassed round with their dogs and beset every place with nets: by and by warning was given to let loose. The dogs rushed in with such a cry, that all the Forest rang again with the noise, but behold there leaped out no goat, nor deer, nor gentle hind, but an horrible and dangerous wild boar, hard and thick skinned, bristled terribly with thorns, foaming at the mouth, grinding his teeth, and looking direfully with fiery eyes. The dogs that first set upon him, he tore and rent with his tusks, and then he ran quite through the nets, and escaped away. When we saw the fury of this beast, we were greatly stricken with fear, and because we never accustomed to chase such dreadful boars, and further because we were unarmed and without weapons, we got and hid ourselves under bushes and trees. Then Thrasillus having found opportunity to work his treason, said to Lepolemus: What stand we here amazed? Why show we ourselves like dastards? Why lose we so worthy a prey with our feminine hearts? Let us mount upon our horses, and pursue him incontinently: take you a hunting staff, and I will take a chasing spear. By and by they leaped upon their horses, and followed the beast. But he returning against them with furious force, pried with his eyes, on whom he might first assail with his tusks: Lepolemus struck the beast first on the back with his hunting staff. Thrasillus feigning to aid and assist him, came behind, and cut off the hinder legs of Lepolemus’ horse, in such sort that he fell down to the ground with his master: and suddenly the Boar came upon Lepolemus and furiously tore and rent him with his teeth. Howbeit, Thrasillus was not sufficed to see him thus wounded, but when he desired his friendly help, he thrust Lepolemus through the right thigh with his spear, the more because he thought the wound of the spear would be taken for a wound of the Boars teeth, then he killed the beast likewise, and when he was thus miserably slain, every one of us came out of our holes, and went towards our slain master. But although that Thrasillus was joyful of the death of Lepolemus, whom he did greatly hate, yet he cloaked the matter with a sorrowful countenance, he feigned a dolorous face, he often embraced the body which himself slew, he played all the parts of a mourning person, saving there fell no tears from his eyes. Thus he resembled us in each point, who verily and not without occasion had cause to lament for our master, laying all the blame of this homicide unto the boar. Incontinently after the sorrowful news of the death of Lepolemus, came to the ears of all the family, but especially to Charites, who after she had heard such pitiful tidings, as a mad and raging woman, ran up and down the streets, crying and howling lamentably. All the citizens gathered together, and such as they met bare them company running towards the chasse. When they came to the slain body of Lepolemus, Charites threw herself upon him weeping and lamenting grievously for his death, in such sort, that she would have presently ended her life, upon the corpse of her slain husband, whom she so entirely loved, had it not been that her parents and friends did comfort her, and pulled her away. The body was taken up, and in funeral pomp brought to the city and buried. In the mean season, Thrasillus feigned much sorrow for the death of Lepolemus, but in his heart he was well pleased and joyful. And to counterfeit the matter, he would come to Charites and say: Oh what a loss have I had of my friend, my fellow, my companion Lepolemus? Oh Charites comfort yourself, pacify your dolour, refrain your weeping, beat not your breasts: and with such other and like words and diverse examples he endeavoured to suppress her great sorrow, but he spake not this for any other intent but to win the heart of the woman, and to nourish his odious love with filthy delight. Howbeit Charites after the burial of her husband sought the means to follow him, and (not sustaining the sorrows wherein she was wrapped) got her secretly into a chamber and purposed to finish her life there with dolour and tribulation. But Thrasillus was very importunate, and at length brought to pass, that at the intercession of the parents and friends of Charites, she somewhat refreshed her fallen members with refection of meat and bain. Howbeit, she did it more at the commandment of her parents, than for anything else: for she could in nowise be merry, nor receive any comfort, but tormented herself day and night before the image of her husband which she made like unto Bacchus, and rendered unto him divine honours and services. In the mean season Thrasillus not able to refrain any longer, before Charites had assuaged her dolor, before her troubled mind had pacified her fury, even in the middle of all her griefs, while she tore her hair and rent her garments, demanded her in marriage, and so without shame, he detected the secrets and unspeakable deceits of his heart. But Charites detested and abhorred his demand, and as she had been stricken with some clap of thunder, with some storm, or with the lightning of Jupiter, she presently fell down to the ground all amazed. Howbeit when her spirits were revived and that she returned to herself, perceiving that Thrasillus was so importunate, she demanded respite to deliberate and to take advice on the matter. In the mean season, the shape of Lepolemus that was slain so miserably, appeared to Charites saying, Oh my sweet wife (which no other person can say but I) I pray thee for the love which is between us two, if there he any memory of me in thy heart, or remembrance of my pitiful death, marry with any other person, so that thou marry not with the traitor Thrasillus, have no conference with him, eat not with him, lie not with him, avoid the bloody hand of mine enemy, couple not thyself with a parricide, for those wounds (the blood whereof thy tears did wash away) were not the wounds of the teeth of the boar, but the spear of Thrasillus, that deprived me from thee. Thus spake Lepolemus, unto his loving wife, and declared the residue of the damnable fact. Then Charites, awaking from sleep, began to renew her dolour, to tear her garments, and to beat her arms with her comely hands, howbeit she revealed the vision which she saw to no manner of person, but dissembling that she knew no part of the mischief, devised with herself how she might be revenged on the traitor, and finish her own life to end and knit up all sorrow. Incontinently came Thrasillus, the detestable demander of sudden pleasure, and wearied the closed ears of Charites with talk of marriage, but she gently refused his communication, and colouring the matter, with passing craft in the middest of his earnest desires gan say, Thrasillus you shall understand that yet the face of your brother and my husband, is always before mine eyes, I smell yet the cinnamon scent of his precious body, I yet feel Lepolemus alive in my heart: wherefore you shall do well if you grant to me miserable woman, necessary time to bewail his death, that after the residue of a few months, the whole year may be expired, which thing toucheth as well my shame as your wholesome profit, lest peradventure by your speed and quick marriage we should justly raise and provoke the spirit of my husband to work our destruction. Howbeit, Thrasillus was not contented with this promise, but more and more came upon her: Insomuch, that she was enforced to speak to him in this manner: My friend Thrasillus, if thou be so contented until the whole year be complete and finished, behold here is my body, take thy pleasure, but in such sort and so secret that no servant of the house may perceive it. Then Thrasillus trusting to the false promises of the woman, and preferring his inordinate pleasure above all things in the world, was joyful in his heart and looked for night, when as he might have his purpose. But come thou about midnight (quoth Charites) disguised without company, and do but hiss at my chamber door, and my nurse shall attend and let thee in. This counsel pleased Thrasillus marvelously, who (suspecting no harm) did always look for night, and the hour assigned by Charites. The time was scarce come, when as (according to her commandment) he disguised himself, and went straight to the chamber, where he found the nurse attending for him, who (by the appointment of her mistress) fed him with flattering talk, and gave him mingled and doled drink in a cup, excusing the absence of her mistress Charites, by reason that she attended on her Father being sick, until such time, that with sweet talk and operation of the wine, he fell in a sound sleep: now when he lay prostrate on the ground ready to all adventure, Charites (being called for) came in, and with manly courage and bold force stood over the sleeping murderer, saying: Behold the faithful companion of my husband, behold this valiant hunter; behold me dear spouse, this is the hand which shed my blood, this is the heart which hath devised so many subtle means to work my destruction, these be the eyes whom I have ill pleased, behold now they foreshow their own destiny: sleep careless, dream that thou art in the hands of the merciful, for I will not hurt thee with thy sword or any other weapon: God forbid that I should slay thee as thou slewest my husband, but thy eyes shall fail thee, and thou shalt see no more, then that whereof thou dreamest: Thou shalt think the death of thine enemy more sweet than thy life: thou shalt see no light, thou shalt lack the aide of a leader, thou shalt not have me as thou hopest, thou shalt have no delight of my marriage, thou shalt not die, and yet living thou shalt have no joy, but wander between light and darkness as an unsure image: thou shalt seek for the hand that pricked out thine eyes, yet shalt thou not know of whom thou shouldest complain: I will make sacrifice with the blood of thine eyes upon the grave of my husband. But what gainest thou through my delay? Perhaps thou dreamest that thou embracest me in thy arms: leave off the darkness of sleep and awake thou to receive a penal deprivation of thy sight, lift up thy face, regard thy vengeance and evil fortune, reckon thy misery; so pleaseth thine eyes to a chaste woman, that thou shall have blindness to thy companion, and an everlasting remorse of thy miserable conscience. When she had spoken these words, she took a great needle from her head and pricked out both his eyes: which done, she by and by caught the naked sword which her husband Lepolemus accustomed to wear, and ran throughout all the city like a mad woman towards the sepulchre of her husband. Then all we of the house, with all the citizens, ran incontinently after her to take the sword out of her hand, but she clasping about the tomb of Lepolemus, kept us off with her naked weapon, and when she perceived that every one of us wept and lamented, she spake in this sort: I pray you my friends weep not, nor lament for me, for I have revenged the death of my husband, I have punished deservedly the wicked breaker of our marriage; now is it time to seek out my sweet Lepolemus, and presently with this sword to finish my life. And therewithal after she had made relation of the whole matter, declared the vision which she saw and told by what mean she deceived Thrasillus, thrusting her sword under her right breast, and wallowing in her own blood, at length with manly courage yielded up the ghost. Then immediately the friends of miserable Charites did bury her body within the same sepulchre. Thrasillus hearing all the matter, and knowing not by what means he might end his life, for he thought his sword was not sufficient to revenge so great a crime, at length went to the same sepulchre, and cried with a loud voice, saying: oh ye dead spirits whom I have so highly and greatly offended, vouchsafe to receive me, behold I make sacrifice unto you with my whole body: which said, he closed the sepulchre, purposing to famish himself, and to finish his life there in sorrow. These things the young man with pitiful sighs and tears, declared unto the cowherds and shepherds, which caused them all to weep: but they fearing to become subject unto new masters, prepared themselves to depart away.

The Thirty-Second Chapter

How a young man came and declared the miserable death of Lepolemus and his wife Charites.

About midnight came a young man, which seemed to be one of the family of the good woman Charites, who sometimes endured so much misery and calamity with me amongst the thieves, who after that he had taken a stool, and sat down before the fireside, in the company of the servants, began to declare many terrible things that had happened unto the house of Charites, saying: Oh yee housekeepers, shepheards and cowheards, you shall understand that we have lost our good mistris Charites miserably and by evil adventure: and to the end you may learn and know all the whole matter, I purpose to tell you the circumstances of every point, whereby such as are more learned then I (to whom fortune hath ministred more copious style) may paint it out in paper in form of an History. There was a young Gentleman dwelling in the next City, borne of good parentage, valiant in prowess, and riche in substance, but very much given and adicted to whorehunting, and continual revelling. Whereby he fell in company with Thieves, and had his hand ready to the effusion of human blood; his name was Thrasillus. The matter was this according to the report of every man. He demanded Charites in marriage, who although he were a man more comely then the residue that wooed her, and also had riches abundantly, yet because he was of evil fame, and a man of wicked manners and conversation, he had the repulse and was put off by Charites, and so she married with Lepolemus. Howbeit this young man secretly loved her, yet moved somewhat at her refusal, he busily searched some means to work his damnable intent. And (having found occasion and opportunity to accomplish his purpose, which he had long time concealed) brought to pass, that the same day that Charites was delivered by the subtlel mean and valiant audacity of her husband, from the puissance of the Thieves, he mingled himself among the assembly, faining that he was glad of the new marriage, and coming home again of the maiden, Whereby (by reason that he came of so noble parents) he was received and entertained into the house as one of their chiefe and principal friends: Howbeit under cloak of a faithful welwiller, he dissimuled his mischievous mind and intent: in continuance of time by much familiarity and often conversation and banketting together, he fell more and more in favour, like as we see it fortuneth to Lovers, who first do little delight themselves in love: till as by continual acquaintance they kisse and imbrace each other. Thrasillus perceiving that it was a hard matter to break his mind secretly to Charites, whereby he was wholly barred from the accomplishment of his luxurious appetite, and on the other side perceiving that the love of her and her husband was so strongly lincked together, that the bond between them might in no wise be dissevered, moreover, it was a thing impossible to ravish her, although he had consented thereto, yet was he still provoked forward by vehement lust, when as he saw himself unable to bring his purpose to pass. Howbeit at length the thing which seemed so hard and difficill, thorough hope of his fortified love, did now appear easy and facill: but mark I pray you diligently to what end the furious force of his inordinate desire came. On a day Lepolemus went to the chase with Thrasillus, to hunt for Goates, for his wife Charites desired him earnestly to meddle with no other beasts, which were of more fierce and wild nature. When they were come within the chase to a great thicket fortressed about with briers and thornes, they compassed round with their Dogs and beset every place with nets: by and by warning was given to let loose. The Dogs rushed in with such a cry, that all the Forrest rang again with the noise, but behold there leaped out no Goat, nor Deere, nor gentle Hind, but an horrible and dangerous wild Boare, hard and thicke skinned, bristeled terribly with thornes, foming at the mouth, grinding his teeth, and looking direfully with fiery eyes. The Dogs that first set upon him, he tare and rent with his tuskes, and then he ranne quite through the nets, and escaped away. When we saw the fury of this beast, we were greatly striken with feare, and because we never accustomed to chase such dreadful Boares, and further because we were unarmed and without weapons, we got and hid ourselves under bushes and trees. Then Thrasillus having found opportunity to work his treason, said to Lepolemus: What stand we here amazed? Why show we ourselves like dastards? Why leese we so worthy a prey with our feminine hearts? Let us mount upon our Horses, and pursue him incontinently: take you a hunting staff, and I will take a chasing spear. By and by they leaped upon their Horses, and followed the beast. But he returning against them with furious force, pried with his eyes, on whom he might first assayle with his tuskes: Lepolemus strooke the beast first on the back with his hunting staff. Thrasillus faining to aid and assist him, came behind, and cut off the hinder legges of Lepolemus Horse, in such sort that he fell down to the ground with his master: and sodainely the Boare came upon Lepolemus and furiously tare and rent him with his teeth. Howbeit, Thrasillus was not sufficed to see him thus wounded, but when he desired his friendly help, he thrust Lepolemus through the right thigh with his spear, the more because he thought the wound of the spear would be taken for a wound of the Boars teeth, then he killed the beast likewise, And when he was thus miserably slain, every one of us came out of our holes, and went towards our slain master. But although that Thrasillus was joyful of the death of Lepolemus, whom he did greatly hate, yet he cloked the matter with a sorrowful countenance, he fained a dolorous face, he often imbraced the body which himself slew, he played all the parts of a mourning person, saving there fell no tears from his eyes. Thus he resembled us in each point, who verily and not without occasion had cause to lament for our master, laying all the blame of this homicide unto the Boare. Incontinently after the sorrowful news of the death of Lepolemus, came to the ears of all the family, but especially to Charites, who after she had heard such pitiful tidings, as a mad and raging woman, ran up and down the streets, crying and howling lamentably. All the Citizens gathered together, and such as they met bare them company running towards the chasse. When they came to the slain body of Lepolemus, Charites threw herself upon him weeping and lamenting grievously for his death, in such sort, that she would have presently ended her life, upon the corps of her slain husband, whom she so entirely loved, had it not been that her parents and friends did comfort her, and pulled her away. The body was taken up, and in funeral pomp brought to the City and buried. In the mean season, Thrasillus fained much sorrow for the death of Lepolemus, but in his heart he was well pleased and joyful. And to counterfeit the matter, he would come to Charites and say: Oh what a lose have I had of my friend, my fellow, my companion Lepolemus? Oh Charites comfort yourself, pacifie your dolour, refrain your weeping, beat not your breasts: and with such other and like words and diverse examples he endeavoured to suppress her great sorrow, but he spake not this for any other intent but to win the heart of the woman, and to nourish his odious love with filthy delight. Howbeit Charites after the burial of her husband sought the means to follow him, and (not sustaining the sorrows wherein she was Wrapped) got her secretly into a chamber and purposed to finish her life there with dolour and tribulation. But Thrasillus was very importunate, and at length brought to pass, that at the intercession of the Parents and friends of Charites, she somewhat refreshed her fallen members with refection of meat and baine. Howbeit, she did it more at the commandment of her Parents, then for anything else: for she could in no wise be merry, nor receive any comfort, but tormented herself day and night before the Image of her husband which she made like unto Bacchus, and rendred unto him divine honours and services. In the mean season Thrasillus not able to refrain any longer, before Charites had asswaged her dolor, before her troubled mind had pacified her fury, even in the middle of all her griefes, while she tare her hair and rent her garments, demanded her in marriage, and so without shame, he detected the secrets and unspeakeable deceipts of his heart. But Charites detested and abhorred his demand, and as she had been stroken with some clap of thunder, with some storm, or with the lightning of Jupiter, she presently fell down to the ground all amazed. Howbeit when her spirits were revived and that she returned to herself, perceiving that Thrasillus was so importunate, she demanded respite to deliberate and to take advise on the matter. In the mean season, the shape of Lepolemus that was slain so miserably, appeared to Charites saying, Oh my sweet wife (which no other person can say but I) I pray thee for the love which is between us two, if there he any memory of me in thy heart, or remembrance of my pitiful death, marry with any other person, so that thou marry not with the traitour Thrasillus, have no conference with him, eate not with him, lie not with him, avoid thebloodie hand of mine enemie, couple not thyself with a paricide, for those wounds (theblood whereof thy tears did wash away) were not the wounds of the teeth of the Boare, but the spear of Thrasillus, that deprived me from thee. Thus spake Lepolemus, unto his loving wife, and declared the residue of the damnable fact. Then Charites, awaking from sleep, began to renew her dolour, to tear her garments, and to beat her armes with her comely hands, howbeit she revealed the vision which she saw to no manner of person, but dissimuling that she knew no part of the mischief, devised with herself how she might be revenged on the traitor, and finish her own life to end and knit up all sorrow. Incontinently came Thrasillus, the detestable demander of sodaine pleasure, and wearied the closed ears of Charites with talke of marriage, but she gently refused his communication, and coloring the matter, with passing craft in the middest of his earnest desires gan say, Thrasillus you shall understand that yet the face of your brother and my husband, is always before mine eies, I smell yet the Cinamon scent of his pretious body, I yet feel Lepolemus alive in my heart: wherefore you shall do well if you grant to me miserable woman, necessary time to bewail his death, that after the residue of a few months, the whole year may be expired, which thing toucheth as well my shame as your wholsome profit, lest peradventure by your speed and quick marriage we should justly raise and provoke the spirit of my husband to work our destruction. Howbeit, Thrasillus was not contented with this promise, but more and more came upon her: Insomuch, that she was enforced to speake to him in this manner: My friend Thrasillus, if thou be so contented until the whole year be complete and finished, behold here is my body, take thy pleasure, but in such sort and so secret that no servant of the house may perceive it. Then Thrasillus trusting to the false promises of the woman, and preferring his inordinate pleasure above all things in the world, was joyful in his heart and looked for night, when as he might have his purpose. But come thou about midnight (quoth Charites) disguised without company, and do but hiss at my chamber door, and my nourse shall attend and let thee in. This counsel pleased Thrasillus marveilously, who (suspecting no harm) did alwaies look for night, and the hour assigned by Charites. The time was scarce come, when as (according to her commandment) he disguised himself, and went straight to the chamber, where he found the nourse attending for him, who (by the appointment of her Mistresse) fed him with flattering talke, and gave him mingled and doled drinke in a cup, excusing the absence of her Mistresse Charites, by reason that she attended on her Father being sick, until such time, that with sweet talke and operation of the wine, he fell in a sound sleep: Now when he lay prostrate on the ground readie to all adventure, Charites (being called for) came in, and with manly courage and bold force stood over the sleeping murderer, saying: Behold the faithful companion of my husband, behold this valiant hunter; behold me deere spouse, this is the hand which shed myblood, this is the heart which hath devised so many subtlel means to work my destruction, these be the eies whom I have ill pleased, behold now they foreshew their own destinie: sleep careless, dream that thou art in the hands of the merciful, for I will not hurt thee with thy sword or any other weapon: God forbid that I should slay thee as thou slewest my husband, but thy eies shall faile thee, and thou shalt see no more, then that whereof thou dreamest: Thou shalt think the death of thine enemie more sweet then thy life: Thou shalt see no light, thou shalt lacke the aide of a leader, thou shalt not have me as thou hopest, thou shalt have no delight of my marriage, thou shalt not die, and yet living thou shalt have no joy, but wander between light and darkness as an unsure Image: thou shalt seek for the hand that pricked out thine eies, yet shalt thou not know of whom thou shouldest complaine: I will make sacrifice with theblood of thine eies upon the grave of my husband. But what gainest thou through my delay? Perhaps thou dreamest that thou embracest me in thy armes: leave off the darkness of sleep and awake thou to receive a penal deprivation of thy sight, lift up thy face, regard thy vengeance and evil fortune, reckon thy miserie; so pleaseth thine eies to a chast woman, that thou shall have blindnese to thy companion, and an everlasting remorse of thy miserable conscience. When she had spoken these words, she took a great needle from her head and pricked out both his eies: which done, she by and by caught the naked sword which her husband Lepolemus accustomed to wear, and ranne throughout all the Citie like a mad woman towards the Sepulchre of her husband. Then all we of the house, with all the Citizens, ranne incontinently after her to take the sword out of her hand, but she clasping about the tomb of Lepolemus, kept us off with her naked weapon, and when she perceived that every one of us wept and lamented, she spake in this sort: I pray you my friends weepe not, nor lament for me, for I have revenged the death of my husband, I have punished deservedly the wicked breakr of our marriage; now is it time to seek out my sweet Lepolemus, and presently with this sword to finish my life. And therewithal after she had made relation of the whole matter, declared the vision which she saw and told by what mean she deceived Thrasillus, thrusting her sword under her right brest, and wallowing in her ownblood, at length with manly courage yielded up the Ghost. Then immediately the friends of miserable Charites did bury her body within the same Sepulchre. Thrasillus hearing all the matter, and knowing not by what means he might end his life, for he thought his sword was not sufficient to revenge so great a crime, at length went to the same Sepulchre, and cried with a lowd voice, saying: oh yee dead spirits whom I have so highly and greatly offended, vouchsafe to receive me, behold I make Sacrifice unto you with my whole body: which said, he closed the Sepulchre, purposing to famish himself, and to finish his life there in sorrow. These things the young man with pitiful sighes and tears, declared unto the Cowheards and Shepheards, which caused them all to weepe: but they fearing to become subject unto new masters, prepared themselves to depart away.

The Thirty-Third Chapter

How Apuleius was lead away by the Horsekeeper: and what danger he was in.

By and by the Horsekeeper, to whom the charge of me was committed, brought forth all his substance, and laded me and other Horses withall, and so departed thence: we bare women, children, pullets, sparrowes, kiddes, whelpes, and other things which were not able to keepe pace with us, and that which I bare upon my back, although it was a mighty burden, yet seemed it very light because I was driven away from him that most terribly had appointed to kill me. When we had passed over a great mountain full of trees, and were come again into the open fields, behold we approached nigh to a fair and rich Castell, where it was told unto us that we were not able to pass in our journey that night, by reason of the great number of terrible Wolves which were in the Country about, so fierce and cruel that they put every man in feare, in such sort that they would invade and set upon such which passed by like thieves, and devoure both them and their beasts. Moreover, we were advertised that there lay in the way where we should pass, many dead bodies eaten and torne with wolves. Wherefore we were willed to stay there all night, and on the next morning, to go close and round together, whereby we might pass and escape all dangers. But (notwithstanding this good counsel) our caitife drivers were so covetous to go forward, and so fearefull of pursuite, that they never stayed till the morning: But being welnigh midnight, they made us trudge in our way apace. Then I fearing the great danger which might happen, ran amongst the middle of the other Horses, to the end I might defend and save my poore buttocks from the Wolves, whereat every man much marvelled to see, that I scowred away swifter then the other Horses. But such was my agility, not to get me any praise, but rather for feare: at that time I remembered with myself, that the valiant Horse Pegasus did fly in the ayre more to avoid the danger of dreadful Chimera, then for anything else. The shepheards which drave us before them were well armed like warriours: one had a spear, another had a sheepehooke, some had darts, some clubbes, some gathered up great stones, some held up their sharp Javelings, and some feared away the Woolves with light firebrands. Finally we lacked nothing to make up an Army, but only Drummes and Trumpets. But when we had passed these dangers, not without small feare, we fortuned to fall into worse, for the Woolves came not upon us, either because of the great multitude of our company, or else because [of] our firebrands, or peradventure they were gone to some other place, for we could see none, but the Inhabitants of the next villages (supposing that we were Thieves by reason of the great multitude) for the defence of their own substance, and for the feare that they were in, set great and mighty masties upon us, which they had kept and nourished for the safety of their houses, who compassing us round about leaped on every side, tearing us with their teeth, in such sort that they pulled many of us to the ground: verily it was a pitiful sight to see so many Dogs, some following such as flyed, some invading such as stood still, some tearing those which lay prostrate, but generally there were none which escaped cleare: Behold upon this another danger ensued, the Inhabitants of the Town stood in their garrets and windowes, throwing great stones upon our heads, that we could not tell whether it were best for us to avoid the gaping mouthes of the Dogges at hand or the peril of the stones afar, amongst whom there was one that hurled a great flint upon a woman, which sat upon my back, who cried out pitiously, desiring her husband to helpe her. Then he (coming to succour and aid his wife) beganne to speake in this sort: Alas masters, what mean you to trouble us poore labouring men so cruelly? What mean you to revenge yourselves upon us, that do you no harme? What think you to gaine by us? You dwell not in Caves or Dennes: you are no people barbarous, that you should delight in effusion of human blood. At these words the tempest of stones did cease, and the storme of the Dogges vanished away. Then one (standing on the toppe of a great Cypress tree) spake unto us saying: Think you not masters that we do this to the intent to rifle or take away any of your goods, but for the safeguard of ourselves and family: now a Gods name you may depart away. So we went forward, some wounded with stones, some bitten with Dogs, but generally there was none which escaped free.

The Thirty-Fourth Chapter

How the shepheards determined to abide in a certain wood to cure their wounds.

When we had gone a good part of our way, we came to a certain wood environed with great trees and compassed about with pleasant meddowes, whereas the Shepheards appointed to continue a certain space to cure their wounds and sores; then they sat down on the ground to refresh their wearie minds, and afterwards they sought for medicines, to heal their bodies: some washed away their blood with the water of the running River: some stopped their wounds with Sponges and cloths, in this manner everyone provided for his own safety. In the mean season we perceived an old man, who seemed to be a Shepheard, by reason of the Goates and Sheep that fed round about him. Then one of our company demanded whether he had any milk, butter, or cheese to sell. To whom he made answer saying: Do you look for any meat or drink, or any other refection here? Know you not in what place you be?

And therewithal he took his sheep and drave them away as fast as he might possible. This answer made our shepheards greatly to fear, that they thought of nothing else, but to inquire what Country they were in: Howbeit they saw no manner of person of whom they might demand. At length as they were thus in doubt, they perceived another old man with a staff in his hand very weary with travel, who approaching nigh to our company, began to weep and complain saying: Alas masters I pray you succour me miserable caitife, and restore my nephew to me again, that by following a sparrow that flew before him, is fallen into a ditch hereby, and verily I think he is in danger of death. As for me, I am not able to help him out by reason of mine old age, but you that are so valiant and lusty may easily help me herein, and deliver me my boy, my heir and guide of my life. These words made us all to pity him. And then the youngest and stoutest of our company, who alone escaped best the late skirmish of Dogges and stones, rose up and demanded in what ditch the boy was fallen: Mary (quod he) yonder, and pointed with his finger, and brought him to a great thicket of bushes and thorns where they both entred in. In the mean season, after we cured our wounds, we took up our packs, purposing to depart away. And because we would not go away without the young man our fellow: The shepheards whistled and called for him, but when he gave no answer, they sent one out of their company to seek him out, who after a while returned again with a pale face and sorrowful news, saying that he saw a terrible Dragon eating and devouring their companion: and as for the old man, he could see him in no place. When they heard this, (remembering likewise the words of the first old man that shaked his head, and drave away his sheep) they ran away beating us before them, to fly from this desert and pestilent Country.

The Thirty-Seventh Chapter

How Apuleius saved himself from the Cook, breaking his halter, and of other things that happened.

In this manner the traiterous Cook prepared himself to slay me: and when he was ready with his knives to do his feat, I devised with myself how I might escape the present peril, and I did not long delay: for incontinently I brake the halter wherewith I was tied, and flinging my heeles hither and thither to save myself, at length I ran hastily into a Parlour, where the Master of the house was feasting with the Priests of the goddess Syria, and disquieted all the company, throwing down their meats and drinks from the table. The Master of the house dismayed at my great disorder, commanded one of his servants to take me up, and locke me in some strong place, to the end I might disturb them no more. But I little regarded my imprisonment, considering that I was happily delivered from the hands of the traiterous Cook. Howbeit fortune, or the fatal disposition of the divine providence, which neither can be avoided by wise counsel, neither yet by any wholesome remedie, invented a new torment, for by and by a young ladde came running into the Parlour all trembling, and declared to the Master of the house, that there was a madde Dog running about in the streetes, which had done much harme, for he had bitten many grey hounds and horses in the Inne by: And he spared neither man nor beast. For there was one Mitilius a Mulettour, Epheseus, a Cook, Hyppanius a chamberlaine, and Appolonius a Physition, who (thinking to chase away the madde Dogge) were cruelly wounded by him, insomuch that many Horses and other beasts infected with the venyme of his poisonous teeth became madde likewise. Which thing caused them all at the table greatly to feare, and thinking that I had beene bitten in like sort, came out with spears, Clubs, and Pitchforks purposing to slay me, and I had undoubtedly beene slain, had I not by and by crept into the Chamber, where my Master intended to lodge all night. Then they closed and locked fast the doors about me, and kept the chamber round, till such time as they thought that the pestilent rage of madness had killed me. When I was thus shutte in the chamber alone, I laid me down upon the bed to sleepe, considering it was long time past, since I lay and took my rest as a man doth. When morning was come, and that I was well reposed, I rose up lustily. In the mean season, they which were appointed to watch about the chamber all night, reasoned with themselves in this sort, Verely (quoth one) I think that this rude Ass be dead. So think I (quoth another) for the outragious poison of madness hath killed him, but being thus in diverse opinions of a poore Ass, they looked through a crevis, and espied me standing still, sober and quiet in the middle of the chamber; then they opened the doors, and came towards me, to prove whether I were gentle or no. Amongst whom there was one, which in my opinion, was sent from Heaven to save my life, that willed the other to set a bason of fair water before me, and thereby they would know whether I were mad or no, for if I did drinke without feare as I accustomed to do, it was a sign that I was whole, and in mine Assie wits, where contrary if I did flie and abhorre the tast of the water, it was evident proofe of my madness, which thing he said that he had read in ancient and credible books, whereupon they took a bason of cleere water, and presented it before me: but I as soon as I perceived the wholesome water of my life, ran incontinently, thrusting my head into the bason, drank as though I had beene greatly athirst; then they stroked me with their hands, and bowed mine ears, and took me by the halter, to prove my patience, but I taking each thing in good part, disproved their mad presumption, by my meeke and gentle behaviour: when I was thus delivered from this double danger, the next day I was laded again with the goddess Siria, and other trumpery, and was brought into the way with Trumpets and Cymbals to beg in the villages which we passed by according to our custom. And after that we had gone through a few towns and Castles, we fortuned to come to a certain village, which was builded (as the inhabitants there affirme) upon the foundation of a famous ancient Citie. And after that we had turned into the next Inne, we heard of a prettie jest committed in the town there, which I would that you should know likewise.

The Thirty-Eighth Chapter

Of the deceit of a Woman which made her husband Cuckold.

There was a man dwelling in the town very poor, that had nothing but that which he got by the labour and travel of his hands: his wife was a fair young woman, but very lascivious, and given to the appetite and desire of the flesh. It fortuned on a day, that while this poor man was gone betimes in the morning to the field about his business, according as he accustomed to do, his wives lover secretly came into his house to have his pleasure with her. And so it chanced that during the time that she and he were basking together, her husband suspecting no such matter, returned home praising the chaste continence of his wife, in that he found his doors fast closed, wherefore as his custom was, he whistled to declare his coming. Then his crafty wife ready with shifts, caught her lover and covered him under a great tub standing in a corner, and therewithal she opened the door, blaming her husband in this sort: Commest thou home every day with empty hands, and bringest nothing to maintain our house? thou hast no regard for our profit, neither providest for any meat or drink, whereas I poor wretch do nothing day and night but occupy myself with spinning, and yet my travel will scarce find the Candles which we spend. Oh how much more happy is my neighbour Daphne, that eateth and drinketh at her pleasure and passeth the time with her amorous lovers according to her desire. What is the matter (quoth her husband) though Our Master hath made holiday at the fields, yet think not but I have made provision for our supper; doest thou not see this tub that keepeth a place here in our house in vain, and doth us no service? Behold I have sold it to a good fellow (that is here present) for five pence, wherefore I pray thee lend me thy hand, that I may deliver him the tub. His wife (having invented a present shift) laughed on her husband, saying: What merchant I pray you have you brought home hither, to fetch away my tub for five pence, for which I poor woman that sit all day alone in my house have been proffered so often seven: her husband being well apaid of her words demanded what he was that had bought the tub: Look (quoth she) he is gone under, to see where it be sound or no: then her lover which was under the tub, began to stir and rustle himself, and because his words might agree to the words of the woman, he said: Dame will you have me tell the truth, this tub is rotten and cracked as me seemeth on every side. And then turning to her husband said: I pray you honest man light a Candle, that I may make clean the tub within, to see if it be for my purpose or no, for I do not mind to cast away my money wilfully: he by and by (being made a very Ox) lighted a candle, saying, I pray you good brother put not yourself to so much pain, let me make the tub clean and ready for you. Whereupon he put off his coat, and crept under the tub to rub away the filth from the sides. In the mean season this minion lover cast his wife on the bottom of the tub and had his pleasure with her over his head, and as he was in the middest of his pastime, he turned his head on this side and that side, finding fault with this and with that, till as they had both ended their business, when as he delivered seven pence for the tub, and caused the good man himself to carry it on his back again to his Inn.

The Fortieth Chapter

How Apuleius was handled by the Bakers wife, which was a harlot.

The Baker which bought me was an honest and sober man; but his wife was the most pestilent woman in all the world, insomuch that he endured many miseries and afflictions with her, so that I myself did secretly pity his estate, and bewaile his evill fortune: for she had not one fault alone, but all the mischiefes that could be devised: she was crabbed, cruell, lascivious, drunken, obstinate, niggish, covetous, riotous in filthy expenses, and an enemy to faith and chastity, a despise of all the Gods, whom other did honour, one that affirmed that she had a God by herself, wherby she deceived all men, but especially her poore husband, one that abandoned her body with continuall whoredome. This mischievous queane hated me in such sort, that she commanded every day before she was up, that I should be put into the mill to grind: and the first thing which she would do in the morning, was to see me cruelly beaten, and that I should grind when the other beasts did feed and take rest. When I saw that I was so cruelly handled, she gave me occasion to learne her conversation and life, for I saw oftentimes a yong man which would privily go into her chamber whose face I did greatly desire to see, but I could not by reason mine eyes were covered every day. And verily if I had beene free and at liberty, I would have discovered all her abhomination. She had an old woman, a bawd, a messenger of mischiefe that daily haunted to her house, and made good cheere with her to the utter undoing and impoverishment of her husband, but I that was greatly offended with the negligence of Fotis, who made me an Asse, in stead of a Bird, did yet comfort myself by this onely meane, in that to the miserable deformity of my shape, I had long eares, whereby I might heare all things that was done: On a day I heard the old bawd say to the Bakers wife:

Dame you have chosen (without my counsell) a young man to your lover, who as me seemeth, is dull, fearefull, without any grace, and dastard-like coucheth at the frowning looke of your odious husband, whereby you have no delight nor pleasure with him: how farre better is the young man Philesiterus who is comely, beautifull, in the flower of his youth, liberall, courteous, valiant and stout against the diligent pries and watches of your husband, whereby to embrace the worthiest dames of this country, and worthy to weare a crown of gold, for one part that he played to one that was jealous over his wife. Hearken how it was and then judge the diversity of these two Lovers: Know you not one Barbarus a Senator of our town, whom the vulgar people call likewise Scorpion for his severity of manners? This Barbarus had a gentlewoman to his wife, whom he caused daily to be enclosed within his house, with diligent custody. Then the Bakers wife said, I know her very well, for we two dwelleth together in one house: Then you know (quoth the old woman) the whole tale of Philesiterus? No verily (said she) but I greatly desire to know it: therefore I pray you mother tell me the whole story. By and by the old woman which knew well to babble, began to tell as followeth.

The Forty-Fifth Chapter

How Apuleius was sold to two brethren, whereof one was a Baker, and the other a Cook, and how finely and daintily he fared.

The Soldier that paid never a penny for me, by the commandment of his Captain was sent unto Rome, to carry Letters to the great Prince, and General of the Camp. Before he went, he sold me for eleven pence to two of his Companions, being Servants to a man of worship, whereof one was a Baker that baked sweet bread and delicates, the other a Cook, which dressed fine and excellent meats for his Master. These two lived in common, and would drive me from place to place, to carry such things as was necessary, insomuch that I was received by these two, as a third Brother, and Companion, and I thought I was never better placed, than with them: for when night came that Supper was done, and their business ended, they would bring many good morsels into their Chamber for themselves. One would bring Pigs, Chickens, fish, and other good meats, the other fine bread, pasties, tarts, custards and other delicate Junkets dipped in honey. And when they had shut their chamber door, and went to the baines: (Oh Lord) how I would fill my guts with these goodly dishes: neither was I so much a fool, or so very an Ass, to leave the dainty meats, and to grind my teeth upon hard hay. In this sort I continued a great space, for I played the honest Ass, taking but a little of one dish, and a little of another, whereby no man distrusted me. In the end, I was more hardier and began to devour the whole messes of the sweet delicates, which caused the Baker and the Cook to suspect, howbeit they nothing mistrusted me, but searched about to apprehend the thief. At length they began to accuse one another of theft, and to set the dishes and morsels of meat in order, one by another, because they would learn what was taken away, whereby one of them was compelled to say thus to his fellow: Is it reason to break promise and faith in this sort, by stealing away the best meat, and to sell it to augment thy good, and yet nevertheless to have thy part in the residue that is left: if our partnership do mislike thee, we will be partners and brothers in other things, but in this we will break of: for I perceive that the great loss which I sustain, will at length be a cause of great discord between us. Then answered the other, Verily I praise thy great constancy and subtleness, in that (when thou hast secretly taken away the meat) [thou] dost begin to complain first, whereas I by long space of time have suffered thee, because I would not seem to accuse my brother of theft, but I am right glad in that we are fallen into communication of the matter, least by our silence, like contention might arise between us, as fortuned between Eteocles and his Brother. When they had reasoned together in this sort, they swore both earnestly, that neither of them stole or took away any jot of the meat, wherefore they concluded to search out the Thief by all kind of means. For they could not imagine or think, the Ass who stood alone there, would eat any such meats, neither could they think that Mice or flies, were so ravenous, as to devour whole dishes of meat, like the Birds Harpies which carried away the meats of Phineus the King of Arcadia. In the Mean season while I was fed with dainty morsels, I gathered together my flesh, my skin waxed soft, my hair began to shine, and was gallant on every part, but such fair and comely shape of my body, was cause of my dishonour, for the Baker and Cook marvelled to see me so slick and fine, considering I did eat no hay at all. Wherefore on a time at their accustomed hour, they went to the baines, and locked their chamber door. It fortuned that ere they departed away, they espied me through a hole, how I fell roundly to my victuals: then they marvelled greatly, and little esteemed the loss of their meat, laughed exceedingly, calling the servants of the house, to show them the greedy gorge and appetite of the Ass. Their laughing was so immoderate that the master of the house heard them, and demanded the cause of their laughter, and when he understood all the matter, he looked through the hole likewise, wherewith he took such a delectation that he commanded the door to be opened, that he might see me at his pleasure. Then I perceiving every man laugh, was nothing abashed, but rather more bold, whereby I never rested eating, till such time as the master of the house commanded me to be brought into his parlor as a novelty, and there caused all kinds of meats which were never touched to be set on the table, which (although I had eaten sufficiently before, yet to win the further favour of the master of the house) I did greedily devour and made a clean riddance of all the delicate meats. And to prove my nature wholly, they gave met such meats as every Ass doth abhor: for they put before me beef and vinegar, birds and pepper, fish and verjuice: in the mean season they that beheld me at the table did nothing but laugh. Then one of the servants of the house said to his master, I pray you sir give him some drink to his supper: Marry (quoth he) I think thou saist true, for it may be, that to his meat he would drink likewise a cup of wine. Ho boy, wash yonder pot, and fill it with wine, which done, carry it to the Ass, and say that I have drunk to him. Then all the standers-by looked on, to see what would come to pass: but I (as soon as I beheld the cup) stayed not long, but gathering my lips together, supped up all the wine at one draught. The master being right joyful hereat caused the Baker and Cook which had bought me, to come before him, to whom he delivered four times as much for me, as they paid, which done he committed me to one of his rich Libertines, and charged him to look well to me, and that I should lack nothing, who obeyed his masters commandment in every point: and to the end he would creep further into his favour, he taught me a thousand qualities. First he instructed me to sit at the table upon my tail, and how I should leap and dance, holding up my former feet: moreover he taught me how I should answer when anybody spake unto me, with nodding my head, which was a strange and marvelous thing, and if I did lack drink, I should look still upon the pot. All which things I did willingly bring to pass, and obeyed his doctrine: howbeit, I could have done all these things without his teaching, but I feared greatly lest in showing myself cunning without a master, I should pretend some great and strange wonder, and thereby be thrown out to wild beasts. But my fame was spread about in every place, and the qualities which I could do, insomuch that my master was renowned throughout all the Country by reason of me. For every man would say: Behold the Gentleman that hath an Ass, that will eat and drink with him, that will dance, and understand what is said to him, will show his fantasy by signs. But first I will tell you (which I should have done before) who my master was, and of what country. His name was Thiasus, he was born at Corinth, which is a principal town of Achaea, and he had passed many offices of honor, till he had taken upon him the degree Quinquennial, according as his birth and dignity required, who to show his worthiness, and to purchase the benevolence of every person, appointed public joys and triumphs, to endure the space of three days, and to bring his endeavour to pass, he came into Thessaly to buy excellent Beasts, and valiant fighters for the purpose.

Chapter XVI

How Fotis brought Apuleius to see her mistress enchant.

On a day Fotis came running to me in great fear, and said that her mistress, to work her sorceries on such as she loved, intended the night following to transform herself into a bird, and to fly whither she pleased. Wherefore she willed me privily to prepare myself to see the same. And when midnight came she led me softly into a high chamber, and bid me look through the chink of a door: where first I saw how she put off all her garments, and took out of a certain coffer sundry kinds of boxes, of the which she opened one, and tempered the ointment therein with her fingers, and then rubbed her body therewith from the sole of the foot to the crown of the head, and when she had spoken privily with herself, having the candle in her hand, she shaked the parts of her body, and behold, I perceived a plume of feathers did burgeon out, her nose waxed crooked and hard, her nails turned into claws, and so she became an owl. Then she cried and screeched like a bird of that kind, and willing to prove her force, moved herself from the ground by little and little, till at last she flew quite away.

Thus by her sorcery she transformed her body into what shape she would. Which when I saw I was greatly astonied: and although I was enchanted by no kind of charm, yet I thought that I seemed not to have the likeness of Lucius, for so was I banished from my senses, amazed in madness, and so I dreamed waking, that I felt mine eyes, whether I were asleep or no. But when I was come again to myself, I took Fotis by the hand, and moved it to my face and said, I pray thee while occasion doth serve, that I may have the fruition of the fruits of my desire, and grant me some of this ointment. Oh Fotis I pray thee by thy sweet paps, to make that in the great flames of my love I may be turned into a bird, so I will ever hereafter be bound unto you, and obedient to your commandment. Then said Fotis, Will you go about to deceive me now, and enforce me to work my own sorrow? Are you in the mind that you will not tarry in Thessaly? If you be a bird, where shall I seek you, and when shall I see you? Then answered I, God forbid that I should commit such a crime, for though I could fly in the air as an eagle or though I were the messenger of Jupiter, yet would I have recourse to nest with thee: and I swear by the knot of thy amiable hair, that since the time I first loved thee, I never fancied any other person: moreover, this commeth to my mind, that if by the virtue of the ointment I shall become an owl, I will take heed I will come nigh no man’s house: for I am not to learn, how these matrons would handle their lovers, if they knew that they were transformed into owls: moreover, when they are taken in any place they are nailed upon posts, and so they are worthily rewarded, because it is thought that they bring evil fortune to the house. But I pray you (which I had almost forgotten) to tell me by what means when I am an owl, I shall return to my pristine shape, and become Lucius again. Fear not (quoth she) for my mistress hath taught me the way to bring that to pass, neither think you that she did it for any goodwill and favour, but to the end that I might help her, and minister some remedy when she returneth home.

Consider I pray you with yourself, with what frivolous trifles so marvelous a thing is wrought: for by Hercules I swear I give her nothing else save a little dill and laurel leaves, in well water, the which she drinketh and washeth herself withal. Which when she had spoken she went into the chamber and took a box out of the coffer, which I first kissed and embraced, and prayed that I might [have] good success in my purpose. And then I put off all my garments, and greedily thrust my hand into the box, and took out a good deal of ointment and rubbed myself withal.

Introduction

Apuleius—His Style—His Debt to Lucian—The Sermo Milesius—The Book’s Touch with Life—The Dramatis Personae—The Witches of Thessaly—Cupid and Psyche—The Macabre Element—Apuleius the Man—Autobioggraphy—His Apology—Modern Parallels—Adlington—His Purism—His simple Diction—Coined Words—The Imagery shirked—His rare Ornament—His Ignorance of Latin—The Ideal Translation—Adlington’s English—His Mastery of Phrase—His Sustained Rhythm—A Model of Prose—Two French Versions—Guillaume Michel—His Misleading of Adlington—Adlington the Man—His Morality—His Love of Allegory.

The Golden Ass of Apuleius is, so to say, a beginning of modern literature. From this brilliant medley of reality and romance, of wit and pathos, of fantasy and observation, was born that new art, complex in thought, various in expression, which gives a semblance of frigidity to perfection itself. An indefatigable youthfulness is its distinction. As it was fresh when Adlington translated it “out of Latine” three centuries since, so it is familiar today, and is like to prove an influence tomorrow. Indeed, it is among the marvels of history that an alien of twenty-five and Apuleius was no more when he wrote his Metamorphoses should have revolutionised a language not his own, and bequeathed us a freedom which, a thousand times abused, has never since been taken away.

A barbarian born, a Greek by education, Apuleius only acquired the Latin tongue by painful effort. Now, a foreigner, not prejudiced by an inveterate habit of speech, seldom escapes a curiosity of phrase. Where the language is the same, whether written or spoken, art is wont to lapse into nature. But there was no reason why Apuleius, who could not but be conscious of his diction, should ever deviate from artifice. His style, in truth, he put on as a garment, and it fitted the matter without a crease. His exotic vocabulary was the fruit of the widest research. He ransacked the ancient plays for long-forgotten words. He cared not where he picked up his neologisms, so they were dazzling and bizarre. Greece, his own Carthage, the gutters of Rome, contribute to the wealth of his diction, for he knew naught of that pedantry which would cramp expression for authority’s sake. The literary use of slang was almost his own invention. He would twist the vulgar words of every day into quaint, unheard-of meanings, nor did he ever deny shelter to those loafers and footpads of speech which inspire the grammarian with horror. On every page you encounter a proverb, a catchword, a literary allusion, a flagrant redundancy. One quality only was distasteful to him: the commonplace. He is ever the literary fop, conscious of his trappings and assured of a handsome effect. In brief, he belonged to the African School, for which elaboration was the first and last law of taste. He may even have been a pupil of Fronto, the prime champion of the elocutio novella, the rhetorician who condemned Cicero in that he was not scrupulous in his search for effect, and urged upon his pupils the use of insperata atque inopinata verba. No wonder poor Adlington, whose equipment of Latin was of the lightest, hesitated for a while! No wonder he complained that “the “Author had written his work in so darke and high a stile, “in so strange and absurd words, and in such new invented “phrases, as hee seemed rather to set it forth to show his “magnificencie of prose, than to participate his doings to “others’! But the difficulty is not invincible; and the adventurous have their reward. The prose sparkles with light and colour. Not a page but is rich inlaid with jewels of fantastic speech. For Apuleius realised centuries before Baudelaire that a vocabulary is a palette, and he employed his own with incomparable daring and extravagance.

Though his style be personal, the machinery of his story is frankly borrowed. The hero who, transformed by magic to an ass, recovers human shape by eating roses was no new invention. He had already supplied two writers with a motive ; and the learned have not decided whether it was from Lucian (so-called) or from Lucius of Patrae that Apuleius got his inspiration[1]. 1 But a comparison of the Latin, version with its Greek forerunner, commonly attributed to Lucian, proves the debt a feather’s weight. Whatever Apuleius conveyed, he so boldly changed and elaborated, as to make the material his own. His method is a miracle of simplicity. He accepts the Λοὐκιος ἣ Ὄνος as a framework, sometimes following it word for word, yet decorating it with so lavish an array of phrases, tricking it out with episodes so fertile and ingenious, as to force you to forget the original in the copy. Only in a single incident does his fancy lag behind. His hero’s interview with the serving-maid is chastened and curtailed. The professionally elaborate detail, wherewith Lucian enhances this famous episode, is touched by Apuleius with a light and summary hand. But elsewhere he appropriates to adorn. Though again and again the transference is verbal, the added ornament is entirely characteristic, and it is as unjust to charge the author with plagiarism as it were to condemn the Greek tragedians for their treatment of familiar themes. Indeed the two writers approach the matter from opposite points of view. Lucian’s austere concision is purely classical. He has a certain story to present, and he reaches the climax by the shortest possible route. The progress is interrupted neither by phrase nor interlude, and at the end you chiefly admire the cold elegance, wherewith the misfortunes of Lucius are expressed, so to say, in their lowest terms. Apuleius, on the other hand, is unrestrainedly romantic. He cares not how he loiters by the way ; he is always ready to beguile his reader with a Milesian story one of those quaint and witty interludes, which have travelled the world over, and become part, not merely of every literature, but of every life. Our new fashion of analysis, our ineradicable modesty, have at last denied them literary expression, and today they eke out a beggarly and formless existence by the aid of oral tradition. But time was they were respectable as well as joyous. What reproach is attached to the Widow of Ephesus, who has wandered from Petronius even unto Rabelais? To what admirable purpose is the Sermo Milesius handled in the Decamerone, to which Apuleius himself contributed one delectable tale! Did not the genius of Balzac devise a monument proper to its honourable antiquity in the Contes Drolatiques? And yet the second century was its golden age, and none so generously enhanced its repute as Apuleius. His masterpiece, in truth, is magnificently interlaced with jests, sometimes bound to the purpose of the story by the thinnest of thin threads, more often attached merely for their own or for ornament’s sake. But not only thus is he separate from his model. Though he is romantic in style and temper alike and romanticism is an affair of treatment rather than of material he never loses touch with actuality. He wrote with an eye upon the realities of life. Observation was a force more potent with him than tradition. If his personages and incidents are wholly imaginary, he could still give them a living semblance by a touch of intimacy or a suggestion of familiar detail. Compare his characters to Lucian’s, and measure the gulf between the two! Lucian’s Abroea is a warning voice that, and no more. Byrrhena, on the other hand, is a great lady, sketched, with a quick perception of her kind, centuries before literature concerned itself with the individual. And is not Milo, the miser, leagues nearer the possibility of life than Hipparchus? Even Palaestra, despite the ingenuity of one episode, is not for an instant comparable in charm and humour to Fotis, most complaisant of servingmaids. Nor is it only in the portrayal of character that Apuleius proves his observation. There are many scenes whose truthful simplicity is evidence of experience. When Lucius, arrived in Hypata, goes to the market to buy him fish, he encounters an old fellow-student Pythias by name already invested with the authority and insignia of an aedile. Now he, being a veritable jack-in-office, is enraged that Lucius has made so ill a bargain, and overturning his fish, bids his attendants stamp it under foot, so that the traveller loses supper and money too. The incident is neither apposite nor romantic ; it is no more Milesian than mystical ; but it bears the very pressure of life, and you feel that it was transferred straight from a notebook. Again, where shall you find a franker piece of realism than the picture of the mill, whereto the luckless Ass was bound? Very ugly and evil-favoured were the men, covered only with ragged clouts ; and how horrible a spectacle the horses, with their raw necks, their hollow flanks, their broken ribs!

The Greek author, disdaining atmosphere, is content to set out his incidents in a logical sequence. Apuleius has enveloped his world of marvels in a heavy air of witchery and romance. You wander with Lucius across the hills and through the dales of Thessaly. With all the delight of a fresh curiosity you approach its far-seen towns. You journey at midnight under the stars, listening in terror for the howling of the wolves, or the stealthy ambush. At other whiles, you sit in the robbers 1 cave, and hear the ancient legends of Greece retold. The spring comes on, and “the little birds chirp“ and sing their steven melodiously.” 1 Secret raids, ravished brides, valiant rescues, the gayest of intrigues these are the diverse matters of this many-coloured book. The play of fancy, the variety of style, the fertility of resource are inexhaustible. Mythology is lifted into life, and life itself transformed to mystery at the wizard’s touch. The misery and terror of the Ass’s life are intercepted by the story of Cupid and Psyche, set forth with rare beauty and distinction of Cupid and style. And yet this interlude, exquisitely planned and Psyche phrased, which suggested a worthless play[2] to Tom Heywood, and has been an inspiration to many poets from Mrs. Tighe to Mr. Bridges, is the one conspicuous fault of the book. Admirable in itself, it is out of proportion as well as out of key, and though you turn to it again and again for its own sake, you skip it industriously when it keeps you from robbery and witchcraft. But the most remarkable characteristic of The Golden Ass is the ever-present element of sorcery, of the Macabre as Mr. Pater calls it. Grim spectres and horrid ghosts stalk through its pages. The merriest Milesian jest turns sudden to the terror of death and corruption. The very story which Boccaccio borrowed is shifted by Apuleius to a weird conclusion. The baker, having most wittily avenged his wife’s deceit, is lured into a chamber by a meagre, ragged, ill-favoured woman, her hair scattering upon her face, and when the servants burst open the door to find their master, behold! no woman, but only the baker hanging from a rafter dead! And where for pure horror will you match Meroe’s mutilation of Socrates? Secretly the witch attacks him in his sleep, drives her sword deep into his neck, and dragging out his heart, stops the wound with a sponge. Aristomenes, unwilling witness of the cruelty, half believes it a dream, and gladly they resume the journey, until, when Socrates goes to the river to drink, the sponge falls out and with it the last, faint pulse of life. Again, when Thelyphron watches in the chamber of the dead, lest witches should bite off morsels of the dead man’s face, and, falling asleep at sight of a weasel, loses his ears and nose, who so callous as to feel no shudder of alarm? But the most terrific apparition of all is the obscene priest of the Syrian Goddess, with his filthy companions carrying the Divine Image from village to village, and clanging their cymbals to call the charitable. This grimy episode, with its sequent orgies, is related with an incomparably full humour which, despite its Oriental barbarity, is unmatched in literature.

Indeed there is scarce a scene without its ghostly enchantment, its supernatural intervention. And herein you may detect the personal predilection of Apuleius. The infinite curiosity wherewith Lucius pries into witchcraft and sorcery was shared by his author. The hero transformed suffered his many and grievous bufFetings because he always coveted an understanding of wizardry and spells ; and Apuleius, in an age devoted to mysticism, was notorious for a magicmonger. Seriously it was debated, teste St. Augustine, whether Christ or he wrought the greater marvels: and though the shape wherein the romance is cast induced a confusion of author and hero, it is recorded that Apuleius was a zealous magician, and doubtless it is himself, not Lucius, he pictures in his last book among the initiate. In the admirable description of Isis and her visitation, as of the ceremonies wherein he was admitted to the secret worship of the Goddess, he departs entirely from his Greek original. Here, indeed, we have a fragment of autobiography. When in 158 AD, at the dramatic moment of an adventurous career, Apuleius delivered his Apology—pro se de magia before Claudius Maximus, he confessed that he had been initiated into all the sacred rites of Greece, and had squandered the better part of a comfortable fortune in mysticism and the grand tour. The main accusation was that he had won his wife a respectable and wealthy widow by magic arts. He was also charged with other acts of witchcraft and enchantment. Thattus, it was said, and a freeborn woman had swooned in his presence: a piece of superstition which reminds you of Cotton Mather. But, replied Apuleius, with excellent humour and a scepticism worthy of Reginald Scot, they were epileptics, who could stand in the presence of none save a magician. In brief, we cannot appreciate The Golden Ass, until we realise the modern spirit of curiosity which possessed its author. The lecturer’s fame well-nigh outran the writer’s. Apuleius travelled the length of civilised Africa with his orations, as the popular lecturer of today invades America; and the Majesty of ^Esculapius, a favourite subject, was an excellent occasion for his familiar mysticism. He had been as intimately at home in the nineteenth century as in the second. Were he alive today Paris would have been his field, and he the undisputed master of Decadence and Symbolism. The comparison is close at all points. Would he not have delighted in the Black Mass, as celebrated on the heights of Mont Paniasse? Like too many among the makers of modern French literature he was an alien writing an alien tongue. His curiosity of diction, his unfailing loyalty to speech, his eager search after the strange and living word, his love of an art which knows no concealment these qualities proclaim the Decadent. And that Symbolist is wayward indeed who finds not matter for his fancy in the countless stories, which a perverse ingenuity has twisted a hundred times into allegory.

Such the author and his book. And when William Adlington, in the untried youth of English prose, undertook the translation of The Golden Asse, you would have thought no apter enterprise possible. Primitive and Decadent approach art in the same temper. Each is of necessity inclined to Euphuism. In the sixteenth century the slang, the proverb, the gutter phrase, which Apuleius brought back to the Latin tongue were not yet sifted from English by the pedantry of scholars. But William Adlington, though an Elizabethan, was something of a purist. To be sure, he was unable to purge his diction of colour and variety, and his manner was far better suited to the rendering of Apuleius than the prose of today, which has passed through the sieve of the eighteenth century. But with an excellent modesty he pleads acceptance for his“ simple translation. ‘* Though he applauds the “franke and“ flourishing stile ‘” of his author,“ as he seems to have the “ Muses at his will to feed and maintains his pen,” 1 he uses of deliberation“ more common and familiar words “ the phrase proves the essential recognition of his own style “fearing lest“ the book should appear very obscure and darke, and thereby “ consequently loathsome to the reader.” Indeed, he elected to translate the one book of the world which demanded the free employment of strange terms, and set himself incontinent to avoid slang and to simplify redundancies. And his restraint is the more unexpected when you recall the habit of contemporary translators. Barnaby Rich studded Herodotus thick with colloquialisms and fresh-minted words. Philemon Holland made no attempt to chasten his vocabulary. But Adlington, his opportunity being the higher, fell the more marvellously below it. For the most part, then, you will ransack his version in vain for obsolete words or exotic flowers of speech. And yet not even his love of simplicity has kept his vocabulary entirely pure. Again and again a coined phrase, a strange form shows, like a dash of colour, upon his page. “ The roperipe boy “ thus he renders puer ille peremptor meus by a happy inspiration, which Apuleius himself might envy. Fresh and unhackneyed is “ the gleed “ of the sun” 1 for jubaris orbe. How exquisitely does “a * swathell of red silke “ represent russea fasceola! “ Traffe or “ baggage “ is more pleasantly picturesque than sarcinam vel laciniam, and one’s heart rejoices to hear a churl styled *a “ rich chuff’e.” Again, “ ungles “ is far more expressive, if less common, than “claws”; and who would write “niggardly” when “ niggish “ is ready to his hand? And is not “ a carraine “ stinke “ a high-sounding version of fetore nimio? To encounter so sturdy and wholesome a phrase as “ I smelling his “ crafty and subtle fetch “ though it be a poor echo of ego perspiciens malum istum verberonem blaterantem et inconcinne causificantem—is to regret the impoverishment of our English tongue. But not often are we rejoiced by the unexpected, and for the most part Adlington is a scrupulous critic of his diction. As he makes no attempt to represent in English his author’s vocabulary, so is he wont to shirk the imagery, and curtail the redundancy affected by Apuleius, repressing the hyperbolical ostentations of his original, save only when he indulges in exaggerations of his own. When the miserable Thelyphron is protecting a dead man from the witch women, thus does Apuleius, with his admirable sense of words, enhance the horror of crawling minutes: cum ecce crepusculum et nox provecta et nox altior et dein concubia altiora; et jam nox intempesta for which Adlington writes in all brevity 'midnight.' 1 Apuleius again has a dozen fantastical notions of the dawn, and Adlington cuts them all down to the colourless level of “when morning“ was come/ Thus even does he reduce so garishly purple a piece of imagery as: Commodum punicantibus phaleris Aurora roseum quatiens lacertum caelum inequitabat. When the thieves return to their den after the sack of Mile’s house, and sit them down to revelry, Apuleius surpasses even his own habit of opulent description. Estur ac potatur—thus he writes incondite pulmentis acervatim, panibus aggeratim, poculis agminatim ingestis. “Cups in battalions!“ ’Tis a pretty conceit, and for Adlington it means no more than “ they drank and eat exceedingly. 1 But having accustomed you to a chaste severity of language, he will break out suddenly into a decorative passage, for which the Latin gives no warrant. “Moreover there be diverse that will cast off “ their partlets, collars, habiliments, fronts, cornets, and krip” pins’ ”: thus he turns a perfectly simple sentence lacinias omnes eocuunt^ amicula dimovent—proving his quietude of phrase the effect of design rather than of necessity. So also he is wont to clip and crop his author’s metaphors. “While I considered these things“ is a withered, nerveless rendering of cum isto cogitationis solo luctuarem; yet is it entirely characteristic of his method. Indeed, from beginning to end he treats his author with the freest hand, and never permits the form and colour of the Latin to interrupt his conception of English prose.

But if he sacrificed something by too scrupulous a restraint, he sacrificed still more by his scanty knowledge of Latin. Scholarship was as little fashionable in Tudor England as pedantry, the defect corresponding to its quality; and Adlington laid no claim to profound erudition. He did but purpose “according to his slender knowledge (though “it were rudely, and farre disagreeing from the fine and“ excellent doings now-adayes),” to translate “the delectable“ j easts of Lucius Apuleius into our vulgar tongue. 1 Nor is the confession of “slender knowledge“ a mere parade of modesty: it is wholly justified by the event. To compile a list of errors were superfluous. In truth there is no page without its blunder, though, as we shall presently see, the translator commonly manages to tumble not only into sense but into distinction. Now and again the mistakes are so serious as to pervert the meaning, and then one regrets that Adlington was not more wisely guided. For instance, the servants of Philebus, the priest of the Syrian Goddess, are called puella by Apuleius in contempt of their miserable profession, and the translator impenetrably obscures the episode by rendering the word “daughters’ without a hint of explanation. Still, all are not so grave, though you are constantly driven to wonder at the ingenuity of error. When Byrrhena, in her panegyric of Hypata, tells Lucius that there the merchant may encounter the bustle of Rome, the quiet visitor enjoy the peace of a country-house, Adlington thus heroically misses the mark: “When the 4 Roman merchants arrive in this city they are gently and 4 quietly entertained, and all that dwell within this province 4 (when they purpose to solace and repose themselves) do come * to this city! “ Verily there is magnificence (of a kind) in such confusion ; and how shall one reproach a translator, upon whom accuracy sets so light a burden? Again, with a sublime recklessness Adlington perverts extorta dentibus ferarum trunca calvaria into “ the jawbones and teeth of 4 wilde beasts, 1 not pausing to consider the mere formality of grammatical concord. And when Fotis relates how Pamphile, having failed to advance her suit by other arts (quod nihil etiam tune in suos amores ceteris artibus promoveref), designs to assume the shape and feathers of a bird, Adlington so carelessly confounds cause and effect as to say that the transformation was intended “ to worke her sorceries on such 4 as she loved. Tune solus ignoras longe faciliores ad expugnandum domus esse majores? asks one of the robbers; and Adlington, with the twisted cleverness of a fourth form boy, extorts therefrom this platitude: “ Why are you only “ ignorant that the greater the number is, the sooner they may 4 rob and spoil the house? “ When one of Psyche’s wicked sisters threatens to go hang herself if Psyche prove the mother of a god (si divini puelli—quod absit—haec mater audierit, statim me laqueo nexili suspendam), “ if it be a divine * babe, 1 says the sister in the translation, “ and fortune to 4 come to the ears of the mother (as God forbid it should) 4 then may I go and hang my selfe”: thus ignorant was our Englishman of the commonest idiom. Once, at the marriage of Charite good fortune seemed to wait upon the Ass, and his mistress promised him hay enough for a Bactrian camel (faenum camelo Bactrinae sufficiens): a promise misinterpreted by a masterpiece of grotesquerie into “she would call me her“ little cam ell. 1 With his very easy baggage of Latin, the translator lost the point of every Sprichwort, and turned the literary allusion into nonsense. In the phrase non cervam pro virgine sed hominem pro homine, the reference to Iphigenia is patent, and yet our excellent Adlington gets no nearer the truth than “ not a servant for his maidens, “but rather an Asse for himselfe.’

So much must be said in dispraise of what after all is a masterpiece of prose. The translator, said Dr. Johnson, “ is * to exhibit his author’s thoughts in such a dress as the author “ would have given them had his language been English.” Now, Adlington has failed, with the rest of the world, to reach this high standard. Under no conceivable circumstances could Apuleius have written in his terms and with his significance. For the perfect translation a knowledge of two languages is necessary. The modern translator is commonly endowed with a complete apprehension of Latin or Greek, and is withal lamentably ignorant of English. Adlington, on the other hand, was sadly to seek in Latin, but he more than atoned for his slender knowledge by an admirable treatment of his own language. Though he abandoned the colour and variety of Apuleius, he turned his author into as handsome a piece of prose as you are like to meet. From the first page to the last you will not find a trace of foreign idiom. The result is not so much a fine translation as a noble original, fitted to endure by its vigorous diction and excellent rhythm. The manner j s perfectly adapted to narration, and there are few can handle a story with better delicacy and point. The style, if simple for its age, has all the distinction of simplicity. The cadences are a perpetual pleasure to the ear. There is a stateliness, a dignity of effect, which proves that the prose of the Authorised Version was no invention, but a growth. Though Adlington does not pretend to echo the locutions of Apuleius, he is, after his own method, a master of phrase, “ Girded with her beautiful skarfe of love 1 is it not an exquisite idea? How more nearly or more adroitly would you turn tamen nisi capillum distinxerit than in these terms: “ if her hair be not curiously set forth “? If only the modern translator dared to represent ementita lassititdo by “ feigned “ and coloured weariness, 1 there were hope that his craft might rise above journey-work. Who would complain that the original was embroidered when it is to such admirable purpose as: “ Thus she cried and lamented, and after “ she had wearied herself with sorrow and blubbered her “ face with teares, she closed the windows of her hollow eyes, “ and laid her down to sleep. 1 Here is prose, ever vivid and alert, ever absolved from the suspicion of the stereotyped phrase. In Adlington’s day “good taste 1 had not banned freshness and eccentricity from the language. A century later it had been impossible to translate glebosa camporum into “ cloggy, fallowed fields “ ; yet this is Adlington’s expression, and it may be matched or bettered on every page. Above all, his work is distinguished by that sustained nobility of rhythm which makes the Tudor prose the best of good reading. “ And while I considered these things, I “ looked about, and behold I saw a farre off a shadowed “ valley adjoyning nigh unto a wood, where amongst diverse ” other hearbes and pleasant verdures, me thought I saw ; diverse flourishing Roses of bright damaske colour ; and said “ within my beastiall mind, Verily that place is the place of “ Venus and the Graces, where secretly glistereth the royall “ hew, of so lively and delectable a floure“: here are no exotic words, no long-sought images ; the rare effect is attained by a harmony, which not even the sternest simplicity can impoverish. Or take a passage in another key: * In the meane “ season while I was fed with dainty morsels, I gathered “ together my flesh, my skin waxed soft, my haire began to “ shine, and was gallant on every part, but such faire and “ comely shape of my body, was cause of my dishonour, for the “ Baker and Cooke marvelled to see me so slick and fine, con4 sidering I did eat no hay at all/ True, the word “ slick “ (aptly suggested by nitore) is, so to say, a high light ; but the beauty still depends upon the rhythm, to which Adlington’s ear is ever attuned. In brief, whatever defects of scholarship and restraint mar the translation, it remains a model of that large, untrammelled prose which, before the triumph of common sense, seemed within the reach of all. But is it not the strangest paradox of literary history that they who lived in the golden age of translation sought their original at second hand, or fumbled for their meaning in the dark?

One advantage at least was enjoyed by Adlington. He studied Apuleius in the native Latin, using, we may believe, the famous folio of 1500 (cum Beroaldi commentariis), prefaced by that Vita Lucii Apuleii summatim relata, which he paraphrased in English with his accustomed inaccuracy. Howbeit, he did not “ so exactly pass through the author, * as to point every sentence according as it is in Latine“: for so, he adds, “the French and Spanish translators have “ not done. 1 Nor is there any doubt that he attempted to amend his ignorance of Latin by the aid of a French version. It is some proof of the early popularity of The Golden Ass that Spain, Italy, and France had each its translation into the vulgar tongue, before Adlington undertook the work. In 1522 there appeared a tiny quarto Versions bearing this legend upon its titlepage: “Lucius Apuleius “ de Lasne dore … On les vend a Paris en la grand “ rue St. Jacques, Par Philippe le noir. It was by one Guillaume Michel ; and though before the English translation was a-making there had appeared another version by Georges de la Bouthiere (Lyons, 1553), adorned with cuts in the manner of Bernard Salmon, the earlier book was a guide, and too often a blind guide, unto Adlington’s footsteps. The Frenchman, indeed, was the riper scholar, but not only did ne indulge the tiresome habit of commenting by the way, and without warning, upon his text, but he was also guilty of the most ingenious blunders, which Adlington, as though his own errors were no t sufficient, too readily followed. A comparison of the versions sets the matter beyond uncertainty. If again and again the same inaccuracy glares in English and French, it is obvious that the one was borrowed from the other. At the very outset there is a clear clue. Guillaume Michel, according to his habit of expansion, paraphrases haec me suadente in half a dozen lines; and Adlington, turning his invigilant eye from the Latin, is guilty of the like unwarranted prolixity. Moreover, when Apuleius by a quip says of Meroe, sic reapse nomen ejus tune Jubulis Socratis convenlre sentiebam, you are puzzled by the ingenuity of Adlington’s rendering 1: “being so named because “ she was a Taverner,” until you turn to the French and find in taverniere the source of error. Again, Diophanes, the magician in Milo’s story, is consulted by a certain merchant, Cerdo by name. (The Latin is unmistakable: Cerdo quidam nomine negotiator.) Now, Adlington boldly translates “a “ certaine Cobler,” 2 and instantly the Frenchman’s quelque savatier explains the blunder. Toutfoys mon cheval et tautre beste lasne de Milo ne me voulurent souffrir avec eulx paistre: so Michel at the beginning of the Fourth Book. And thus Adlington: “ but myne own horse and Miloes Asse * would not suffer me to feed there with them, but I must seeke * my dinner in some other place.” 3 The renderings agree precisely in a gross inaccuracy, and the Latin nec me cum asino vel equo meo compascuus coetus attinere potuit adhuc insolitum alioquin prandere foenum is involved enough to explain Adlington’s reliance upon the French. Another passage * is even more convincing. Ad quandam villam possessoris beati pervemunt, writes Apuleius, whom Adlington translates: l we fortuned to come to one Britunis house “ 4 ; nor would it appear who this Britunis might be, unless you turned to Michel’s French and read, en aucun village chiez ung riche laboureur nomme Brulinus. This strange correspondence in error might be enforced by countless examples. But by this it is evident that, although Adlington did not, like Angell Day, Sir Thomas North, George Nichols (translator of Thucydides), render his author from the French openly and without shame, he consulted the French as well as the Latin, and fared rather the worse therefor.

If for a judgment of Adlington the writer there is ample material, of Adlington the man we know nothing more than he vouchsafes himself. That six editions appeared in some seventy years is proof of the book’s popularity. But its only mention is in the Register of the Stationers’ 1 Company, where it figures “ In the enterynge of Coopyes “ between the 22nd July 1565 and the 22nd July 1566 something earlier than the date of the dedication. “Wekes. Recevyd of henry wekes,“ thus it runs, “for his lycense for pryntinge of a boke intituled the hole boke of lucious apelious of ye golden asse, viijd.“ The epistle dedicatory to Thomas, Earle of Sussex, is dated “from University College in Oxenford, the “xviii. of September, 1566[3].” But whether or no he was a graduate of that seat of learning is still uncertain. His name does not appear in the Register of the University, and in vain you consult the common sources of information. He presents his book to his patron in the customary terms of extravagant eulogy:“ The which if your honourable Lordship “ shall accept, 1 writes he of his Apuleius, “ and take in good “ part, I shall not only thinke my small travell and labour “ well employed, but shall also receive a further comfort to “ attempt some more serious matter.” 1 If the serious matter were ever attempted, its very gravity has sunk it out of knowledge: unless, indeed, he be the author of that very rare and exceeding obvious tract in verse, entitled, A Speciall Remedie against the force of lawlesse Love [4]. 1 This was published in 1579, and ascribed upon the titlepage to W. A. As the agreement of name and date is perfect, so also the tone of the preface corresponds precisely with Adlington’s admonition to the reader of The Golden Asse. When the “ friendly Reader “ of the Speciall Remedie is warned how “ like unto a beast love transformeth a man, during the which “ nothing can be exercised in minde, nothing by reason or 4 study of minde can be done,” 1 you are forthwith reminded of Adlington and of Lucius changed to an ass. The verses are properly forgotten, but by his own confession we know him subject to an invincible morality which, ill according with his century, drove him perchance to undertake this enterprise gloomy enough for oblivion. Lector intende: laetaberis such is the bidding of Apuleius. And Adlington apologises that “ although the matter seeme very light and merry, “ yet the effect thereof tendeth to a good and vertuous moral,” 12 just as the author of the Speciall Remedie remarks with Plinie, “ there is no book so simple, but that therein is some” what worthy the noating.’ 1 As though the Milesian Tale were judged, not by its pleasantry and delight, but by the quality of its moral sustenance! But Adlington was of those who would allegorise both mythology and romance. “ The f a }} o f Icarus is an example to proud and arrogant “ persons, that weeneth to climbe up to the heavens “ ; and further, he holds that “ by Mydas is carped the foul sin of “ Avarice/ 1 And, as if to excuse the translation of a * meere “ jeast and fable,” he addresses to the reader a most solemn homily, setting forth the example of Nebuchadnezzar and upholding the efficacy of prayer. * Verily under the wrap of this transformation is taxed the life of mortall men,” thus he writes in the proper spirit of the divine; concluding that “ we can never bee restored to the right figure of our selves, “ except we taste and eat the sweet Rose of reason and vertue, * which the rather by mediation of praier we may assuredly “ attained 2 Nor is this the mere perversion of ingenuity. His prudery is perfectly sincere. In many places he is inclined, by a modest suppression, to mitigate the gaiety of the Apuleian narrative. But only once does he completely sacrifice his author’s effect to his own scruples ; and the restrained nobility of his prose more than atones for lack of scholarship and a prudish habit of mind. The lapse of three centuries has left his book as fresh and living as its original, and withal as brave a piece of narrative as the literature of his century has to show.

Charles Whibley.

The Life of Lucius Apuleius
Briefly Described

Lucius Apuleius African, an excellent follower of Plato his sect, born in Madaura, a country sometime inhabited by the Romans, and under the jurisdiction of Syphax, situate and lying on the borders of Numidia and Getulia, whereby he calleth himself half a Numidian and half a Getulian: and Sidonius named him the Platonian Madaurence: his father called Theseus had passed all offices of dignity in his country with much honour. His mother named Salvia was of such excellent virtue, that she passed all the Dames of her time, born of an ancient house, and descended from the philosopher Plutarch, and Sextus his nephew. His wife called Prudentila was endowed with as much virtue and riches as any woman might be. He himself was of an high and comely stature, gray eyed, his hair yellow, and a beautiful personage. He flourished in Carthage in the time of Iolianus Avitus and Cl. Maximus Proconsuls, where he spent his youth in learning the liberal sciences, and much profited under his masters there, whereby not without cause he calleth himself the nurse of Carthage, and the celestial Muse and venerable mistress of Africke. Soon after, at Athens (where in times past the well of all doctrine flourished) he tasted many of the cups of the Muses, he learned the poetry, geometry, music, logic, and the universal knowledge of philosophy, and studied not in vain the nine Muses, that is to say, the nine noble and royal disciplines.

Immediately after he went to Rome, and studied there the Latin tongue, with such labour and continual study, that he achieved to great eloquence, and was known and approved to be excellently learned, whereby he might worthily be called polyhistor, that is to say, one that knoweth much or many things.

And being thus no less endued with eloquence, than with singular learning, he wrote many books for them that should come after: whereof part by negligence of times be now intercepted and part now extant, do sufficiently declare, with how much wisdom and doctrine he flourished, and with how much virtue he excelled amongst the rude and barbarous people. The like was Anacharsis amongst the most luskish Scythes. But amongst the Books of Lucius Apuleius, which are perished and prevented, howbeit greatly desired as nowadays, one was entitled Banqueting questions, another entreating of the nature of fish, another of the generation of beasts, another containing his Epigrams, another called “Hermagoras”: but such as are now extant are the four books named Floridorum, wherein is contained a flourishing style, and a savory kind of learning, which delighteth, holdeth, and rejoiceth the reader marvelously; wherein you shall find a great variety of things, as leaping one from another: one excellent and copious oration, containing all the grace and virtue of the art oratory, where he cleareth himself of the crime of art magic, which was slanderously objected against him by his adversaries, wherein is contained such force of eloquence and doctrine, as he seemeth to pass and excel himself. There is another book of the god of the spirit of Socrates, whereof St. Augustine maketh mention in his book of the definition of spirits, and description of men. Two other books of the opinion of Plato, wherein is briefly contained that which before was largely expressed. One book of cosmography, comprising many things of Aristotle’s meteors. The Dialogue of Trismegistus, translated by him out of Greek into Latin, so fine, that it rather seemeth with more eloquence turned into Latin, than it was before written in Greek. But principally these eleven Books of the Golden Ass, are enriched with such pleasant matter, with such excellency and variety of flourishing tales, that nothing may be more sweet and delectable, whereby worthily they may be entitled The Books of the Golden Ass, for the passing style and matter therein. For what can be more acceptable than this ass of gold indeed. Howbeit there be many who would rather entitle it Metamorphosis, that is to say, a transfiguration or transformation, by reason of the argument and matter therein.

To the Right Honourable and Mighty Lord,
Thomas Earl of Sussex,
Viscount Fitzwalter, Lord of Egremont and of Burnell, Knight of the Most Noble Order of the Garter, Justice of the Forests and Chases from Trent Southward; Captain of the Gentleman Pensioners of the House of the Queen Our Sovereign Lady

After that I had taken upon me (right Honourable) in manner of that unlearned and foolish Poet, Choerilus, who rashly and unadvisedly wrought a big volume in verses, of the valiant prowess of Alexander the Great, to translate this present book, containing the Metamorphosis of Lucius Apuleius; being moved thereunto by the right pleasant pastime and delectable matter therein; I eftsoones consulted with myself, to whom I might best offer so pleasant and worthy a work, devised by the author, it being now barbarously and simply framed in our English tongue. And after long deliberation had, your honourable lordship came to my remembrance, a man much more worthy, than to whom so homely and rude a translation should be presented. But when I again remembered the jesting and sportful matter of the book, unfit to be offered to any man of gravity and wisdom, I was wholly determined to make no Epistle Dedicatory at all; till as now of late persuaded thereunto by my friends, I have boldly enterprised to offer the same to your Lordship, who as I trust will accept the same, than if it did entreat of some serious and lofty matter, light and merry, yet the effect thereof tendeth to a good and virtuous moral, as in the following Epistle to the reader may be declared. For so have all writers in times past employed their travel and labours, that their posterity might receive some fruitful profit by the same. And therefore the poets feigned not their fables in vain, considering that children in time of their first studies, are very much allured thereby to proceed to more grave and deep studies and disciplines, whereas their minds would quickly loath the wise and prudent works of learned men, wherein in such unripe years they take no spark of delectation at all. And not only that profit ariseth to children by such feigned fables, but also the virtues of men are covertly thereby commended, and their vices discommended and abhorred. For by the fable of Acteon, where it is feigned that he saw Diana washing herself in a well, he was immediately turned into an Hart, and so was slain of his own Dogs; may be meant, That when a man casteth his eyes on the vain and soon fading beauty of the world, consenting thereto in his mind, he seemeth to be turned into a brute beast, and so to be slain by the inordinate desire of his own affects. By Tantalus that stands in the midst of the flood Eridan, having before him a tree laden with pleasant apples, he being nevertheless always thirsty and hungry, betokeneth the insatiable desires of covetous persons. The fables of Atreus, Thiestes, Tereus and Progne signifieth the wicked and abominable facts wrought and attempted by mortal men. The fall of Icarus is an example to proud and arrogant persons, that weeneth to climb up to the heavens. By Midas, who obtained of Bacchus, that all things which he touched might be gold, is carped the foul sin of avarice. By Phaeton, that unskillfully took in hand to rule the chariot of the Sun, are represented those persons which attempt things passing their power and capacity. By Castor and Pollux, turned into a sign in heaven called Gemini, is signified, that virtuous and godly persons shall be rewarded after life with perpetual bliss. And in this feigned jest of Lucius Apuleius is comprehended a figure of man’s life, ministering most sweet and delectable matter, to such as shall be desirous to read the same. The which if your honourable lordship shall accept and take in good part, I shall not only think my small travel and labour well employed, but also receive a further comfort to attempt some more serious matter, which may be more acceptable to your Lordship: desiring the same to excuse my rash and bold enterprise at this time, as I nothing doubt of your Lordships goodness. To whom I beseech Almighty God to impart long life, with increase of much honour.

From University College in Oxenford, the xviij of September, 1566.

Your Honours most bounden,

Wil. Adlington.

Endnotes

That the hero transformed to an ass was the motive of two Greek romances can hardly be doubted after Photius’ statement. The one, he says, was the work of Lucius of Patrae (who wrote μεταμορφώσεων λόγους διαφόρους), the other the work of Lucian. The Λοὐκιος ἣ Ὄνος preserved in the works of Lucian, is doubtless one of the romances known to Photius. But its style and impartiality never for an instant suggest Lucian, who would have made the metamorphosis a peg for satire. And modern scholars are for the most part agreed that Lucian was not the author. Other considerations prevent our assigning it to Lucius, who, it is said, ran to a greater length, and it would be difficult to set forth the story in briefer terms than are employed by the author of Λοὐκιος ἣ Ὄνος. Probably it is the work of neither, though it may well be the romance attributed to Lucian by Photius. The only sure fact is that in the Λοὐκιος ἣ Ὄνος are to be found the dry bones of The Golden Ass. The curious may consult Professor Rohde’s Ueber Luciarfs Schrift Λοὐκιος ἣ Ὄνος und ihr Verhaeltniss zu Lucius von Patrae und den Metamorphosen des Apuleius. ↩

Loves Mistress: or, the Queens Masque. As it was three times presented before their two Excellent Majesties, within the space of eight days. In the presence of sundry foreign Ambassadors. 1636. ↩

The first edition was “imprinted at London in Fleet street at the sign of the Oliphant by Henry Wykes, Anno 1566.” Other editions appeared in 1571, 1582 (the rarest), 1596, 1600, 1639. ↩

The full title runs thus: “A Special Remedy Against the Furious Force of Lawless Love. And also, a true description of the same. With other delightful devices of dainty delights to pass away idle time, with pleasure and profit. Newly compiled in English verse by W. A. Imprinted by Richard Ihones, and are to be sold at his shop over against S. Sepulchres Church without Newgate. 1579.” The tract, which is unique, was found in the Evidence Room in Northumberland House, and reprinted in 1844 by the Roxburghe Society. ↩